<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wisconsin Weed Science on Wisconsin Weed Science</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Wisconsin Weed Science on Wisconsin Weed Science</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 WiscWeeds</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>2018 Wisconsin Cropping Systems Weed Science Survey - Where are we at?</title>
      <link>/post/2018-wisconsin-cropping-systems-weed-science-survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-wisconsin-cropping-systems-weed-science-survey/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist) and&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/maxwelco&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Maxwel Oliveira&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Postdoctoral Research Associate)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objective of our survey was to evaluate the main weed species and management strategies adopted in Wisconsin cropping systems, particularly in corn and soybeans. The survey was conducted this winter during the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ipcm.wisc.edu/blog/2017/12/2018-wisconsin-agronomy-update-meetings/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2018 Wisconsin Agronomy Update Meetings&lt;/a&gt;, held across the state. A total of 286 respondents, representing 54 counties, completed the survey. Herein we present a summary of the main survey results with the hope these may help stakeholders with management decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;primary-role-of-survey-respondents&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Primary role of survey respondents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agronomists and farmers were the main participants in our survey.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 WI survey/Figure 1. survey respondents.png&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Figure 1. Bla&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;crops-managed-by-survey-respondents&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crops managed by survey respondents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corn, soybeans, alfalfa and wheat, respectively, are the main crops managed by survey respondents.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 WI survey/Figure 2. crops managed.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 2&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;adoption-of-tillage&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adoption of tillage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tillage is a common practice in Wisconsin cropping systems according to survey respondents.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 WI survey/Figure 3. adoption of tillage.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 3&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;most-troublesome-weeds&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most troublesome weeds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Waterhemp, giant ragweed, common lambsquarters, and common ragweed, respectively, are considered the most troublesome weed species in Wisconsin cropping systems according to survey respondents.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 WI survey/Figure 4. most troublesome weeds in wisconsin.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 4&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;perceived-presence-of-glyphosate-resistant-weeds&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Perceived presence of glyphosate-resistant weeds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Waterhemp, giant ragweed, and horseweed (aka marestail) are the main weed species that have evolved resistance to glyphosate in Wisconsin according to survey respondents.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 WI survey/Figure 5. gr weeds.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 5&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;perceived-presence-of-weed-s-resistant-to-a-herbicide-site-of-action-soa-other-than-glyphosate&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Perceived presence of weed(s) resistant to a herbicide site-of-action (SOA) other than glyphosate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Several survey respondents reported the occurrence of ALS-resistant waterhemp and giant ragweed in Wisconsin.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 WI survey/Figure 6. hr weeds.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 6&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;adoption-of-1-vs-2-pass-herbicide-program-in-corn-and-soybeans&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adoption of 1- vs 2-pass herbicide program in corn and soybeans&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A 1-pass herbicide program is still pretty common in Wisconsin, particularly in corn.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 WI survey/Figure 7. 1 vs 2 pass.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 7&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;anticipated-adoption-of-auxin-tolerant-crops-such-as-xtend-dicamba-tolerant-and-enlist-2-4-d-tolerant-soybeans&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anticipated adoption of auxin-tolerant crops such as Xtend (dicamba-tolerant) and Enlist (2,4-D tolerant) soybeans&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The adoption of auxin-tolerant crops in Wisconsin will likely not be as high as in central and southern states.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 WI survey/Figure 8. auxin tolerant crops.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 8&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;adoption-of-or-interest-in-cover-crops&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adoption of or interest in cover crops&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Several survey respondents reported the adoption or expressed interest in adopting cover crops in Wisconsin.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 WI survey/Figure 9. cover crops.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 9&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned-from-the-survey&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lessons learned from the survey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wisconsin cropping systems are very diversified in terms of crop rotation and tillage is a common strategy. The combination of crop rotation and tillage has likely helped postpone the selection for herbicide-resistant weeds (when comparing to the situation in neighboring states). Thus, Wisconsin farmers, continue to do what you have been doing, it&amp;rsquo;s working!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite the &amp;ldquo;delayed&amp;rdquo; arrival, herbicide-resistant weeds are here to stay, and perhaps more widespread than some of us may think (check this presentation: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HR1KFvHgYr0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2018 Update on Herbicide Resistant Weeds in Wisconsin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). In order to manage herbicide-resistant weeds, besides continuing to deploy integrated weed management strategies (e.g., crop rotations, tillage, cover crops), farmers may have to consider adjusting their herbicide programs. A two pass program may be necessary to control the troublesome weed species with extended emergence window we are dealing with (e.g., waterhemp, giant ragweed, common lambsquarters). The addition of herbicides with soil residual activity in herbicide programs will enhance the control of these troublesome weeds and reduce the selection pressure on POST-emergence herbicides.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;For assistance with herbicide selection, check:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://learningstore.uwex.edu/Assets/pdfs/A3646.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pest Management in Wisconsin Field Crops&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
UWEX Bulletin A3646 (PDF)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://ipcm.wisc.edu/download/pubsPM/Herbicide-Mode-of-Action.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wisconsin Herbicide Mode of Action Chart&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;br /&gt;
Always read the product label.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lower interest in auxin-tolerant crops in Wisconsin is likely due to i) high diversity of sensitive crops in the landscape and concerns with off-target movement, ii) relative small fields, reducing the practically for the adoption of the technology due to buffer restrictions, and iii) lower incidence of herbicide-resistant weeds thus less need for the technology (as compared to neighboring states).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There seems to be high interest in incorporating cover crops in Wisconsin cropping systems. When deciding how best to use cover crops, it is important to consider the ultimate goal. Is it to increase soil organic matter, increase nutrient availability to subsequent crops, reduce soil compaction, supply forage for livestock, and/or suppress weeds? Answering these questions will help identify the cover crops strategies that offer the best chance of success for meeting the goal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;WiscWeeds&lt;/strong&gt; program will be investigating the several topics addressed in this survey: i) distribution and management of herbicide-resistant weeds, ii) the fit of auxin-tolerant crops in Wisconsin, and iii) cover crop management strategies. To stay tuned about our research updates and field days this summer, follow us on Twitter &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/WiscWeeds&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;@WiscWeeds&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the survey respondents for valuable feedback and to Maxwel Oliveira for compiling the results.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcoming New WiscWeeds Team Members</title>
      <link>/post/welcoming-new-wiscweeds-team-members/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/welcoming-new-wiscweeds-team-members/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am excited to introduce and welcome the new members of the Wisconsin Cropping Systems Weed Science (&lt;strong&gt;WiscWeeds&lt;/strong&gt;) Program: Maxwel Oliveira, Ryan DeWerff, Sarah Striegel, Victor Ribeiro and Nikola Arsenijevic.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/team/Maxwel Oliveira.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Maxwel Oliveira&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://maxweeds.rbind.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Maxwel Coura Oliveira&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Postdoctoral Research Associate)&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Maxwel started at the University of Wisconsin-Madison as a Weed Science Postdoctoral Research Associate in January 2018 in Dr. Werle’s program. Maxwel was born in the state of Minas Gerais, Brazil. He earned his B.S. in Agronomy and M.S. in Weed Science from the Federal University of Jequitinhonha and Mucuri Valleys, Brazil under Dr. Jose Barbosa dos Santos. He received his PhD in Weed Science from the University of Nebraska-Lincoln in December 2017 under Dr. Stevan Knezevic. Maxwel is interested in investigating the distribution and management of herbicide-resistant weeds in Wisconsin, and evaluating weed management strategies in corn, soybeans and small grains. Maxwel is responsible for training the Badger Weeds Team, mentoring undergraduate and graduate students in the WiscWeeds program, and assist with the Wisconsin Herbicide Evaluation Program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/team/Ryan DeWerff.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Ryan DeWerff&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ryan DeWerff&lt;/strong&gt; (Research Specialist)&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ryan started at the University of Wisconsin-Madison as a Weed Science Research Specialist in March 2018. Ryan grew up in central Illinois, where he was actively involved in the production of corn and soybean on his family’s farm. He received his B.S. in Crop Science at the University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign in Fall 2011. Ryan earned his M.S. in Agronomy at the University of Wisconsin-Madison in 2014, where he specialized in weed science under Dr. Vince Davis.  As part of his thesis, he researched how current soybean planting date and seeding rate recommendations affect weed management decisions in Wisconsin soybean production systems.  Ryan manages the Wisconsin Herbicide Evaluation Program and provides technical assistance for ongoing WiscWeeds program and graduate student research projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/team/Sarah Striegel.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sarah Striegel&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sarah Striegel&lt;/strong&gt; (MS Graduate Student)&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Sarah started at the University of Wisconsin-Madison as an MS student in Agronomy in April 2018, specializing in weed science under Dr. Rodrigo Werle. She was awarded the R. Gordon Harvey Wisconsin Distinguished Graduate Fellowship in Weed Science and the O.N. Allen Graduate Scholarship to support her studies. Sarah grew up in southern Iowa on a row crop corn and soybean farm. She earned her B.S. in Agronomy, Crop Management and Business at Iowa State University in December 2017. Her graduate research focuses on the evaluation of dicamba’s effectiveness as a tool for weed control in resistant crops and managing the risk of off-target movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/team/Victor Ribeiro.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Victor Ribeiro&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Victor Ribeiro&lt;/strong&gt; (Visiting MS Graduate Student)&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Victor will spend one year at the University of Wisconsin-Madison as a visiting M.S. graduate student under Dr. Rodrigo Werle. Victor comes from the state of Minas Gerais, Brazil. He is currently an M.S. student in Crop Production at the Federal University of Jequitinhonha and Mucuri Valleys, Brazil, under Dr. Jose Barbosa dos Santos, where they are studying the fate of 2,4-D and dicamba in soil. Victor earned his B.S. in Agronomy at the same institution in March 2018 and was an active student in Dr. Barbosa’s weed science program throughout his degree. As a visiting M.S. graduate student at UW-Madison, Victor will study the fate of dicamba in soil and also participate in several projects conducted by the WiscWeeds Program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/team/Nikola Arsenijevic.png&#34; alt=&#34;Nikola Arsenijevic&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nikola Arsenijevic&lt;/strong&gt; (MS Graduate Student)&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Nikola will start at the University of Wisconsin-Madison as an MS student in Agronomy this summer, specializing in weed science under Dr. Rodrigo Werle. Nikola grew up in a small town in central Republic of Serbia. He received his B.S. in Crop Protection at University of Belgrade, Serbia, in Fall 2017. As an undergraduate student, he conducted weed science research under Dr. Sava Vrbnicanin. His graduate research project will focus on the impact of soil-applied PPO and PSII herbicides on early season soybean development and Palmer amaranth control. Part of Nikola’s MS research was conducted in Western Nebraska during his senior internship at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln under Dr. Werle.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Talk</title>
      <link>/presentation/example-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/presentation/example-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Embed your slides or video here using &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/post/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;. Further details can easily be added using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
