<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wisconsin Weed Science on Wisconsin Weed Science</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Wisconsin Weed Science on Wisconsin Weed Science</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2021 WiscWeeds</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Cereal Rye Cover Crop Termination Timing and its Impact on Weed Suppression and Soybean Yield</title>
      <link>/post/cereal-rye-cover-crop-termination-timing-and-its-impact-on-weed-suppression-and-soybean-yield/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/cereal-rye-cover-crop-termination-timing-and-its-impact-on-weed-suppression-and-soybean-yield/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;With increased temperatures and recent rain, Wisconsin fields that were planted with a cereal rye cover crop in the fall are showing signs of life. If you are planning to manage your cereal rye cover crop as part of an integrated weed management program for in season suppression of small seeded annual weeds, it is important to ensure a large amount of biomass is produced by the time of termination. Research conducted by the WiscWeeds team at the Arlington and Lancaster Agricultural Research Stations over the last two years has shown that a cereal rye cover crop’s ability to suppress weeds improves as the amount of biomass produced increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Establishment of a cover crop following corn harvest in the fall can be difficult due to the short window of time that fields are accessible with equipment. Later established cereal rye may not produce much, if any biomass in the fall and winter, leaving producers to rely on biomass that is produced in the spring. In 2021, we have observed variable biomass production across our cover crop research sites, likely due to differences in when we established our cereal rye in the fall, highlighting the importance of early establishment. Check out recent photos from our research sites:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 cover crop update/brooklyn2021.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
Brooklyn, WI (cereal rye planted September 25, 2020; photo taken April 13, 2021)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 cover crop update/janesville2021.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
Janesville, WI (cereal rye planted October 21, 2020; photo taken April 13, 2021)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Winter rye for our &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/WiscWeeds?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@WiscWeeds&lt;/a&gt; 2021 corn and soybean system studies is looking great &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/UWMadisonCALS?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@UWMadisonCALS&lt;/a&gt; Lancaster ARS &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/zITQ47r5FH&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/zITQ47r5FH&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Daniel H Smith (@agronomybadger) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/agronomybadger/status/1379909151095148547?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;April 7, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Lancaster, WI (cereal rye planted October 21, 2020; photos taken April 7, 2021)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, producers that plant a cereal rye cover crop proceeding soybean will terminate their cereal rye 10-14 days before planting to minimize any impact on yield. This strategy may not allow enough time for adequate biomass production for aiding in weed suppression, especially as farmers continue to shift towards earlier planting in May to maximize yield potential. One way to increase biomass production is to delay termination of the cereal rye until time of soybean planting or even after soybean emergence. This strategy is commonly referred to as ‘&lt;strong&gt;planting green&lt;/strong&gt;’, as soybeans are no-till planted into a standing cereal rye cover crop. Delaying termination until early reproductive stages, such as anthesis, increases the C:N ratio of rye vegetation. This slows residue decomposition leading to biomass which persists longer, further aiding with weed suppression. Furthermore, ensuring effective termination before or at anthesis is important as this eliminates the chances of the cereal rye from producing seed and becoming an additional weed to manage. Generally, our recommendation for an effective termination of cereal rye is to use a full rate of glyphosate with recommended adjuvants (see: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wiscweeds.info/post/2020-considerations-for-cover-crop-termination/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;‘2020 Considerations for Cover Crop Termination’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;). If terminating the cereal rye at or within three days of soybean planting, glyphosate can be tank mixed with a PRE herbicide as part of an integrated weed management strategy. If you are planning to delay cereal rye terminations until after soybean emergence, glyphosate still remains an effective option in GMO (glyphosate-resistant) soybean; however, it will have to be replaced by a Group 1 (ACCase; e.g., clethodim, quizalofop) herbicide with recommended adjuvants in non-GMO soybeans. For soybean farmers interested in adopting cereal rye cover crops, we recommend using an effective PRE herbicide applied at planting as an additional tool for weed management regardless of cereal rye termination timing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below we discuss some highlights from two research studies conducted over two years in Wisconsin evaluating the impacts of cereal rye termination timing on both GMO and non-GMO soybean yield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-1-cereal-rye-termination-timing-impact-on-weed-suppression-and-gmo-roundup-ready-soybean-yield&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study 1: Cereal Rye Termination Timing Impact on Weed Suppression and GMO (Roundup Ready) Soybean Yield&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soil management experiment at Arlington Agricultural Research Station. Photo taken April 13, 2021. These plots will be planted to corn this growing season:
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 cover crop update/Systems Arlington 2021.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Managing &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/cerealrye?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#cerealrye&lt;/a&gt; for weed suppression in soybean? Effective termination + adequate moisture = minimal impacts on soy yield in WI. In 2021, be mindful of moisture cond. in your field and manage accordingly &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/WiscWeeds?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@WiscWeeds&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/KolbyCoverCrops?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@KolbyCoverCrops&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/agronomybadger?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@agronomybadger&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/ohYtuit01I&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/ohYtuit01I&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Nick Arneson (@arnaman6) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/arnaman6/status/1383050310243999750?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;April 16, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study was conducted at Arlington and Lancaster Agricultural Research Stations in 2019 and 2020. Treatments included six soil management strategies (tillage, no-till and 4 methods of cereal rye cover crop termination: 14 days before planting, at planting, at planting forage harvest, and 14 days after planting) and two herbicide programs (no PRE-emergence program or Authority MTZ @ 16 oz/acre applied PRE at planting). All terminations were achieved with a full rate of glyphosate plus recommended adjuvants (Roundup PowerMax @ 32 fl oz/acre + AMS @ 1% v/v). When no PRE was used, delayed cereal rye termination timing resulted in improved weed suppression, with the highest level of suppression observed in the 14 days after planting cover crop termination treatment. When a PRE was used, effective weed control was achieved across soil management strategies. The cover crop treatments, regardless of termination timing, did not reduce soybean yield compared to tillage and no-till strategies in this study. Results from this study demonstrate the value of using an effective PRE herbicide with potential added value from delayed termination of a cereal rye cover crop. The combination of these practices improved weed suppression in soybean with minimal to no yield impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For full study details, check out the UW-Mad About Weeds YouTube summary video &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Impact of
Cereal Rye Cover Crop on Weed Control and Crop Productivity in Wisconsin&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;:
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/Q6UToPwuUS4&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34; title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-2-cereal-rye-termination-timing-impact-on-non-gmo-conventional-soybean-yield&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study 2: Cereal Rye Termination Timing Impact on non-GMO (conventional) Soybean Yield&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cereal rye cover crop impact on non-GMO soybean experiment at Arlington Agricultural Research Station. Photo taken at the time of soybean planting (May 15, 2020). Note the plots of cereal rye turning yellow from the 8 days before planting termination time:
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 cover crop update/Food grade.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study was conducted at the Arlington Agricultural Research Stations in 2019 and 2020 in collaboration with Dr. Shawn Conley, Wisconsin Soybean Extension Specialist, and Dr. Damon Smith’s, Wisconsin Field Crops Pathologist, research programs. Treatments included two non-GMO (food grade) soybean varieties, three cover crop termination timings (8 days before planting, at planting, and 14 days after planting), and two herbicide programs (no PRE-emergence program or BroadAxe XC @ 22 fl oz/acre applied PRE at planting). The 8 days before and at planting termination timings were terminated with glyphosate plus recommended adjuvants (Roundup PowerMax @ 22 fl oz/acre + AMS @ 1.275 lb/acre). The 14 days after planting timing was terminated with a full rate of clethodim plus recommended adjuvants (Volunteer @ 8 fl oz/acre + AMS @ 2.5 lb/acre + COC @ 1% v/v). Termination timing had no impact on non-GMO soybean yield for either variety in 2019. In 2020, the 14 days after planting termination treatment (terminated with clethodim) reduced non-GMO soybean yield compared to the 8 days before planting termination timing. In general, the early part of the 2020 growing season was particularly dry compared to 2019. The 14 days after planting termination in 2020 did not completely terminate the cereal rye which remained green and standing for an extended period. In general, clethodim and other Group 1 herbicides provide a slower death compared to glyphosate which can lead to an extended period of standing, green rye. The stress from the incomplete termination, coupled with drier conditions, likely contributed to the yield drag observed in 2020 for this study. Results from this study indicate that a delayed cereal rye termination may not have an impact on soybean yield if the termination is effective and adequate precipitation occurs; however, if ineffective, a delayed termination can negatively impact soybean yield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For full study details, check out the UW-Mad About Weeds YouTube summary video &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Impact of
Cereal Rye Cover Crop on Preemergence Herbicide Fate and Non-GMO Soybean Yield in Wisconsin&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;:
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/BXqrJ1CBRBk&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34; title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more videos, check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCH-XrJxxyGoP2E-DGGpdF-w&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UW-Mad About Weeds YouTube Page&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maximizing cereal rye biomass will increase likelihood of weed suppression in soybean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Effective termination of cereal rye is necessary to minimize impacts on soybean yield&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Given adequate soil moisture, a fall-seeded cereal rye cover crop should not impact yield of mid- to late-May planted soybean, regardless of termination timing up to 14 days after planting when rye should be approaching or reached anthesis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Farmers are encouraged to visit with their insurance provider when deciding the time for cover crop termination and crop management practices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cereal rye cover crop is an additional tool for weed management and should not be used in place of an effective herbicide program when managing troublesome weeds such as waterhemp and giant ragweed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nicholas Arneson&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kolby Grint&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Graduate Student)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dan Smith&lt;/em&gt; (UW NPM Southwest Wisconsin Regional Specialist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ryan DeWerff&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Research Specialist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2020 Wisconsin Weed Science Visual Research Reports</title>
      <link>/post/2020-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-with-field-images/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-with-field-images/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this post is to share images from some of the corn and soybean herbicide evaluation research trials conducted by the Wisconsin Cropping Systems Weed Science Program during the 2020 growing season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;to-download-the-2020-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-click-here-pdf-file-img-2020-research-report-2020-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/2020 Wisconsin Weed science Research Report.pdf&#34;&gt;To download the 2020 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report, CLICK HERE (PDF FILE).&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2020 Corn Weed Control Trials (field images):&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Bayer Corn Herbicide Programs.pdf&#34;&gt;Bayer Corn Herbicide Programs (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Shieldex Weed Control and Crop Safety.pdf&#34;&gt;Shieldex Weed Control and Crop Safety (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Corn Herbicide Evaluation 1 and 2-Pass Programs with Atrazine.pdf&#34;&gt;Corn Herbicide Evaluation 1 and 2-Pass Programs with Atrazine (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Anthem Maxx Corn Herbicide Programs.pdf&#34;&gt;Anthem Maxx Corn Herbicide Programs (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Evaluation of Acuron GT in a One Pass System.pdf&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Acuron GT in a One Pass System (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Evaluation of Acuron GT in a Two Pass System.pdf&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Acuron GT in a Two Pass System (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Evaluation of Acuron XR and Acuron Flexi XR.pdf&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Acuron XR and Acuron Flexi XR (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Sinate Corn Herbicide Comparison.pdf&#34;&gt;Sinate Corn Herbicide Comparison (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2020 Soybean Weed Control Trials (field images):&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/XtendFlex Soybean Herbicide Programs.pdf&#34;&gt;XtendFlex Soybean Herbicide Programs (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Valent Herbicides in Enlist Soybeans.pdf&#34;&gt;Valent Herbicides in Enlist Soybeans (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Authority Brand Herbicide Programs in Enlist Soybeans.pdf&#34;&gt;Authority Brand Herbicide Programs in Enlist Soybeans (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Liberty and Enlist Efficacy in Enlist Soybean - BASF.pdf&#34;&gt;Liberty and Enlist Efficacy in Enlist Soybean - BASF (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Liberty and Enlist Efficacy in Enlist Soybean - Corteva.pdf&#34;&gt;Liberty and Enlist Efficacy in Enlist Soybean - Corteva (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Syngenta Herbicide Programs in Enlist Soybeans.pdf&#34;&gt;Syngenta Herbicide Programs in Enlist Soybeans (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Utility of Layering Residual Herbicides in Soybean.pdf&#34;&gt;Utility of Layering Residual Herbicides in Soybean (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Liberty Tank Mix Combinations for Waterhemp Control.pdf&#34;&gt;Liberty Tank Mix Combinations for Waterhemp Control (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Liberty and Engenia in XtendFlex Soybean.pdf&#34;&gt;Liberty and Engenia in XtendFlex Soybean (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Expanding Residual Control with Alite 27.pdf&#34;&gt;Expanding Residual Control with Alite 27 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Evaluation of Soybean Soil Residual Herbicides - Giant Ragweed.pdf&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Soybean Soil Residual Herbicides - Giant Ragweed (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2020 Bareground Weed Control Trials (field images):&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Evaluation of Roundup PowerMAX 3.pdf&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Roundup PowerMAX 3 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Burndown Control of Giant Ragweed.pdf&#34;&gt;Burndown Control of Giant Ragweed (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Burndown Control of Glyphosate-Resistant Waterhemp.pdf&#34;&gt;Burndown Control of Glyphosate-Resistant Waterhemp (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to &lt;strong&gt;Ryan DeWerff&lt;/strong&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Research Specialist) for generating the visual research reports and to our team for capturing the images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information herein does not constitute a recommendation or endorsement of any particular product or practice. Information in these reports also does not replace any information presented on herbicide labels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please do not reproduce information presented within this report for public distribution without the expressed written consent from Dr. Rodrigo Werle.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/headers/2020WiscWeedsTeam.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2020-wiscweeds-team&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020 WiscWeeds Team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2020 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report</title>
      <link>/post/2020-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;by Ryan DeWerff (UW-Madison Weed Science Research Specialist), Nicholas Arneson (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist), and &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this report is to share the results of corn and soybean herbicide evaluation research trials conducted by the Wisconsin Cropping Systems Weed Science Program during the 2020 growing season. Information in this report does not constitute a recommendation or endorsement of any particular product or practice. Information in this report also does not replace any information presented on herbicide labels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;to-download-the-2020-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-click-here-pdf-file-img-2020-research-report-2020-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/2020 Wisconsin Weed science Research Report.pdf&#34;&gt;To download the 2020 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report, CLICK HERE (PDF FILE).&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please do not reproduce information presented within this report for public distribution without the expressed written consent from Dr. Rodrigo Werle.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2020-research-trials&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020 Research Trials:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;corn-weed-control-trials&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Corn Weed Control Trials&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bayer Corn Herbicide Programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shieldex Weed Control and Crop Safety&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corn Herbicide Evaluation: 1 and 2-pass Programs with Atrazine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anthem Maxx Corn Herbicide Programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Acuron GT in a One Pass System&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Acuron GT in a Two Pass System&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Acuron XR/Acuron Flexi in a 1 and 2 Pass System&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sinate Corn Herbicide Programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;soybean-weed-control-trials&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Soybean Weed Control Trials&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;XtendFlex Soybean Herbicide Programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Valent Herbicides in Enlist Soybeans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Authority Brand Herbicide Programs in Enlist Soybeans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liberty and Enlist Efficacy in Enlist Soybean - BASF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liberty and Enlist Efficacy in Enlist Soybean - Corteva&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syngenta Herbicide Programs in Enlist Soybean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Utility of Layering Residual Herbicides in Soybean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liberty Tank Mix Combinations for Waterhemp Control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liberty and Engenia in XtendFlex Soybean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expanding Residual Control with Alite 27&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Soybean Soil Residual Herbicides - Giant Ragweed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bareground-weed-control-trials&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bareground Weed Control Trials&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Burndown Programs for 8-12&amp;rdquo; Marestail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Roundup PowerMAX 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Burndown Control of Waterhemp and Giant Ragweed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-this-year&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;New This Year&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summary of Giant Ragweed Control in Corn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summary of Waterhemp Control in Soybean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/headers/2020WiscWeedsTeam.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2020-wiscweeds-team&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020 WiscWeeds Team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spray solution pH and soybean injury as influenced by dicamba and 2,4-d herbicide formulation and spray additives</title>
      <link>/post/spray-solution-ph-and-soybean-injury-as-influenced-by-dicamba-and-2-4-d-herbicide-formulation-and-spray-additives/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/spray-solution-ph-and-soybean-injury-as-influenced-by-dicamba-and-2-4-d-herbicide-formulation-and-spray-additives/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Sarah Striegel, former graduate student in the Cropping Systems Weed Science program, Department of Agronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison, had her first manuscript recently published in Weed Technology. Herein we provide the highlights of her latest publication and access to two technical articles for download and circulation to our clientele.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original research article:&lt;/strong&gt; Striegel S, Oliveira MC, Arneson N, Conley SP, Stoltenberg DE, Werle R (2020) Spray solution pH and soybean injury as influenced by synthetic auxin formulation and spray additives. Weed Technol.
DOI: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/weed-technology/article/spray-solution-ph-and-soybean-injury-as-influenced-by-synthetic-auxin-formulation-and-spray-additives/2AC0129BAD3C2EC05542E03D87635FEB&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;10.1017/wet.2020.89&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use of synthetic auxin herbicides has increased across the Midwestern United States after adoption of synthetic auxin-resistant soybean traits, in addition to extensive use of these herbicides in corn. Off-target movement of synthetic auxin herbicides such as dicamba can lead to severe injury to sensitive plants nearby. Previous research has documented effects of glyphosate on spray-solution pH and volatility of several dicamba formulations, but our understanding of the relationships between glyphosate and dicamba formulations commonly used in corn and for 2,4-D remains limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-objectives&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research Objectives&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main objectives of S. Striegel’s research were to (1) investigate the roles of synthetic auxin herbicide formulation, glyphosate, and spray additives on spray solution pH; and (2) assess the influence of glyphosate and application time of year on dicamba and 2,4-D volatility using soybean as bioindicators in low-tunnel field volatility experiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addition of glyphosate to a synthetic auxin herbicide decreased solution pH below 5.0 for four of the seven herbicides tested (range of initial pH of water source, 7.45–7.70). Among all treatment factors, inclusion of glyphosate was the most important affecting spray solution pH; however, the addition of glyphosate did not influence area under the injury over distance stairs in low-tunnel field volatility experiments. Greater soybean injury in field experiments was associated with high air temperatures (maximum, &amp;gt;85 F) and low wind speeds (mean, 0.7–3 mph) during the 48 h after treatment application. The two dicamba formulations (diglycolamine salt with VaporGrip® [Xtendimax with VaporGrip® herbicide] and sodium salt [Status herbicide]) resulted in similar levels of soybean injury for applications that occurred later in the growing season. Greater soybean injury was observed after dicamba than after 2,4-D choline treatments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technical articles for download and circulation to our clientele (PDF files):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/Update Series Articles/WWRUS Article 1_Spray Solution pH.pdf&#34;&gt;WiscWeeds Research Update Series, Article 1: Spray solution pH as influenced by synthetic auxin formulation and spray additives (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/Update Series Articles/WWRUS Article 2_Low tunnel volatility.pdf&#34;&gt;WiscWeeds Research Update Series, Article 2: Soybean injury as influenced by synthetic auxin formulation and spray additives (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;These technical articles have been developed by Nick Arneson (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist), Sarah Striegel (Former UW-Madison Weed Science Graduate Student) and Dr. Maxwel Oliveira (UW-Madison Weed Science Research Associate).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Funding for S. Striegel’s graduate research assistantship was provided by Bayer Crop Science and the R.Gordon Harvey Distinguished Graduate Fellowship. Dr. Werle served as S. Striegel&amp;rsquo;s major advisor; Drs. Conley and Stoltenberg served as advisory committee members. The authors would like to thank the University of Wisconsin-Madison Cropping Systems Weed Science research group and the Arlington Agricultural Research Station staff for their technical assistance in establishing the experiments.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weed Seed Movement Via Combines</title>
      <link>/post/weed-seed-movement/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/weed-seed-movement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Crop harvest is here and that means it’s time to be thinking about weed seedbank management. Over the last few weeks we have observed fields throughout Wisconsin with a fair amount of weed escapes. The most troublesome weeds in Wisconsin, waterhemp and giant ragweed, will retain their seeds well into October in the Upper Midwest. If you have weeds that have set seed in your field, now is the time to get out there, remove and burn them before combines start rolling. Check the &lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 combine/Weed Seed Management at Crop Harvest.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;UW-NPM Weed Seed Management at Crop Harvest (PDF file)&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; handout used in our Combine Cleaning Workshops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are unable to remove weeds that have gone to seed, it is important to develop a sound harvest strategy to minimize the spread of weeds from field to field. This would include cleaning combines between fields and harvesting fields with severe weed infestations last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last fall, to validate our concerns of weed seed movement via combines, we put out a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wiscweeds.info/post/2019-wiscweeds-research-coalition-combine-weed-seed-collection-project/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;call&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to UW-Madison Ag Extension Educators and stakeholders to take the time to clean and collect samples from combines before putting them away for the winter. We specifically asked for samples from four locations: head, feeder house, rock trap, and rotor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.vimeo.com/video/374533967&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total we received 31 samples from nine different combines (many thanks to all project participants). We then mixed the samples with field soil and potting mix in our greenhouse and observed what weeds emerged after two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the results by downloading this handout: &lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 combine/Weed Seed Movement via Combines.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Weed Seed Movement Via Combines: 2019-2020 Case Study (PDF file)&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here are some of the highlights:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;97% of samples contained viable weed seed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Combine head samples contained ~49% of the total weeds emerged, followed by the feeder house ~30%, rock trap ~19%, and rotor ~2%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most frequently observed weeds were grasses, pigweeds and common lambsquarters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When time is limited, we believe that prioritizing the front of the combine (head and feeder house) would provide the most benefit in reducing weed seed spread by combines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Last winter &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/agronomybadger?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@agronomybadger&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/WiscWeeds?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@WiscWeeds&lt;/a&gt; asked for  &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/combine?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#combine&lt;/a&gt; samples 2 c what &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/weeds?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#weeds&lt;/a&gt; we&amp;#39;re moving around WI. U delivered + here is quick update. Weeds setting seed in your field? Now&amp;#39;s the time to make moves! Stay tuned 4 further updates this fall &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/3mrP60YC4D&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/3mrP60YC4D&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Nick Arneson (@arnaman6) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/arnaman6/status/1296193027648688128?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 19, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some additional tips for cleaning combines and reducing the spread of weeds:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use an air compressor or leaf blower to force air through and clear debris from critical portions of the combine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run a bag of wood shavings through the combine to clean rotor/auger area&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/nDMq1UanSkE&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34; title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nick Arneson&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dan Smith&lt;/em&gt; (UW NPM Southwest Wisconsin Regional Specialist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Post-emergence Corn and Soybean Herbicide Product Restrictions for Broadcast Applications</title>
      <link>/post/post-emergence-corn-and-soybean-herbicide-product-restrictions-for-broadcast-applications/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/post-emergence-corn-and-soybean-herbicide-product-restrictions-for-broadcast-applications/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Favorable spring weather has given Wisconsin farmers a great start to the season with a fair amount of corn and soybean acres planted already. The recent trend in warmer temperatures will also lead to weed germination and emergence. However, the lack of significant rain events over recent weeks has left fields that had PRE-emergence herbicides applied without the moisture necessary for activation. This will likely result in weed escapes and place additional pressure on POST-emergence herbicides. In anticipation for heavy reliance on early POST applications to control troublesome weeds in corn and soybean, the Cropping Systems Weed Science program put together a handy guide for over-the-top broadcast application windows of commonly used POST herbicides in corn and soybean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application window tables (&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 POST Window/2020 POST Herbicide Application Window_Final.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CLICK HERE TO DOWNLOAD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;; Table 1 – Corn, Table 2 – Soybean) were generated based on information obtained from each of the product’s label. For additional information on recommended adjuvants and tank mix partners consult individual product labels and/or your local agronomist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When selecting a POST herbicide program, it is important to consider the weed species present, weed height, and crop growth and/or height.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inclusion of specific products does not constitute a recommendation or endorsement. Always read, follow, and understand the pesticide label. &lt;em&gt;The label is the law.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;additional-helpful-resources&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Additional Helpful Resources:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://corn.agronomy.wisc.edu/Management/pdfs/Corn%20Growth%20and%20Development%20poster.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Wisconsin Visual Guide to Corn Development&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://coolbean.info/library/documents/2017_Soybean_GrowthDev_Guide_FINAL.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Wisconsin Visual Guide to Soybean Growth Stages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0145/8808/4272/files/A3646-2020.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2020 Pest Management in Wisconsin Field Crops&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ipcm.wisc.edu/blog/2020/04/2020-wisconsin-herbicide-mode-of-action-chart/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2020 Wisconsin Herbicide Mode of Action Chart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wiscweeds.info/img/2019%20Research%20Report/2019%20Wisconsin%20Weed%20science%20Research%20Report.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2019 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wiscweeds.info/img/2018%20Research%20Report/2018%20WiscWeeds%20Research%20Report_Web.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2018 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nick Arneson&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Emily Glaeser&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Undergraduate Research Assistant)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2020 Considerations for Cover Crop Termination</title>
      <link>/post/2020-considerations-for-cover-crop-termination/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020-considerations-for-cover-crop-termination/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The adoption of cover crops in corn-soybean production systems can help growers improve cropping system resiliency to extreme weather events, improve soil conservation and health, and slow the evolution of weed herbicide resistance. To get the most out of cover crops prior to corn and soybean establishment, growers should have a sound termination plan in mind to maximize cover crop benefits and successful establishment of the following cash crop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2020 cc termination/CoverCrop Picture.png&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;small&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cover-crop-termination-with-herbicides&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover Crop Termination with Herbicides&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;herbicide-selection&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Herbicide Selection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cover crop species, weeds present under cover crop residue, and following cash crop should all be considered when selecting the proper herbicide to terminate a cover crop. This will ensure the cover crop does not later become a weed problem, all weeds present are terminated, and the cash crop isn’t negatively impacted by the cover crop and/or herbicide program of choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research conducted in Wisconsin indicates that glyphosate is an effective herbicide for termination of annual grass cover crops, including cereal rye and wheat. A 2019 study comparing termination of a winter wheat cover crop found glyphosate (Roundup) to be more effective than glufosinate (Liberty) (Dewerff et al., 2020; Figure 1). See also: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ipcm.wisc.edu/download/pubsPM/AnnualRye_WinterRye_Glyphosate.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Termination of Cereal Rye and Annual Ryegrass Using Glyphosate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2020 cc termination/WI_TermHerbFigure.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;small&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 1. Influence of application method and carrier volume on the termination of winter wheat cover crop using glufosinate (32 fl oz Liberty/acre + 1.5 lbs AMS/acre) and glyphosate (22 fl oz Roundup PowerMAX/acre + 1.5 lbs AMS/acre) sprayed at the day of soybean planting (June 05, 2019). Red bars indicate herbicide application using backpack sprayer, gray bars indicate application using a planter-mounted sprayer. Data collected 21 days after treatment. Experiment conducted at Arlington Agricultural Research Station, WI.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For termination of broadleaf cover crops there are differences regarding most effective herbicide(s) depending upon cover crop species. For information on effective chemical termination of broadleaf cover crops see: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ipm.missouri.edu/IPCM/2020/3/coverCropTermination-KB/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;University of Missouri Final Results from a Multi-state Study on Cover Crop Termination with Herbicides&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://ipcm.wisc.edu/download/pubsPM/CoverCropTerminationOptions.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;UW NPM Cover Crop Termination&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-considerations-for-herbicide-selection&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Other considerations for herbicide selection:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If glyphosate is used for cover crop termination, it should be sprayed when day temperatures are above 55° F and night temperatures are above 40° F. To further improve effective cereal rye control, glyphosate should be applied before the boot stage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If glyphosate-resistant weeds are present in your cover crop at termination (e.g., marestail, giant ragweed) adding herbicides such as 2,4-D and/or saflufenacil (e.g., Sharpen) to a glyphosate tank-mix can assist in improving control. This has also been shown to aid in termination of broadleaf cover crops (check product labels for planting restrictions).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If using contact herbicides such as paraquat (e.g., Gramoxone) and glufosinate (e.g., Liberty, Cheetah, Scout, etc.), practices that improve spray coverage will improve efficacy (e.g., medium spray droplet size and higher application carrier volumes [≥20 GPA]).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Applicators and handlers of paraquat (e.g., Gramoxone) are now required by the U.S. EPA to complete training every 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;termination-timing&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Termination Timing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benefits associated with using cover crops are correlated to the amount of biomass produced. Allowing cover crops to accumulate as much biomass as possible prior to termination will increase extent and longevity of benefits received, including reduced soil erosion and weed control. Ideally a grower would want to terminate their cover crops at a time when they can obtain the maximum amount of biomass without reducing resources for their cash crop (i.e., water, nutrients, sunlight). In general, the later a cover crop is terminated, the longer cover crop biomass will persist on the soil surface, suppressing weeds and protecting the soil surface (Figure 2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2020 cc termination/Termination Timing Figure_Field Pictures.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;small&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 2. Effect of termination timing with glyphosate (22 fl oz Roundup PowerMAX/acre + 1.5 lb AMS/acre) on cereal rye cover crop biomass in corn and soybean. Cover Crop terminated approximately two weeks prior to crop planting (Early, May 7), during crop planting (Plant, May 23), and two weeks after crop planting (Late, June 6). Images display remaining cover crop residue at Lancaster Agricultural Research Station, WI on June 18, 2019. Images by K. Grint.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Potential causes of cash crop yield reduction from cover crops include early season nitrogen tie-up limitations in corn, water stress during drought situations when cover crops can reduce available soil water for an early growing crop, competition for light, and/or poorly adjusted and maintained planting equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wet springs, such as in 2019, can make timely termination of cover crops difficult. A study conducted by the Wisconsin Cropping Systems Weed Science program (part of Kolby Grint&amp;rsquo;s MS graduate research) in 2019 at Arlington and Lancaster Agricultural Research Stations, Wisconsin found that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In soybean, termination of a cereal rye cover crop 2 weeks after planting had no impact on yield compared to tillage, no-till, and earlier terminations of a cereal rye cover crop (Figure 3).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In corn, yield was consistently reduced when cereal rye was terminated after planting (Figure 4). It is suspected early season available nitrogen was a limiting factor for corn.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2020 cc termination/WISoybeanYield.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;small&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 3. Soybean yield for tillage (Till), no-till (NT), early cover crop termination (NT+CCET), at plant cover crop termination (NT+CCPT), forage harvest of a cover crop at planting (NT+CCFH), and later cover crop termination (NT+CCLT) soil management practices. Visual representation of late season cereal rye biomass from this study can be seen in Figure 2. Bars with similar letter are not statistically different at α=0.05 using Fisher’s LSD. Preliminary results from K. Grint MS Projects.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2020 cc termination/WICornYield.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;small&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 4. Corn yield for tillage (Till), no-till (NT), early cover crop termination (NT+CCET), at plant cover crop termination (NT+CCPT), forage harvest of a cover crop at planting (NT+CCFH), and later cover crop termination (NT+CCLT) soil management practices. Visual representation of late season cereal rye biomass from this study can be seen in Figure 2. Bars with similar letter are not statistically different at α=0.05 using Fisher’s LSD. Preliminary results from K. Grint MS Projects.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://coolbean.info/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2020/03/PlantingSoybeansIntoRye_2020.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Regional Soybean Yield Rye Cover Crop Study&lt;/a&gt; conducted in 2019 by the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, University of Minnesota, and University of Wisconsin-Madison also found that cover crop termination shortly after planting had no effect on soybean yield (Figure 5). These findings indicate that soybean is less likely to experience a yield reduction from cover crop termination after planting compared to corn when adequate soil moisture is available (which was the case at all these research sites in 2019).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2020 cc termination/BeanTeam_YieldFigure.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;small&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 5. Soybean yield for no cover crop (NC), termination prior to crop planting (T1), termination at crop planting (T2), and termination approximately 1 week after crop planting (T3).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UW-Madison researchers and many others across the Midwest typically recommend terminating cover crops before crop planting when possible (see: &lt;a href=&#34;http://coolbean.info/library/documents/CPN-4002.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Cover Crops Do’s and Don’t’s&lt;/a&gt;). Delaying the termination and planting of fields with cover crops until non-cover cropped fields have been planted can be one way to maximize cover crop biomass accumulation, while minimizing potential for cash crop yield reduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-considerations-for-timing-of-cover-crop-termination&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Other considerations for timing of cover crop termination:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What are the forecasted weather conditions? Consider the following question: Is there time to delay termination a my cover crop while still allowing timely establishment of a cash crop?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When using herbicides for cover crop termination, efficacy can be reduced after cover crops reach reproductive stages. Termination prior to reproductive stages is recommended for best chemical control.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Producers are encouraged to visit with their insurance provider when deciding the time for cover crop termination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If cover crops will be harvested for forage, herbicides should be sprayed after biomass harvest and removal from the field to control the re-growth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;considerations-for-herbicides-following-cover-crop-termination&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Considerations for Herbicides following Cover Crop Termination&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pre-emergence-herbicide-application&#34;&gt;PRE-emergence Herbicide Application&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A grower may decide to spray their PRE-emergence herbicides before, during or after cover crop termination; see &lt;a href=&#34;https://crops.extension.iastate.edu/cropnews/2020/02/managing-residual-herbicides-cover-crops&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Iowa State University Managing Residual Herbicides with Cover Crops&lt;/a&gt;. Cover crop residue can alter the fate of PRE-emergence herbicides. When an abundance of cover crop biomass is present at application there is potential for spray interception and subsequent reduced soil concentration of PRE-emergence herbicides. This is most prevalent when precipitation doesn’t occur soon after herbicide application. Residual herbicide incapable of reaching the soil will not have the desired impact on controlling germinating weed species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If concerned about a PRE-emergence herbicide being ineffective when high amounts of cover crop residue are present, growers may consider including soil residual herbicides with a POST-emergence application (after some of the cover crop residue has decomposed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;post-emergence-herbicide-application&#34;&gt;POST-emergence Herbicide Application&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover crops alone will likely not provide season-long weed control. POST-emergence herbicides are necessary to maintain control of in-season weeds. As always, scouting is very important for determining when to make a POST-emergence herbicide application. Cover crops typically aren’t as effective for suppression of large seeded weed species (e.g., velvetleaf, giant ragweed).
Including a residual herbicide with POST-emergence  applications can provide extended in season weed control. This can be especially effective when a PRE herbicide wasn’t used or when cover crop residue quickly degrades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If planning to plant cover crops again in the fall, herbicides with soil residual activity should be carefully selected so they don’t negatively impact establishment of the cover crop species intended to use. For additional information on herbicide rotational restrictions for cover crops see: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ipcm.wisc.edu/download/pubsPM/2019_RotationalRestrictions_final.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;UW NPM Herbicide Rotational Restrictions for Cover and Forage Cropping Systems&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;roller-crimper&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roller-Crimper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Timing is the most important factor for termination of a cover crop when using a roller-crimper. For grass cover crops, termination should occur when flowering has begun (Figure 6). Full anthesis of cereal rye in WI typically occurs around Memorial Day. For legume cover crops, termination should occur when the plants begin producing pods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If roller-crimping occurs too early the cover crop will not be successfully terminated, if done too late there is risk the seed produced by the cover crop will be viable and add to the weed seedbank. Using a roller-crimper creates a dense mat of residue parallel to the soil surface which has been shown to be one of the best ways to suppress weeds with cover crop residue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For additional information on roller-crimpers, watch the video: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ipcm.wisc.edu/blog/2015/07/advances-using-the-roller-crimper-for-organic-no-till-in-wisconsin/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Advances Using the Roller-crimper for Organic No-till in Wisconsin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2020 cc termination/roller crimper.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;small&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 6. Cover crop roller attachment to the planter in operation at Arlington Agricultural Research Station, WI.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nebraska-and-wisconsin-planting-green-cover-crop-survey&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nebraska and Wisconsin Planting Green Cover Crop Survey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nebraska and Wisconsin farmers were surveyed in early 2020 regarding their successes and challenges from planting green. The target audience was those who already adopt cover crops. A quick look at the responses show that more than half (53%) of growers indicated that they used this practice for planting both corn and soybean. Most farmers reported that they observed none or minor impacts of planting “green” on crop emergence, yields, allelopathic reactions, pests (disease, insects, weeds), and/or fertility. Once we summarize all the survey responses we will share more details about what has worked well and what has been challenging for farmers planting green.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you planted green in 2019 or previous growing seasons, please take the time to fill out the quick &lt;a href=&#34;https://ssp.qualtrics.com/jfe/form/SV_0St2eD2n5KH9jWB&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Planting Green into Cover Crops SURVEY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from our colleagues at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. Your participation assists our programs by directing our research to best meet the growers we serve. Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kolby Grint&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Graduate Student)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dan Smith&lt;/em&gt; (UW NPM Southwest Wisconsin Regional Specialist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nicholas Arneson&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ryan DeWerff&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Research Specialist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shawn Conley&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Soybean and Small Grain Specialist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Utility of a Planter Mounted Pulse Width Modulation Spray System. Ryan P. DeWerff, Nicholas J. Arneson, and Rodrigo Werle. University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI (2020 WSSA Poster 159).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://extension.unl.edu/statewide/enre/2020SMFDResearchUpdateBooklet-FINAL.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Impact of Cover Crop Termination Timing on Arthropod Abundance, Defoliation, and Soybean Yield&lt;/a&gt;. Justin McMechan, Thomas Hunt, and Robert Wright. University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, NE (2019 Soybean Management Field Days Research Update).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enlist E3 Soybean System in 2020: What We Think Applicators Should Know</title>
      <link>/post/enlist-e3-system-in-2020-what-we-think-applicators-should-know/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/enlist-e3-system-in-2020-what-we-think-applicators-should-know/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Information presented herein does not represent an endorsement of Enlist E3 soybean technology nor any seed trait or herbicide product. The purpose of this publication is solely to educate potential applicators and promote effective use of the Enlist E3 soybean technology from Corteva Agriscience.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winter has come and gone and Spring is officially here. This means that farmers around Wisconsin and across the Midwest are getting prepared to hit the ground running when the time comes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, we understand that most seed and chemical orders have been placed and the decision on whether or not to adopt the novel soybean herbicide trait technologies (RR2YX, LLGT27, and Enlist E3) has been made. A recent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/survey-wisconsin-soybean-herbicide-tolerance-trait-selection-2019-2020/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt; conducted by the UW-Madison Cropping Systems Weed Science Lab provided interesting insight of how Wisconsin farmers intend to adopt these technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey results included 58 participants representing approximately 330,000 soybean acres across 46 WI counties. According to participants, 14% of the represented acres in the survey will be planted with Enlist E3 soybeans in 2020 compared to 1% in 2019. Of those acres, 81% and 63% are expected to receive a 2,4-D choline and glufosinate application POST-emergence, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2020 Enlist E3/2020 HT Trait.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the anticipated increased adoption of Enlist E3 soybeans and 2,4-D choline POST-emergence (particularly targeting waterhemp control), this is an essential time to review some of the important information regarding 2,4-D choline applications in Enlist E3 soybeans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, Enlist One (2,4-D choline) and Enlist Duo (2,4-D choline and glyphosate premix) are the only 2,4-D products labeled for use in Enlist E3 soybeans. Other 2,4-D products are &lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt; labeled thus should &lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt; be used in Enlist E3 soybeans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;application-window-and-rate-structure&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Application Window and Rate Structure:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enlist One application rate: 1.5 – 2 pts/acre*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enlist Duo application rate: 3.5 – 4.75 pts/acre*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply Enlist herbicides when weeds are small (&amp;lt; 4 inches)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply Enlist herbicides no later than R2 (full flowering stage) in Enlist E3 soybeans&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two POST-emergence applications maximum within a growing season with a minimum of 12 days between applications (keep in mind that overreliance will lead to additional weed resistance)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;em&gt;Maximum label rates of Enlist herbicides should be used when managing troublesome weeds such as waterhemp.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sensitive-area-buffers&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sensitive Area Buffers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;30 ft buffer downwind between application area and sensitive areas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examples of sensitive areas:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;wooded area&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pasture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;roadside ditch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lawns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buffers are not meant to protect downwind adjacent susceptible crops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buffers are a requirement from EPA (US Environmental Protection Agency) to protect potential endangered species habitat areas&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;susceptible-crops&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Susceptible Crops:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not spray Enlist One or Enlist Duo herbicides when adjacent susceptible crops are downwind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examples of susceptible crops:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;grapes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tomatoes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cucurbits (watermelon, squash, pumpkins)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fruiting vegetables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tobacco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;non-Enlist cotton&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;compatible-crops&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compatible Crops:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crops not listed as susceptible on the Enlist One and Enlist Duo labels which can be downwind from application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examples of compatible crops:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;non-Enlist soybeans&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;corn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;wheat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;alfalfa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sorghum&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;peanuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sugarcane&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sweet potato&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, with adequate environmental conditions and proper sprayer setup, Enlist One or Enlist Duo can be sprayed when non-Enlist E3 soybeans are downwind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mixing-and-application-considerations&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mixing and Application Considerations:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10 gallons or more per acre of spray volume (15 GPA is recommended)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use high level of gallonage when tank mixing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use plenty of water between additions for induction tanks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tank-mix sequence procedures (begin with half-full tank of water; begin agitation and continue throughout mixing process):

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AMS / water conditioning agents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pre-slurry water-soluble packets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wettable powders / dry flowables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compatibility agents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liquid flowables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Capsule suspension (CS) or suspension emulsion (SE)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emulsifiable concentrate (EC)

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Soluble liquids (SL)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enlist Duo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enlist One*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Glyphosate products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crop Oil Concentrate (COC), NIS, other adjuvants&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Top off with water carrier
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;em&gt;When mixing with Enlist One, do not pour glufosinate products or potassium salt of glyphosate into the tank at the same time as Enlist One. Add products one at a time, allowing enough time for recirculation between additions of each separate product.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;approved-enlist-e3-tank-mixes&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Approved Enlist E3 Tank Mixes*:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enlist One: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.enlist.com/en/approved-tank-mixes/enlist-one.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.enlist.com/en/approved-tank-mixes/enlist-one.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enlist Duo: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.enlist.com/en/approved-tank-mixes/enlist-duo.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.enlist.com/en/approved-tank-mixes/enlist-duo.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;em&gt;Applicators should check websites frequently throughout the growing season to ensure they have the most up to date information regarding approved tank mixes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that a glyphosate, 2,4-D choline and glufosinate tank mix is only permitted with the Enlist One formulation. Glufosinate products are not approved for tank mix with Enlist Duo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also important to note that Roundup PowerMAX which is labeled for use in “Roundup Ready Crops” now has a supplemental label for use in Glyphosate-Tolerant Crops such as Enlist E3 soybeans and LLGT27 soybeans in Wisconsin. You can find the labels on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cdms.net/Label-Database&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;CDMS label database&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;approved-enlist-e3-allowable-nozzles&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Approved Enlist E3 Allowable Nozzles:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enlist One: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.enlist.com/en/approved-tank-mixes/enlist-one/enlist-one-allowable-nozzles.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.enlist.com/en/approved-tank-mixes/enlist-one/enlist-one-allowable-nozzles.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enlist Duo: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.enlist.com/en/approved-tank-mixes/enlist-duo-allowable-nozzles.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.enlist.com/en/approved-tank-mixes/enlist-duo-allowable-nozzles.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adopt best management practices and follow label requirements to minimize particle drift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sprayer-tank-cleanout-guide&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sprayer/Tank Cleanout Guide:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.enlist.com/content/dam/hdas/enlist/pdfs/Guide%20to%20Sprayer%20Cleanout.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.enlist.com/content/dam/hdas/enlist/pdfs/Guide%20to%20Sprayer%20Cleanout.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-the-most-out-of-2-4-d&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting the Most out of 2,4-D:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start clean and use an effective PRE-emergence herbicide program*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spray small weeds (4 inches or less) &amp;amp; consider a layered-residual approach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Large droplet size&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the landscape (be aware of sensitive areas and susceptible crops)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow label requirements by the book!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;em&gt;For assistance with PRE-emergence herbicide selection, check our publication: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/residual-control-of-waterhemp-with-pre-emergence-herbicides-in-soybean/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Residual Control of Waterhemp with PRE-emergence Herbicides in Soybeans&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further guidance on proper Enlist One and Enlist Duo applications consult the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.enlist.com/en/application-guide.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enlist Herbicides website&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;additional-considerations&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Additional Considerations:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our low tunnel volatility and large-scale drift trials conducted at UW Arlington Ag Research Station and Sun Prairie, WI have indicated minimal to no injury from 2,4-D choline into non-Enlist soybeans. Check our video from the &lt;strong&gt;2019 large-scale 2,4-D field trial&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.vimeo.com/video/357101555&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Glufosinate can also be sprayed POST-emergence in Enlist E3 soybeans, which gives farmers an additional chemical option for broadleaf weed control. Check our video &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;getting the most out of glufosinate&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;:
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.vimeo.com/video/335011671&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information regarding our 2,4-D and glufosinate efficacy trials check our &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/2019-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2019 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it is important to use an integrated weed management approach with multiple strategies (e.g., mix and rotate effective herbicide sites of action, crop rotation, promote good agronomics to hasten canopy closure, incorporate cover crops, use of tillage when appropriate, etc.) to postpone evolution of weed resistance to 2,4-D and glufosinate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgments:&lt;/strong&gt; Many thanks to our Industry and University colleagues who provided valuable feedback towards this blog article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt;: Nicholas Arneson (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist) and Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2019 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report with Field Images</title>
      <link>/post/2019-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-with-field-images/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-with-field-images/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this post is to share images from some of the corn and soybean herbicide evaluation research trials conducted by the Wisconsin Cropping Systems Weed Science Program during the 2019 growing season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2019-corn-weed-control-trials-click-to-download-the-pdf-file&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;2019 Corn Weed Control Trials (click to download the PDF file):&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2019 Research Report/Bayer Integrated Corn Herbicide Programs_WiscWeeds 2019.pdf&#34;&gt;Bayer Integrated Corn Herbicide Programs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2019 Research Report/Corn Herbicide Evaluation with Atrazine_WiscWeeds 2019.pdf&#34;&gt;Corn Herbicide Evaluation: 1- and 2-pass Programs with Atrazine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2019 Research Report/Corn Herbicide Systems Approach_WiscWeeds 2019.pdf&#34;&gt;Systems Approach to Weed Management in Corn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2019-soybean-weed-control-trials-click-to-download-the-pdf-file&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;2019 Soybean Weed Control Trials (click to download the PDF file):&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2019 Research Report/Tavium Plus VaporGrip Efficacy in Xtend Soybean_WiscWeeds 2019.pdf&#34;&gt;Tavium Plus VaporGrip Efficacy in Xtend&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2019 Research Report/Authority Brand Programs Efficacy in Soybean_WiscWeeds 2019.pdf&#34;&gt;Authority Brand Programs Efficacy in Soybean&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2019 Research Report/Evaluation of Soybean Soil Residual Herbicides-Brooklyn_WiscWeeds 2019.pdf&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Soybean Soil Residual Herbicides - Brooklyn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2019 Research Report/Evaluation of Soybean Soil Residual Herbicides-Fon du Lac__WiscWeeds 2019.pdf&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Soybean Soil Residual Herbicides - Found du Lac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2019 Research Report/Liberty and Enlist One-Enlist Duo Efficacy in Enlist Soybean_WiscWeeds 2019.pdf&#34;&gt;Liberty and Enlist One/Enlist Duo Efficacy in Enlist Soybean&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2019 Research Report/Valent Actives in a Liberty Link System_WiscWeeds 2019.pdf&#34;&gt;Valent Herbicides in a Liberty Link System&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Ryan DeWerff (UW-Madison Weed Science Research Specialist) for generating the visual research reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;to-download-the-2019-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-click-here-pdf-file-img-2019-research-report-2019-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2019 Research Report/2019 Wisconsin Weed science Research Report.pdf&#34;&gt;To download the 2019 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report, CLICK HERE (PDF FILE).&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information herein does not constitute a recommendation or endorsement of any particular product or practice. Information in these reports also does not replace any information presented on herbicide labels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please do not reproduce information presented within this report for public distribution without the expressed written consent from Dr. Rodrigo Werle.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/headers/2019WiscWeedsTeam.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2019-wiscweeds-team&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2019 WiscWeeds Team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2020 Wisconsin Regional Waterhemp Workshops</title>
      <link>/post/2020-wisconsin-regional-waterhemp-workshops/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020-wisconsin-regional-waterhemp-workshops/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;We invite farmers and crop advisors to attend one of the &lt;strong&gt;2020 Wisconsin Regional Waterhemp Workshops&lt;/strong&gt; to be held in four locations across the state in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt; &lt;strong&gt;These workshops are FREE with 3 CEUs (PM) available.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Waterhemp Workshops/2020_WaterhempWorkshop.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Download the Promotional Flyer HERE (PDF File)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These workshops are designed for farmers and crop advisors and will build on the &lt;strong&gt;2019 Regional Waterhemp Workshops (Waterhemp 101)&lt;/strong&gt;. Topics include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;current state of herbicide resistance in Wisconsin and the Midwest&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;systems approach to weed management on a field by field basis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;considerations for adoption of Enlist E3 system&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;managing herbicide resistant weeds by adding alfalfa to crop rotation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;cover crops and other considerations for weed management&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenters:&lt;/strong&gt; UW-Madison Extension Weed Scientists Rodrigo Werle and Mark Renz, Weed Science Outreach Specialist Nick Arneson, UW-NPM Outreach Specialist Dan Smith and members of the WiscWeeds Team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants should RSVP with the local contact by &lt;strong&gt;March 11&lt;/strong&gt; (limit of 60 participants per location).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;march-16-bangor-wi&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;March 16: Bangor, WI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Log Cabin, N4697 State Rd 162, Bangor, WI 54614&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Registration, coffee and rolls start at 9:30 am&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workshop: 10:00 am – 1:45 pm (lunch: 12:00 – 12:15)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bill Halfman, Monroe County Agriculture Agent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RSVP:&lt;/strong&gt; 608-269-8722 or william.halfman@wisc.edu&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;march-17-chippewa-falls-wi&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;March 17: Chippewa Falls, WI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eagles’ Club Banquet Hall, 2588 Hwy 53, Chippewa Falls, WI 54729&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Registration, coffee and rolls start at 8:30 am&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workshop: 9:00 am – noon (lunch to follow program)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jerry Clark, Chippewa County Agriculture Educator&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RSVP:&lt;/strong&gt; 715-726-7950 or jerome.clark@wisc.edu&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;march-23-appleton-wi&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;March 23: Appleton, WI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;D.J. Bordini Center, Room 112-A, Fox Valley Technical College, N Systems Dr, Appleton, WI 54914&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Registration, coffee and rolls start at 9:30 am&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workshop: 10:00 am – 1:45 pm (lunch: 12:00 – 12:15)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rhonda Sumnicht, Extension Shawano County&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RSVP:&lt;/strong&gt;  715-526-6136 or rhonda.sumnicht@co.shawano.wi.us&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;march-24-arlington-wi&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;March 24: Arlington, WI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Public Events Building, Arlington Agricultural Research Station, N695 Hopkins Rd, Arlington, WI 53911&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Registration, coffee and rolls start at 9:30 am&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workshop: 10:00 am – 1:45 pm (lunch: 12:00 – 12:15)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chelsea Zegler, Dane County Crop and Soils Educator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RSVP:&lt;/strong&gt; 608-224-3716 or zegler@wisc.edu&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to our sponsors (FMC confirmed; awaiting response from additional companies), meals and educational materials will be provided to participants for FREE! Thanks to the UW-NPM Program, UW-Extension, Wisconsin Soybean Marketing Board, Wisconsin Corn Promotion Board and the United Soybean Board for supporting our waterhemp management educational efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For general questions related to the workshops, please contact Nick Arneson at njarneson@wisc.edu or Dr. Rodrigo Werle at 608-262-7130 or rwerle@wisc.edu.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Residual Control of Waterhemp with PRE-emergence Herbicides in Soybean</title>
      <link>/post/residual-control-of-waterhemp-with-pre-emergence-herbicides-in-soybean/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/residual-control-of-waterhemp-with-pre-emergence-herbicides-in-soybean/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Waterhemp management in soybean was challenge for several Wisconsin farmers in 2019. The use of PRE-emergence herbicides is a foundation for effective waterhemp control; however, results from our &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/2018-wisconsin-cropping-systems-weed-science-survey/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;2018 weed management survey&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; indicated that the use of a single POST herbicide application is still a common weed control strategy for several farmers in the state. Furthermore, recent research by the UW-Madison Cropping Systems Weed Science Lab revealed that waterhemp resistance to glyphosate (EPSPS; Group 9) and imazethapyr (ALS; Group 2) is widespread across corn and soybean fields in Wisconsin, limiting effective POST herbicide control options, particularly in soybean (see &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/wisconsin-waterhemp-herbicide-resistance-project-2019-update/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;“Wisconsin Waterhemp Herbicide Resistance Project – 2019 Update”&lt;/a&gt;  for an in depth look at those results).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting in 2018 (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/img/2018%20waterhemp%20challenge/Waterhemp%20Management%20PRE%20Comparison_Lancaster%20WI%202018.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;“2018 UW-Waterhemp Challenge: Comparison of Soil Residual Soybean Herbicides”&lt;/a&gt;), and replicated in 2019, a study was conducted to evaluate and demonstrate the effectiveness of multiple PRE-emergence soybean herbicides. This was a joint effort between the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ipcm.wisc.edu/npm/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;UW-Madison Nutrient and Pest Management Program&lt;/a&gt; (NPM; Dan Smith and Richard Proost) and the UW-Madison Cropping Systems Weed Science team. The study was conducted both years at &lt;a href=&#34;https://lancaster.ars.wisc.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;UW Lancaster Ag Research Station&lt;/a&gt;, in Lancaster, WI (Grant Co; Southwest WI) in fields naturally infested with waterhemp. Treatments consisted of PRE-emergence soybean herbicides with one, two, or three different active ingredient(s) and/or site(s) of action (SOA). Herbicide rates tested in this study were selected based on recommendations for a typical WI Silt Loam soil. Herbicides were sprayed within 3 days after soybean planting and visual efficacy data collected at 25 and 50 days after treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When selecting a PRE-herbicide program, it is important to balance efficacy and product cost. Always consider soil characteristics, geographic restrictions and crop rotation when determining which products and rates to use in your PRE-emergence herbicide program. The residual activity of a PRE-emergence herbicide is dependent on the rate applied; cutting rates is not a recommended strategy when attempting to manage troublesome weeds like waterhemp. &lt;strong&gt;Always read, understand, and follow the pesticide label.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To download the &lt;a href=&#34;/img/2018 2019 waterhemp challenge/PreEmergence_waterhempFINAL.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Residual Control of Waterhemp with PRE-emergence Herbicides in Soybean&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; Article (PDF file) click HERE&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for additional research updates related to control of waterhemp and other troublesome weeds in Wisconsin as well summer plot tour opportunities in 2020!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 2019 waterhemp challenge/2018 25 DAT.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 2019 waterhemp challenge/2018 50 DAT.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure2&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 2019 waterhemp challenge/2019 25 DAT.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure3&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 2019 waterhemp challenge/2019 50 DAT.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure4&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take-Home from the “Residual Control of Waterhemp with PRE-emergence Herbicides in Soybean” Publication:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Due to its genetic variability, wide emergence window, vigorous growth potential, and prolific seed production, waterhemp has become a troublesome weed in soybean cropping systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wisconsin research summarized herein demonstrates the effectiveness of incorporating pre-emergence herbicides into waterhemp management programs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Effective herbicide programs should be determined on a field to field basis taking into consideration soil properties, geographic restrictions, subsequent crop(s), and soil seedbank weed species composition, pressure, and presence of herbicide resistance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sustainable management of herbicide-resistant waterhemp populations requires a holistic integrated approach incorporating cultural and/or mechanical practices alongside chemical herbicide programs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember, don’t let them seed. No seed, no weed!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgements:&lt;/strong&gt; We would like to thank Mimi Broeske, UW-NPM Senior Editor, for developing the publication layout. Members of the UW-Madison Cropping Systems Weed Science Lab helped with study establishment and data collection. Thanks to Doug Wiedenbeck and the UW Lancaster Ag Research Station staff for their support. Thanks to industry colleagues who helped in developing the rate structure for this study. This study was partially funded by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://wisoybean.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Wisconsin Soybean Marketing Board&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt;: Nicholas Arneson (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist), Dan Smith (UW NPM Southwest Wisconsin Regional Specialist), Ryan Dewerff (UW-Madison Weed Science Research Specialist), Maxwel Coura Oliveira (UW-Madison (UW-Madison Weed Science Postdoctoral Research Associate), and Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/headers/2019WiscWeedsTeam.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2019-wiscweeds-team&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2019 WiscWeeds Team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2019 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report</title>
      <link>/post/2019-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;by Ryan DeWerff (UW-Madison Weed Science Research Specialist), Nicholas Arneson (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist), and &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this report is to share the results of corn and soybean herbicide evaluation research trials conducted by the Wisconsin Cropping Systems Weed Science Program during the 2019 growing season. Information in this report does not constitute a recommendation or endorsement of any particular product or practice. Information in this report also does not replace any information presented on herbicide labels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;to-download-the-2019-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-click-here-pdf-file-img-2019-research-report-2019-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2019 Research Report/2019 Wisconsin Weed science Research Report.pdf&#34;&gt;To download the 2019 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report, CLICK HERE (PDF FILE).&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please do not reproduce information presented within this report for public distribution without the expressed written consent from Dr. Rodrigo Werle.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2019-research-trials&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2019 Research Trials:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;corn-weed-control-trials&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Corn Weed Control Trials&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bayer Integrated Corn Herbicide Programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corn Herbicide Evaluation: 1 and 2-pass Programs with Atrazine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corn Herbicide Evaluation: 1 and 2-pass Programs without Atrazine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Systems Approach to Weed Management in Corn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Corn Herbicide Soil Residual Activity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;soybean-weed-control-trials&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Soybean Weed Control Trials&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;XtendFlex Soybean Herbicide Programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Soybean Herbicide Evaluation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UPL Preemergence Soybean Herbicide Programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enlist Weed Control System in Soybean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Systems Approach to Weed Control in Xtend Soybeans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spray Early with Confidence Program in Xtend Soybean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tavium Plus VaporGrip Efficacy in Xtend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Authority Brand Programs Efficacy in Soybean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Soybean Soil Residual Herbicides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Utility of Layering Residual Herbicides in Soybean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liberty and Enlist One/Enlist Duo Efficacy in Enlist Soybean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Valent Herbicides in a Liberty Link System&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bareground-weed-control-trials&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bareground Weed Control Trials&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fall vs Spring Burndown Control of Dandelion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engenia, Enlist One, and Liberty Burndown Efficacy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Postemergence Control of Waterhemp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/headers/2019WiscWeedsTeam.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2019-wiscweeds-team&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2019 WiscWeeds Team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Herbicide Comparison for Residual Waterhemp Control in Corn</title>
      <link>/post/herbicide-comparison-for-residual-waterhemp-control-in-corn/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/herbicide-comparison-for-residual-waterhemp-control-in-corn/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Waterhemp management has become a major challenge for several corn and soybean farmers in Wisconsin and beyond. Waterhemp has an extended emergence window and is a competitive, prolific and genetically diverse weed species which has evolved resistance to commonly used corn and soybean herbicides across the Midwest (see &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/wisconsin-waterhemp-herbicide-resistance-project-2019-update/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2019 Wisconsin Waterhemp Herbicide Resistance Project Update&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). The use of soil residual herbicides is a foundation for waterhemp control and given that several effective and flexible herbicide options in terms of application window (PRE through early-POST) are available for corn, this crop provides farmers with a good opportunity for effective waterhemp management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2019 we conducted a study to evaluate and demonstrate the effectiveness of multiple soil-applied corn herbicides. The study was conducted at a grower’s field south of Brooklyn, Dane county, WI in a field with natural and significant waterhemp infestation as part of our &lt;strong&gt;WiscWeeds Waterhemp Management Challenge&lt;/strong&gt; educational efforts. Treatments consisted of corn herbicides containing one or multiple sites of action (SOA). Herbicides were sprayed when corn reached the V2 growth stage. Visual evaluation data on a 0-100% scale (0% indicating no waterhemp control and 100% indicating complete control) were collected at 25 and 50 days after treatment (DAT). Since the objective was to evaluate soil residual activity, Liberty (32 fl oz per acre) was tank-mixed to all treatments to eliminate established waterhemp plants at the time of herbicide application (corn hybrid used in this study was LibertyLink). Two treatments were intentionally applied off-label in this study given their relevance in our state and thus the importance of collecting their soil residual efficacy data: Princep 4FL and Verdict (these products are labeled PRE-emergence only in corn).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To download the 2019 Preliminary Report of the “&lt;strong&gt;WiscWeeds Herbicide Comparison for Residual Waterhemp Control in Corn&lt;/strong&gt;” (PDF file) click &lt;a href=&#34;/img/2019 corn residual/WiscWeeds Herbicide Comparison for Residual Waterhemp Control in Corn.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HERE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2019 corn residual/25 dat corn.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;25 DAT&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2019 corn residual/50 dat corn.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;50 DAT&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2019 corn residual/IMG_2766.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Natural Infestation&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The herbicide rates used in the study are ones recommended by our industry colleagues and supported by us for a typical Wisconsin Silt Loam soil. In this report we also include site and study information, and the equivalent rate of single active ingredient products in the premixes evaluated (herbicides with multiple active ingredients). Our intent with this study is not to promote one product versus another, instead, demonstrate the value of using an effective soil residual programs for waterhemp control in corn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;take-home&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take-Home&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When selecting a soil-applied herbicide program, we challenge agronomists and farmers to balance efficacy (using our results and their experience), product cost, and rotation restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also encourage farmers to compare their use rates with the ones used in our study (recommended by industry representatives and respective product labels), assuming Silt Loam soils. The residual activity of a soil-applied herbicide is dependent on the rates applied; cutting rates is not a recommended strategy when attempting to manage troublesome weeds like waterhemp.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;PRE-emergence herbicide programs containing multiple effective sites of action are recommended to broaden weed control spectrum and to lower selection for additional herbicide resistance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When selecting a commercial premix, note that not all active ingredients may be considered effective. For instance, Halex GT contains 3 SOA (glyphosate, Group 9; S-metolachlor, Group 15; mesotrione, Group 27) but only two will provide effective soil residual control for waterhemp (S-metolachlor, Group 15; mesotrione, Group 27).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these results should be taken with a grain of salt (only one year of data), they clearly indicate the value of effective soil residual herbicides. This study will be replicated in 2020. Stay tuned for additional research findings related to our waterhemp control studies and also plot tour opportunities in 2020!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Always read, understand and follow the pesticide label.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/strong&gt;: we would like to thank the &lt;strong&gt;Wisconsin Corn Promotion Board&lt;/strong&gt; for supporting this project and Industry Representatives for assisting with treatment structure and providing chemicals for trial establishment. Members of the Wisconsin Cropping Systems Weed Science Lab provided technical assistance towards the execution of this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Weed Scientist), Nicholas Arneson (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist), and Ryan DeWerff (UW-Madison Weed Science Research Specialist).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wisconsin Waterhemp Herbicide Resistance Project - 2019 Update</title>
      <link>/post/wisconsin-waterhemp-herbicide-resistance-project-2019-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/wisconsin-waterhemp-herbicide-resistance-project-2019-update/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Felipe Faleco (UW-Madison Agronomy Graduate Student), &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/dave-stoltenberg/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;David Stoltenberg&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Agronomy Professor), &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/mark-renz/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mark Renz&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Weed Scientist) and &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Weed Scientist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Waterhemp&lt;/strong&gt; is a competitive, prolific and genetically diverse weed species which has evolved resistance to commonly used corn and soybean herbicides across the Midwest. In Wisconsin, waterhemp populations have been confirmed resistant to three sites of action (SOA): ALS (acetolactate synthase; Group 2), EPSPS (enolpyruvyl shikimate phosphate synthase; Group 9), and/or PPO-inhibitor herbicides (protoporphyrinogin oxidase; Group 14). Glyphosate resistance has been confirmed in 28 Wisconsin counties and multiple resistance to glyphosate and PPO-inhibitors has been confirmed in 10 of these counties. For more information on the status of herbicide resistance in Wisconsin click &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/herbicide-resistance-in-wisconsin-an-overview/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HERE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identifying the distribution of herbicide resistance in waterhemp to commonly used herbicides is vital for the selection of appropriate management strategies. The &lt;strong&gt;objective&lt;/strong&gt; of this study was to determine the frequency and distribution of glyphosate (EPSPS; Group 9), imazethapyr (ALS; Group 2) and atrazine (photosystem II [PSII]; Group 5)-resistant waterhemp populations in Wisconsin corn and soybean production systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2019 waterhemp resistance update/Glyphosate.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Glyphosate&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Out of 86 waterhemp populations screened, 95% and 70% were confirmed resistant to 1x and 3x label rate of &lt;strong&gt;glyphosate&lt;/strong&gt;, respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2019 waterhemp resistance update/Imazethapyr.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Imazethapyr&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Out of 82 waterhemp populations screened, 98% and 93% were confirmed resistant to 1x and 3x label rate of &lt;strong&gt;imazethapyr&lt;/strong&gt;, respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2019 waterhemp resistance update/Atrazine.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Atrazine&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Out of 80 waterhemp populations screened, 10% and 3% were confirmed resistant to 1x and 3x label rate of &lt;strong&gt;atrazine&lt;/strong&gt;, respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Glyphosate and imazethapyr-resistant waterhemp populations are widespread across corn and soybean fields in Wisconsin, requiring awareness and action from stakeholders to mitigate their detrimental impacts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Atrazine restrictions in Wisconsin may partially explain the lower than expected resistance frequency. Atrazine resistance in waterhemp populations from other Midwestern states is more common.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Understanding the distribution of waterhemp resistance and selection of effective PRE and POST emergence herbicides can assist growers develop better management strategies and ameliorate the issues with herbicide resistance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;future-directions&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Future Directions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A subset of populations will be selected and further studies will be conducted to evaluate the response of these populations to other herbicides applied POST (lactofen, mesotrione, glufosinate, 2,4-D and dicamba) or PRE (atrazine, mesotrione, metribuzin, sulfentrazone and &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;-metolachlor).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgments&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank the &lt;strong&gt;Wisconsin Soybean Marketing Board&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;Wisconsin Corn Promotion Board&lt;/strong&gt; for supporting this project. Many thanks to those who contributed to this project by collecting waterhemp seeds (individual reports to collaborators will be submitted in January 2020). Members of the Wisconsin Cropping Systems Weed Science Lab provided technical assistance towards the execution of this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-methods&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research Methods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;86 waterhemp populations from 27 Wisconsin counties were collected and submitted by stakeholders in the fall of 2018 (many thanks to those who contributed to this &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/wisconsin-waterhemp-herbicide-resistance-project/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by collecting waterhemp seeds).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Experimental units consisted of cone-tainers (656 ml) filled with Pro-Mix HP Mycorrhizae potting mix. Plants were maintained in a greenhouse with a controlled environment, watered daily and fertilized once a week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Treatments were applied when waterhemp plants reached 2-4 inches in height using a single-nozzle research track spray chamber with AI9502EVS nozzle tips, calibrated to deliver 15 GPA of spray solution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Treatments consisted of &lt;strong&gt;glyphosate&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;1X&lt;/strong&gt; = Roundup PowerMax at 22 fl oz/acre and &lt;strong&gt;3X&lt;/strong&gt; = Roundup PowerMax at 66 fl oz/acre), imazethapyr (&lt;strong&gt;1X&lt;/strong&gt; = Pursuit at 4 fl oz/acre and &lt;strong&gt;3X&lt;/strong&gt; = Pursuit at 12 fl oz/acre), atrazine (&lt;strong&gt;1X&lt;/strong&gt;= Aatrex 4L at 2 pts/acre and 3X = Aatrex 4L at 6 pts/acre), and the &lt;strong&gt;nontreated control&lt;/strong&gt;. AMS (2 lbs/acre) was added to the glyphosate treatments. AMS (2 lbs/acre) + COC (0.6% v/v) were added to the imazethapyr treatments. COC (0.8%) v/v was added to the atrazine treatments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The experiment was conducted in a completely randomized design with 8 replications per herbicide treatment and two experimental runs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;21 days after treatment (DAT) visual evaluation (VE) of plant growth was taken on a scale of 1 to 10 (1 representing a dead plant and 10 a completely healthy plant, Figure 1) and aboveground biomass harvested.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Waterhemp populations were considered resistant to each treatment if 50% or more of treated plants between experimental runs had VE ≥ 7 (healthy plants completely capable of reproducing).
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2019 waterhemp resistance update/Visual Scale.png&#34; alt=&#34;Visual Evaluation&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Survey: Wisconsin Soybean Herbicide Tolerance Trait Selection (2019 &amp; 2020)</title>
      <link>/post/survey-wisconsin-soybean-herbicide-tolerance-trait-selection-2019-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/survey-wisconsin-soybean-herbicide-tolerance-trait-selection-2019-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist) and &lt;a href=&#34;http://coolbean.info/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Shawn Conley&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Soybean and Small Grain Specialist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Shawn Conley and team &lt;a href=&#34;https://coolbean.info/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;(Coolbean.info)&lt;/a&gt; recently released the 2019 yield data from their soybean variety trials conducted across the state of Wisconsin and concluded that no yield differences were observed across herbicide tolerance traits within nor across regions (Enlist E3, RR2 Xtend and LLGT27):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2020 Soybean HT Survey/2020 Trait Slide Conley.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;small&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Herein, we would like to ask Wisconsin soybean producers and decision influencers to help us better understand herbicide tolerance trait and POST-emergence herbicide adoption in 2019 and their plans for 2020. This information will be of great value to our educational efforts during this Extension season and research efforts during 2020 and beyond. The survey has 30 questions and should take less than 10 minutes of your time. To start the online survey, please click &lt;a href=&#34;https://uwmadison.co1.qualtrics.com/jfe/form/SV_5dOy1FC5lt3EMp7&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HERE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://uwmadison.co1.qualtrics.com/jfe/form/SV_5dOy1FC5lt3EMp7&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://uwmadison.co1.qualtrics.com/jfe/form/SV_5dOy1FC5lt3EMp7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your time and Happy Holidays!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
