<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wisconsin Weed Science on Wisconsin Weed Science</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Wisconsin Weed Science on Wisconsin Weed Science</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2022 WiscWeeds</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Winter Wheat Rotational Restrictions Following Common Soybean Residual Herbicides</title>
      <link>/post/winter-wheat-rotational-restrictions-following-common-soybean-residual-herbicides/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/winter-wheat-rotational-restrictions-following-common-soybean-residual-herbicides/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;With the widespread occurrence of herbicide-resistant weeds across Wisconsin soybean and corn production acres there has been increased adoption of soil residual herbicides for improved season-long weed control. The primary way growers are bringing residual herbicides into their soybean and corn systems is through PRE-emergence (PRE) applications. The WiscWeeds team firmly believes that PRE herbicides are the foundation for effective chemical weed control (see &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wiscweeds.info/img/2018%202019%20waterhemp%20challenge/PreEmergence_waterhempFINAL.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;“Residual Control of Waterhemp with PRE Herbicides in Soybean”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wiscweeds.info/img/2021%20PMU%20Handouts/2021%20WiscWeeds%20Herbicide%20Comparison%20for%20Residual%20Weed%20Control%20in%20Corn.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;“Herbicide Comparison for Residual Weed Control in Corn”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;). Unfortunately, PRE herbicides alone may not be enough to achieve season-long control of troublesome weeds such as waterhemp. Waterhemp emerges throughout the bulk of the growing season and is forcing growers to consider adopting a &lt;strong&gt;‘layered residual’&lt;/strong&gt; approach with their herbicide programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The layered residual approach is a strategy where herbicides with soil residual activity are applied PRE (i.e., near the time of crop planting) and then at the time for a POST-emergence (POST) application an additional residual herbicide is added to the tank to overlap soil residual control of weeds that are yet to emerge. The layered residual concept is summarized nicely in the Iowa State University blog post by Dr. Hartzler &amp;amp; Anderson: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://crops.extension.iastate.edu/cropnews/2019/02/achieving-full-season-waterhemp-control-soybean&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Achieving Full-season Waterhemp Control in Soybean&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;). Oftentimes, the residual herbicides tank-mixed with a foliar POST application in soybean consist of Group 15 herbicides (e.g., acetochlor [Warrant], S-metolachlor [Dual II Magnum], dimethenamid-P [Outlook], and pyroxasulfone [Zidua]). The WiscWeeds program has gathered years of data suggesting that the layered residual approach can result in season-long control of glyphosate-resistant waterhemp (see pgs. 62-65 in &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wiscweeds.info/img/2020%20Research%20Report/2020%20Wisconsin%20Weed%20science%20Research%20Report.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;“2020 WI Weed Science Research Report”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One complication that goes along with the adoption of the layered residual approach would be herbicide rotational restrictions for winter wheat. According to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/shawn-conley/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Shawn Conley&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, most of the winter wheat acres planted in Wisconsin follow soybeans (see &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://coolbean.info/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;CoolBean.info&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; blog post: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://coolbean.info/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2021/01/EarlySoybeanWheat_Final.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;“Choosing Soybean Varieties for Rotation with Winter Wheat&amp;rdquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;). We are aware that growers who plant winter wheat following harvest of their soybean crop may have difficulty including a layered residual herbicide in their soybean POST program as many products require 4 months or more after application before planting winter wheat. Dr. Conley recommends the window of September 20th to October 10th as the ideal window for winter wheat planting (see &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://coolbean.info/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;CoolBean.info&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; blog post: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://coolbean.info/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2021/09/Top-8-Wheat-recs_21.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;“Top 8 Recommendations for Winter Wheat Establishment in 2021”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;). Assuming an October 1st winter wheat planting date, many of the commonly used residual herbicides as part of a POST program would have to be sprayed by June 1st to remain on-label. One opportunity that we have identified for growers looking to adopt the layered residual approach and planting winter wheat following soybean harvest would be using a reduced Zidua SC rate (3.25 fl oz/acre or less) which requires only a 1-month rotational restriction for winter wheat. Adjusting the time of the POST application in soybean (i.e., spraying earlier) and slightly delaying winter wheat planting to match rotational restrictions represent another opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that multiple agronomists and growers have reached out to us with this question/concern, the WiscWeeds team put together a short report summarizing commonly used soybean residual herbicides and their winter wheat rotational restrictions according to their respective labels. The intention of this resource is to help guide growers in a soybean-wheat rotation who might be battling herbicide-resistant weeds, including waterhemp, with herbicide selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;a href=&#34;/img/2022 wheat following soy/Residual Plant Back Restrictions for Wheat.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HERE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to download the PDF report: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2022 wheat following soy/Residual Plant Back Restrictions for Wheat.pdf&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Winter Wheat Rotational Restrictions Following Common Soybean Residual Herbicides&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please remember to always read, follow, and understand the pesticide label.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nick Arneson&lt;/strong&gt;, Weed Science Program Outreach Manager, Department of Agronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ryan DeWerff&lt;/strong&gt;, Weed Science Research Specialist, Department of Agronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rodrigo Werle,&lt;/strong&gt; Assistant Professor and Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist, Department of Agronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/headers/2021WiscWeedsTeam.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2021-wiscweeds-team&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2021 WiscWeeds Team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2021 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report</title>
      <link>/post/2021-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;by &lt;strong&gt;Ryan DeWerff&lt;/strong&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Research Specialist and Wisconsin Herbicide Evaluation Program Coordinator), &lt;strong&gt;Nick Arneson&lt;/strong&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist), and &lt;strong&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/strong&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2021-research-report&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2021 Research Report&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this report is to share the results of corn and soybean herbicide evaluation research trials conducted by the Wisconsin Cropping Systems Weed Science Program during the 2021 growing season. Information in this report does not constitute a recommendation or endorsement of any particular product or practice. Information in this report also does not replace any information presented on herbicide labels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;to-download-the-2021-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-click-here-pdf-img-2021-research-report-2021-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/2021 Wisconsin Weed science Research Report.pdf&#34;&gt;To download the 2021 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report, CLICK HERE (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2021-visual-research-reports&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2021 Visual Research Reports&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the visual research reports is to share field images from some of the corn and soybean herbicide evaluation research trials conducted by the Wisconsin Cropping Systems Weed Science Program during the 2021 growing season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2021 Corn Weed Control Trials (field images):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/Evaluation of Corn PRE-Emergence Herbicides.pdf&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Corn PRE-Emergence Herbicides (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/Weed Control and Crop Safety with EPOST Herbicide Applications.pdf&#34;&gt;Weed Control and Crop Safety with EPOST Herbicide Applications (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/Shieldex Weed Control and Crop Safety.pdf&#34;&gt;Shieldex Weed Control and Crop Safety (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/Reviton Burndown Programs in Corn.pdf&#34;&gt;Reviton Burndown Programs in Corn (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/Restraint Weed Control and Crop Safety.pdf&#34;&gt;Restraint Weed Control and Crop Safety (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/POST and Sequential Weed Control with Maverick.pdf&#34;&gt;POST and Sequential Weed Control with Maverick (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/Evaluation of Acuron GT in a Two-Pass System.pdf&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Acuron GT in a Two-Pass System (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/Corn Herbicide Showcase.pdf&#34;&gt;Corn Herbicide Showcase (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/Bayer and Valent Corn Herbicide Programs.pdf&#34;&gt;Bayer and Valent Corn Herbicide Programs (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2021 Soybean Weed Control Trials (field images):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/XtendiMax Paired Soil Residual Herbicide Programs.pdf&#34;&gt;XtendiMax Paired Soil Residual Herbicide Programs (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/XtendFlex Soybean Herbicide Programs.pdf&#34;&gt;XtendFlex Soybean Herbicide Programs (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/XtendFlex Soybean Herbicide Programs for ESA Counties.pdf&#34;&gt;XtendFlex Soybean Herbicide Programs for ESA Counties (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/Reviton Burndown Programs in Soybean.pdf&#34;&gt;Reviton Burndown Programs in Soybean (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/MON 301668 Residual Weed Control and Crop Safety.pdf&#34;&gt;MON 301668 Residual Weed Control and Crop Safety (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/Liberty Tank Mix Combinations - Crop Tolerance.pdf&#34;&gt;Liberty Tank Mix Combinations - Crop Tolerance (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/Evaluation ofTendovo for Residual Weed Control and Crop Safety.pdf&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Tendovo for Residual Weed Control and Crop Safety (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/Evaluation of Preview 2.1SC for Residual Weed Control and Crop Safety.pdf&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Preview 2.1SC for Residual Weed Control and Crop Safety (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/Evaluation of Layered Residual Herbicide Programs in Enlist Soybean.pdf&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Layered Residual Herbicide Programs in Enlist Soybean (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/Authority Supreme-Edge and Anthem Maxx Herbicide Programs.pdf&#34;&gt;Authority Supreme-Edge and Anthem Maxx Herbicide Programs (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2021 Bareground Weed Control Trials (field images):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Research Report/Burndown Control of Giant Ragweed.pdf&#34;&gt;Burndown Control of Giant Ragweed (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kudos to &lt;strong&gt;Ryan DeWerff&lt;/strong&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Research Specialist and WI Herbicide Evaluation Program Coordinator) for generating these reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/headers/2021WiscWeedsTeam.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2021-wiscweeds-team&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2021 WiscWeeds Team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two pass weed control programs in conventional corn</title>
      <link>/post/two-pass-weed-control-programs-in-conventional-corn/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/two-pass-weed-control-programs-in-conventional-corn/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year we met with the O’Brien brothers, Dan and Mark, to discuss our waterhemp research plans at their farm for the 2021 growing season. During our meeting, Dan and Mark asked if we could conduct a study looking at herbicide programs in conventional corn given they produce seed corn in an atrazine prohibition area in Wisconsin and were having a difficult time controlling waterhemp and annual grasses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the assistance of our lab, Ryan DeWerff (Weed Science Research Specialist) developed and conducted a study evaluating multiple two pass herbicide programs for weed control in corn without glyphosate and atrazine. The 2021 studies were conducted at the UW Arlington Agricultural Research Station near Arlington, WI and at the O’Brien Family Farms near Brooklyn, WI. Weed control data were collected at and following POST application. Corn yield data were collected only at Arlington; the study at Brooklyn was destroyed before the crop tasseled to avoid cross pollination with the O’Brien’s seed corn production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the ongoing glyphosate shortage, the data from this study is also very relevant to growers who may opt not to use glyphosate in glyphosate-resistant corn and save it for their soybeans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 conventional corn/Herbicide Programs for Conventional Corn_Final Report.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HERE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  to download the complete PDF report with data and plot pictures compiled by Ryan DeWerff: &lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 conventional corn/Herbicide Programs for Conventional Corn_Final Report.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2021 WiscWeeds Comparison of Herbicide Programs for Conventional Corn&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 conventional corn/Table 1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 conventional corn/Table 2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study will be replicated in 2022! Stay tuned and Happy Holidays!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ryan DeWerff&lt;/strong&gt;, Weed Science Research Specialist, Department of Agronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nick Arneson&lt;/strong&gt;, Weed Science Program Outreach Manager, Department of Agronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rodrigo Werle,&lt;/strong&gt; Assistant Professor and Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist, Department of Agronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PRE-emergence Herbicide Selection for Early Planted Soybeans</title>
      <link>/post/pre-emergence-herbicide-selection-for-early-planted-soybeans/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/pre-emergence-herbicide-selection-for-early-planted-soybeans/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Over the last two growing seasons (2020 and 2021), weather and soil conditions across southern Wisconsin were favorable for early soybean planting (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nass.usda.gov/Charts_and_Maps/Crop_Progress_&amp;amp;_Condition/2021/WI_2021.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;USDA NASS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; data below). Under suitable environmental conditions, planting soybean early is a recommended strategy to increase the crop’s yield potential (See Dr. Shawn Conley’s blogpost: &lt;a href=&#34;https://coolbean.info/2021/04/11/just-facts-jack-soybean-planting-date-seeding-rate-seed-treatment-recommendations/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Just the Facts Jack: Soybean Planting Date, Seeding Rate and Seed Treatment Recommendations”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 early planted soybean/Figure 1 USDA.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one of our studies, led by the former Weed Science Graduate Student Nikola Arsenijevic, conducted at Arlington Agricultural Research Station, near Arlington, WI in 2020, the early planted soybeans (April 21, 2020) didn’t emerge until mid-May (May 15, 2020) whereas the standard planted soybeans (May 22, 2020) emerged early June (June 01, 2020). See Arsenijevic&amp;rsquo;s images below. The time from soybean planting to emergence is relevant for PRE-emergence herbicide selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 early planted soybean/Figure 2 Early Planted.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure2&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 early planted soybean/Figure 3 Standard Planted.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure3&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PRE-emergence herbicides represent the foundation for weed control in soybean production systems and are recommended for management of weed species with extended emergence window. Additionally, the use of PRE-emergence herbicides is considered a crucial component for integrated management of weeds resistant to glyphosate and other POST-emergence herbicides. Some PRE-emergence herbicides persist in the soil to provide several weeks of residual control of small seeded weeds, reducing the reliance on and the need for multiple POST-emergence applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PRE-emergence herbicide products available for soybeans consist of either a single active ingredient site of action (SOA), or a premix with multiple active ingredients from multiple SOAs. According to our research (see: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wiscweeds.info/img/2018%202019%20waterhemp%20challenge/PreEmergence_waterhempFINAL.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Residual Control of Waterhemp with Pre-emergence Herbicides in Soybean”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), PRE-emergence herbicides containing 2 or more effective SOAs provide better control of a wider range of weed species when compared to the use of a single SOA. Using multiple effective SOAs during each pass is also a proactive strategy for herbicide resistance management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To maximize their residual activity in-season, PRE-emergence herbicides should be sprayed at or shortly after planting. PRE-emergence herbicides need moisture for incorporation and activation in the soil. The flip side is that when PRE-emergence herbicides are sprayed shortly before crop emergence, the risk of crop injury increases, mainly under cool and wet soil conditions during crop emergence. Several effective soybean PRE-emergence herbicides should be applied up to 3 days after planting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sulfentrazone (Spartan) and flumioxazin (Valor) containing herbicides should be sprayed within 3 days from planting according to their product labels as a strategy to minimize crop injury (e.g., Valor XLT, Enlite, Trivence, Surveil, Fierce, Fierce XLT, Fierce MTZ/Kyber, Afforia, Sonic/Authority First, Authority Assist, Authority MTZ, Authority Supreme, Authority Elite/BroadAxe XC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saflufenacil (Sharpen) and metribuzin (Tricor) allow a little more flexibility and can be sprayed after soybean planting but before crop emergence (Canopy DF, Boundary, Verdict, Zidua PRO).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acetochlor (Warrant), dimethenamid-P (Outlook), S-metolachlor (Dual II Magnum), pyroxasulfone (Zidua), chlorimuron-ethyl (Classic), cloransulam-methyl (FirstRate), imazethapyr (Pursuit), and fomesafen (Flexstar) can be sprayed after soybean emergence (e.g., Prefix, Warrant Ultra, Anthem Maxx, Perpetuo; POST-emergence application window is herbicide specific).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned information is intended to address the following questions we have been receiving regarding PRE-emergence herbicide selection for early planted soybeans:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can I skip a PRE-emergence application in early planted soybeans and control weeds POST only?&lt;/strong&gt; We recommend against that. The use of an effective PRE-emergence herbicide is the foundation for chemical weed control in soybeans. Limited effective POST-emergence herbicide options are available for control of herbicide-resistant weed species such as waterhemp and giant ragweed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can I delay my PRE-emergence application in early planted soybeans?&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, one could do so by selecting herbicides with soil residual activity that can be sprayed before crop emergence instead of herbicides that must be sprayed within 3 days of crop planting, particularly when the soybean crop is being planted early in the spring, is not expected to emerge for several weeks, and weeds are not actively emerging due to low soil temperatures. Keep in mind that PRE-emergence herbicides are effective if timely incorporated (by light tillage and/or precipitation) and active in top soil solution as weeds germinate and emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all that in mind, we developed the following handy table displaying the application window of commonly used herbicides with soil residual activity in soybean cropping systems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 PMU Handouts/Soybean PRE Herbicide Application Window.pdf&#34;&gt;Application Window for Soybean Herbicides with Soil Residual Activity (PDF) - Click to Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;Inclusion of specific products does not constitute a recommendation or endorsement. Always read and follow the pesticide label. &lt;strong&gt;The label is the law.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;additional-resources&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Additional resources&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2018 2019 waterhemp challenge/PreEmergence_waterhempFINAL.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Residual Control of Waterhemp with PRE-emergence Herbicides in Soybean&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/Update Series Articles/WWRUS Article 5_Efficacy of Soybean PRE Herbicides in Greenhouse Bioassays.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WISCWEEDS RESEARCH UPDATE SERIES, Article 5: Evaluating efficacy of preemergence soybean herbicides using field treated soil in greenhouse bioassays&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/2020 Wisconsin Weed science Research Report.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rodrigo Werle,&lt;/strong&gt; Assistant Professor and Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist, Department of Agronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nick Arneson&lt;/strong&gt;, Weed Science Program Outreach Manager, Department of Agronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ryan DeWerff&lt;/strong&gt;, Weed Science Research Specialist, Department of Agronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2021 Wisconsin Waterhemp Herbicide Resistance Project (2,4-D, dicamba &amp; glufosinate)</title>
      <link>/post/2021-wisconsin-waterhemp-herbicide-resistance-project-2-4-d-dicamba-and-glufosinate/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021-wisconsin-waterhemp-herbicide-resistance-project-2-4-d-dicamba-and-glufosinate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year we received a few complaints regarding lack of performance of &lt;strong&gt;dicamba&lt;/strong&gt; (XtendiMax, Engenia, Status), &lt;strong&gt;2,4-D&lt;/strong&gt; (Enlist One) and/or &lt;strong&gt;glufosinate&lt;/strong&gt; (Liberty) on POST control of waterhemp in corn and soybean fields in Wisconsin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We invite Wisconsin farmers and agronomists to collect waterhemp seeds this fall from their row crop production fields where one of these three herbicides failed to provide effective POST control and submit them to UW-Madison for herbicide resistance screenings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no cost associated to the herbicide resistance screening. The only cost will be your time to collect the seed samples and mail them to: &lt;strong&gt;Rodrigo Werle, 1575 Linden Drive, Madison, WI 53706.&lt;/strong&gt; We intend to screen all waterhemp samples in the greenhouse for resistance to 2,4-D, dicamba and glufosinate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please download the &lt;a href=&#34;/img/2018 waterhemp seed collection/2021 WiscWeeds Waterhemp Seed Project.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SEED COLLECTION FORM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (PDF file) for information on how to collect the waterhemp seeds for the project. Please fill out the information necessary for each waterhemp sample collected &lt;a href=&#34;https://uwmadison.co1.qualtrics.com/jfe/form/SV_3wQ6hrFrjfR0FrU&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ONLINE (Qualtrics Survey)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;submit the form with the seed sample. Samples will only be included in the herbicide resistance screening if the information requested herein is provided by the farmer/agronomist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For questions, please contact Rodrigo Werle via e-mail: &lt;strong&gt;rwerle@wisc.edu&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thank the &lt;strong&gt;Wisconsin Soybean Marketing Board&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;Take Action Program&lt;/strong&gt; for supporting this project and also those submitting the waterhemp seed samples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rodrigo Werle,&lt;/strong&gt; Assistant Professor and Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist, Department of Agronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Felipe Faleco,&lt;/strong&gt; Weed Science Graduate Student, Department of Agronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nick Arneson&lt;/strong&gt;, Weed Science Outreach Specialist, Department of Agronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2021 Waterhemp Management Plot Tour (O&#39;Brien Hybrids Farm, Brooklyn, WI)</title>
      <link>/post/2021-waterhemp-management-plot-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021-waterhemp-management-plot-tour/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Join us on &lt;strong&gt;July 08, 2021 at the O’Brien Hybrids Farm&lt;/strong&gt; (419 Union Road, Brooklyn, WI) to learn more about waterhemp management in corn and soybean production systems. Research plots showcasing comparison of PRE and POST-emergence herbicide programs and cereal rye cover crop will be displayed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Plot Tours/Waterhemp Management Plot Tour 2021.PDF&#34;&gt;event flyer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for complete information:
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 Plot Tours/Waterhemp Management Plot Tour 2021.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Registration starts at 3:45 PM and the plot tour starts at 4:00 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please &lt;strong&gt;RSVP by July 06, 2021 with Nick Arneson&lt;/strong&gt; via E-mail: njarneson@wisc.edu or phone: 402-676-1618.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See directions provided by our hosts Dan and Mark O’Brien:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;From Madison, take Hwy. 14 south past two Oregon exits toward Evansville.  Turn right onto Cty A and continue on A until you come to Union Rd.  Turn left onto Union Rd.  Approx 1.5 miles to plot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;From Madison, take Hwy. 14 South to second Oregon exit (Hwy. 138)  right at round about into Oregon.  Turn left at the Kwik Trip onto Hwy. MM.  Turn right onto Cty A ,  take the first left onto Union Rd.  Travel approx 1.5 miles to plot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;From Madison, take Fish Hatchery Rd south to Lincoln Rd.  Left onto Lincoln Rd.  Approx 2 miles, turn right on to Glenway Rd. Left on to Cty A  Right on to Union Rd.  Travel approx 1.5 miles to plot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;From Evansville, take Hwy. 14 north/west .  Turn left on to Hwy. 92, (east of Brooklyn)  On the west side of Brooklyn, turn right on to Union Rd.  Proceed approx. two miles to plot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Address: 419 Union Road, Brooklyn, WI (GPS Coordinates: 42.8777 -89.3080)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These educational events are being partially sponsored by the Wisconsin Soybean Marketing Board, Wisconsin Corn Promoting Board, United Soybean Board, and the Take Action program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adhering to &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.wisc.edu/covid-19-policy-changes-events-face-coverings-outdoor-physical-distancing/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;UW-Madison requirements&lt;/a&gt; on outdoor university affiliated events, individuals may choose to wear a face covering and those who are not vaccinated to COVID-19 should maintain six feet physical distancing and if physical distancing is not possible, wear a face covering.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope to see you then!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rodrigo Werle,&lt;/strong&gt; Assistant Professor and Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist, Department of Agronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison on behalf of the &lt;strong&gt;WiscWeeds team&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2021 UW Cover Crop Plot Tour</title>
      <link>/post/2021-uw-cover-crop-plot-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021-uw-cover-crop-plot-tour/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A group of farmers from southern Wisconsin recently asked whether they could visit our cover crop research plots at Arlington Agricultural Research Station; our answer was: &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;absolutely; and why not partner up with other UW Extension colleagues and also invite our clientele from other parts of the state?!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Event Description:&lt;/strong&gt; Join us on &lt;em&gt;July 01 from 1:00PM-3:30PM at Arlington Agricultural Research Station&lt;/em&gt; to visit our conventional and organic cover crop research plots, check equipment and exchange knowledge with University Specialists and fellow farmers adopting cover crops in their crop production systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Plot Tours/2021 UW Extension Cover Crop Plot Tour Flyer.PDF&#34;&gt;event flyer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for complete information:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 Plot Tours/2021 UW Extension Cover Crop Plot Tour Flyer.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meet at 12:45PM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Public Events Building, Arlington Agricultural Research Station&lt;br /&gt;
N695 Hopkins Road, Arlington, WI&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Water and soda will be provided during the plot tour (no food will be provided)!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Folks attending this event may also be interested in attending the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://coolbean.info/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2021/06/2021_SmallGrainsFieldDayFlyer.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;UW Small Grain Field Day&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;which will take place the morning of July 01, 10AM-NOON&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adhering to &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.wisc.edu/covid-19-policy-changes-events-face-coverings-outdoor-physical-distancing/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;UW-Madison requirements&lt;/a&gt; on outdoor university affiliated events, individuals may choose to wear a face covering and those who are not vaccinated to COVID-19 should maintain six feet physical distancing and if physical distancing is not possible, wear a face covering.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope to see you then!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/em&gt;, Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist, Department of Agronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison on behalf of the Cover Crop Plot Tour Hosts (&lt;em&gt;Dr. Erin Silva, Dr. Brian Luck, Mike Bertram, Nick Arneson, et al.&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions? Please email &lt;strong&gt;rwerle@wisc.edu&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2021 Giant Ragweed Management Plot Tour</title>
      <link>/post/giant-ragweed-management-plot-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/giant-ragweed-management-plot-tour/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to announce our &lt;strong&gt;2021 WiscWeeds Giant Ragweed Management Plot Tour&lt;/strong&gt; (June 11, 2021 from 10:00AM to noon at Rock County Farm).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rock County Farm address: 200 US-14, Janesville, WI.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giant ragweed is ranked as the 2nd most troublesome weed species in Wisconsin row crop production according to our recent surveys. To learn more about giant ragweed management in corn and soybean, join us for a tour of our research plots at the Rock County Farm showcasing comparison of multiple PRE and POST-emergence herbicide programs and cereal rye cover crop. Come prepared to gather you own data on giant ragweed control and collect good images from our studies!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RSVP and questions please contact &lt;strong&gt;Nick Arneson&lt;/strong&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist, Email: njarneson@wisc.edu or Phone: 402-676-1618). See &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 Plot Tours/Giant Ragweed Management Challenge Plot Tour 2021.PDF&#34;&gt;event flyer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for complete information:
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 Plot Tours/Giant Ragweed Management Challenge Plot Tour 2021.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adhering to &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.wisc.edu/covid-19-policy-changes-events-face-coverings-outdoor-physical-distancing/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;UW-Madison requirements&lt;/a&gt; on outdoor university affiliated events, individuals may choose to wear a face covering and those who are not vaccinated to COVID-19 should maintain six feet physical distancing and if physical distancing is not possible, wear a face covering.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope to see you then!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rodrigo Werle,&lt;/strong&gt; Assistant Professor and Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist, Department of Agronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison on behalf of the &lt;strong&gt;WiscWeeds team&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Influence of Sentris and VaporGrip Xtra on spray solution pH of Dicamba &#43; Glyphosate tank mixes</title>
      <link>/post/influence-of-sentris-and-vaporgrip-xtra-on-spray-solution-ph-of-dicamba-glyphosate-tank-mixes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/influence-of-sentris-and-vaporgrip-xtra-on-spray-solution-ph-of-dicamba-glyphosate-tank-mixes/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;As an additional measure to minimize the potential for off-site movement of dicamba, an approved volatility reduction agent (VRA), or also referred to as pH-buffering agent, is now required by the United States Environmental Protection Agency to be tank mixed with over-the-top dicamba products (i.e., Engenia, Tavium plus VaporGrip, and XtendiMax with VaporGrip). These buffering agents reduce changes in spray solution pH by scavenging available protons in solution thus reducing the formation of dicamba acid (volatile form of dicamba).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While our lab has conducted extensive research with the VRA VaporGrip Xtra (potassium acetate as the active ingredient; several products are now commercially available) over the past two years, we haven’t had the opportunity yet to assess the impact of the new BASF VRA Sentris (potassium carbonate as the active ingredient) on spray solution pH, dicamba volatility, and weed control. Our preliminary work conducted with potassium carbonate (pure form) in 2020 in partnership with &lt;a href=&#34;https://ssl.acesag.auburn.edu/directory-new/u/Steve-Li-ebusooxn/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Steve Li&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Extension Specialist and Assistant Professor at Auburn University, indicated that this salt can increase spray solution pH and reduce dicamba volatility (Striegel et al. 2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, &lt;a href=&#34;https://crop-soil-environmental-sciences.uark.edu/people/faculty-directory/uid/trbutts/name/Thomas+R.+Butts/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Tommy Butts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Assistant Professor and Extension Weed Scientist with the University of Arkansas System Division of Agriculture, shared an issue encountered by applicators regarding pressure and foam build up in the spray tank when Sentris and glyphosate were tank mixed (see: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arkansascrops.uada.edu/posts/weeds/sentris-glyphosate-tank-mix-compatibility-problems.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;“Sentris and Glyphosate Tank-Mix Compatibility Problems”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;). The report from Dr. Butts, communication with Dr. Vince Davis, BASF Tech Service Rep for Wisconsin and Northern Illinois, and recent questions from stakeholders about Sentris VRA prompted our lab to run a preliminary solution pH study similar to the work conducted by Striegel et al. 2021 (see: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wiscweeds.info/img/Update%20Series%20Articles/WWRUS%20Article%201_Spray%20Solution%20pH.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;“Spray Solution pH as Influenced by Synthetic Auxin Formulation and Spray Additives”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-methodology&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study Methodology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this study comparing two VRAs (Sentris and VaporGrip Xtra) and two dicamba herbicides (Engenia [dicamba BAPMA salt] and Xtendimax with VaporGrip technology [dicamba DGA salt + VaporGrip), we evaluated the solution pH as products were added to the spray solution following the manufacturers’ tank mix recommendations.
Herbicide solution treatments were prepared by mixing tap water from Arlington Agricultural Research Station, WI (initial pH of water source was 7.64±0.02 [average ± standard error]) with additional components to a total volume of 1L (simulating a 15 GPA carrier volume). Solution pH was measured as components were added and thoroughly agitated in solution. Solution pH was measured using an Oakton pHTestr 50 Waterproof Pocket pH Tester, Premium 50 Series probe. For pH readings, ~100 ml of treatment solution was poured into a disposable plastic cup and 3 readings were taken; solution was then immediately returned to the bottle. Each treatment was replicated 3 times (3 separate bottles). Data were subjected to analysis of variance and means were separated when the treatment effect following the addition of each component was less than P = 0.05 using Fisher’s protected least-significant difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 pH VRA/Figure 1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study Treatments:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;(components within a treatment appear in mixing order)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Water + Sentris (VRA) + Class Act Ridion (water conditioner) + Intact (DRA) + Engenia (dicamba) + Roundup PowerMAX (glyphosate)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Water + Sentris (VRA) + Class Act Ridion (water conditioner) + Intact (DRA) + Xtendimax with VaporGrip (dicamba) + Roundup PowerMAX (glyphosate)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Water + VaporGrip Xtra Agent (VRA) + Class Act Ridion (water conditioner) + Intact (DRA) + Engenia (dicamba) + Roundup PowerMAX (glyphosate)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Water + VaporGrip Xtra Agent (VRA) + Class Act Ridion (water conditioner) + Intact (DRA) + Xtendimax with VaporGrip (dicamba) + Roundup PowerMAX (glyphosate)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product Rates:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VRA:&lt;/strong&gt; Sentris = 8 fl oz/a or VaporGrip Xtra = 20 fl oz/a&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Water conditioner:&lt;/strong&gt; Class Act Ridion = 1% v/v&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drift Reduction Agent (DRA):&lt;/strong&gt; Intact = 0.5% v/v&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dicamba:&lt;/strong&gt; Engenia = 12.8 fl oz/a or XtendiMax with VaporGrip = 22 fl oz/a&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Glyphosate:&lt;/strong&gt; Roundup PowerMAX = 32 fl oz/a&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-results&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 pH VRA/Figure 2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure2&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
Click &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2021 pH VRA/2021 pH VRA Results.PDF&#34;&gt;HERE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to download the PDF version of this slide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;outcomes&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outcomes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VRA comparison:&lt;/strong&gt; Sentris had a bigger impact increasing solution pH when compared to VaporGrip Xtra&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Water conditioner:&lt;/strong&gt; Class Act Ridion didn’t have a major impact on solution pH&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DRA:&lt;/strong&gt; Intact didn’t have a major impact on solution pH&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dicamba comparison:&lt;/strong&gt; Engenia treatments had a slightly higher solution pH when compared to Xtendimax with VaporGrip treatments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impact of glyphosate:&lt;/strong&gt; glyphosate had a bigger impact on reducing solution pH in the Sentris treatments when compared to VaporGrip Xtra; however, the final solution pH was higher for the treatments containing Sentris (6.03-6.16) when compared to VaporGrip Xtra (5.24-5.28)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Future work:&lt;/strong&gt; we intend to evaluate the impact of Sentris on dicamba volatility and broad spectrum weed control during the 2021 growing season&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recommendations&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommendations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always follow the product label, including the recommended product mixing order&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To mitigate dicamba off-site movement via vapor drift, the use of a VRA is now mandatory for over-the-top applications of dicamba in dicamba-tolerant soybeans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When using an inductor tank for mixing, add one product at a time and flush the system between products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If mixing Sentris VRA with glyphosate, consider adding an approved defoamer to reduce foam production in the tank and assure the spray system is well-ventilated (not enclosed) to reduce potential pressure build up issues. In our study, increased pressure was detected in the bottles when Sentris and glyphosate were mixed and the bottles were kept enclosed with a lid; when bottles were kept without the lid for &amp;gt;5 minutes following the glyphosate addition to the Sentris containing solution, the pressure from the chemical reaction in the tank was allowed to dissipate (data not shown)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgements:&lt;/strong&gt; Many thanks to Nikola Arsenijevic, UW-Madison Weed Science Research Assistant, for the assistance with pH measurements and to our WiscWeeds lab for facilitating this study. Drs. Tommy Butts and Vince Davis provided invaluable feedback to this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Article written by Dr. Rodrigo Werle,&lt;/strong&gt; Assistant Professor and Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist, Department of Agronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Striegel, S., Oliveira, M., Arneson, N., Conley, S., Stoltenberg, D., &amp;amp; Werle, R. (2021). Spray solution pH and soybean injury as influenced by synthetic auxin formulation and spray additives. Weed Technology, 35(1), 113-127. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/weed-technology/article/abs/spray-solution-ph-and-soybean-injury-as-influenced-by-synthetic-auxin-formulation-and-spray-additives/2AC0129BAD3C2EC05542E03D87635FEB&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;doi:10.1017/wet.2020.89&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Striegel, S., R.D. Langemeier, B.C. Vieira, S. Li, G.R. Kruger, R. Werle. 2020. Evaluation of dicamba vapor reducing agents across different environments. Proceedings of the 75th North Central Weed Science Society of America Annual Meetings, Virtual Conference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Response of Horseweed Accessions from Wisconsin and Northern Illinois to Spring Burndown Herbicides</title>
      <link>/post/response-of-horseweed-accessions-from-wisconsin-and-northern-illinois-to-spring-burndown-herbicides/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/response-of-horseweed-accessions-from-wisconsin-and-northern-illinois-to-spring-burndown-herbicides/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;horseweed-aka-marestail-erigeron-canadensis&#34;&gt;Horseweed (aka marestail) &lt;em&gt;Erigeron canadensis&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;annual weed species that emerges in the fall or early in the spring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;prolific seed producer (up to 200,000 seeds per plant)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;seeds are commonly dispersed by wind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can be a troublesome weed in no-till systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;often resistant to glyphosate (Group 9) and Group 2 herbicides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A greenhouse study was conducted at the University of Wisconsin-Madison in the fall of 2020 to evaluate the response of 21 horseweed accessions from Wisconsin and northern Illinois to spring burndown herbicides (&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt;). Horseweed seeds from suspected glyphosate-resistant accessions were collected by farmers, consultants and Extension educators.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 horseweed/Figure 1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The treatments selected for this greenhouse screening represent common corn and/or soybean spring burndown herbicides used by US Midwest farmers adopting no-till. Herbicides were sprayed at the label rate (except for Roundup PowerMAX which was also sprayed at 3X the label rate) when horseweed plants at the rosette stage reached approximately 3.5 inches in diameter (&lt;strong&gt;Table 1&lt;/strong&gt;). Visual control and biomass reduction data were collected 21 days after treatment.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 horseweed/Table 1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;key-findings-from-this-research&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key findings from this research:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sharpen, Liberty, Gramoxone, AAtrex, Callisto, and Xtendimax provided effective horseweed control (&amp;gt;90% control at 21 DAT). Enlist One was slightly less effective than the aforementioned options (&lt;strong&gt;Figures 2 and 3&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Roundup PowerMAX (1x and 3x) and Pursuit did not provide satisfactory (&amp;lt;90%) horseweed control (&lt;strong&gt;Figures 2 and 3&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Glyphosate (Roundup PowerMAX, Group 9) and imazethapyr (Pursuit, Group 2) resistance appear to be widespread in horseweed accessions from southern WI and northern IL.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 horseweed/Figure 2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 horseweed/Figure 3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For full study details, check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCH-XrJxxyGoP2E-DGGpdF-w&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UW-Mad About Weeds YouTube&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; summary video &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Response of Putative Glyphosate-Resistant Horseweed from Wisconsin to Spring Burndown Herbicides&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/MvoL-odz3NI&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34; title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Always read, understand and follow the pesticide label.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/strong&gt;: we would like to thank the &lt;strong&gt;Wisconsin Soybean Marketing Board&lt;/strong&gt; for sponsoring this project. Many thanks to the stakeholders who contributed to this project by collecting and submitting horseweed seeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alexandre Rosa&lt;/em&gt; (former UW-Madison Weed Science Postdoctoral Research Specialist)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nicholas Arneson&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Maxwel Oliveira&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Research Analyst)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cereal Rye Cover Crop Termination Timing and its Impact on Weed Suppression and Soybean Yield</title>
      <link>/post/cereal-rye-cover-crop-termination-timing-and-its-impact-on-weed-suppression-and-soybean-yield/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/cereal-rye-cover-crop-termination-timing-and-its-impact-on-weed-suppression-and-soybean-yield/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;With increased temperatures and recent rain, Wisconsin fields that were planted with a cereal rye cover crop in the fall are showing signs of life. If you are planning to manage your cereal rye cover crop as part of an integrated weed management program for in season suppression of small seeded annual weeds, it is important to ensure a large amount of biomass is produced by the time of termination. Research conducted by the WiscWeeds team at the Arlington and Lancaster Agricultural Research Stations over the last two years has shown that a cereal rye cover crop’s ability to suppress weeds improves as the amount of biomass produced increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Establishment of a cover crop following corn harvest in the fall can be difficult due to the short window of time that fields are accessible with equipment. Later established cereal rye may not produce much, if any biomass in the fall and winter, leaving producers to rely on biomass that is produced in the spring. In 2021, we have observed variable biomass production across our cover crop research sites, likely due to differences in when we established our cereal rye in the fall, highlighting the importance of early establishment. Check out recent photos from our research sites:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 cover crop update/brooklyn2021.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
Brooklyn, WI (cereal rye planted September 25, 2020; photo taken April 13, 2021)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 cover crop update/janesville2021.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
Janesville, WI (cereal rye planted October 21, 2020; photo taken April 13, 2021)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Winter rye for our &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/WiscWeeds?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@WiscWeeds&lt;/a&gt; 2021 corn and soybean system studies is looking great &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/UWMadisonCALS?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@UWMadisonCALS&lt;/a&gt; Lancaster ARS &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/zITQ47r5FH&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/zITQ47r5FH&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Daniel H Smith (@agronomybadger) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/agronomybadger/status/1379909151095148547?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;April 7, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Lancaster, WI (cereal rye planted October 21, 2020; photos taken April 7, 2021)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, producers that plant a cereal rye cover crop proceeding soybean will terminate their cereal rye 10-14 days before planting to minimize any impact on yield. This strategy may not allow enough time for adequate biomass production for aiding in weed suppression, especially as farmers continue to shift towards earlier planting in May to maximize yield potential. One way to increase biomass production is to delay termination of the cereal rye until time of soybean planting or even after soybean emergence. This strategy is commonly referred to as ‘&lt;strong&gt;planting green&lt;/strong&gt;’, as soybeans are no-till planted into a standing cereal rye cover crop. Delaying termination until early reproductive stages, such as anthesis, increases the C:N ratio of rye vegetation. This slows residue decomposition leading to biomass which persists longer, further aiding with weed suppression. Furthermore, ensuring effective termination before or at anthesis is important as this eliminates the chances of the cereal rye from producing seed and becoming an additional weed to manage. Generally, our recommendation for an effective termination of cereal rye is to use a full rate of glyphosate with recommended adjuvants (see: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wiscweeds.info/post/2020-considerations-for-cover-crop-termination/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;‘2020 Considerations for Cover Crop Termination’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;). If terminating the cereal rye at or within three days of soybean planting, glyphosate can be tank mixed with a PRE herbicide as part of an integrated weed management strategy. If you are planning to delay cereal rye terminations until after soybean emergence, glyphosate still remains an effective option in GMO (glyphosate-resistant) soybean; however, it will have to be replaced by a Group 1 (ACCase; e.g., clethodim, quizalofop) herbicide with recommended adjuvants in non-GMO soybeans. For soybean farmers interested in adopting cereal rye cover crops, we recommend using an effective PRE herbicide applied at planting as an additional tool for weed management regardless of cereal rye termination timing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below we discuss some highlights from two research studies conducted over two years in Wisconsin evaluating the impacts of cereal rye termination timing on both GMO and non-GMO soybean yield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-1-cereal-rye-termination-timing-impact-on-weed-suppression-and-gmo-roundup-ready-soybean-yield&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study 1: Cereal Rye Termination Timing Impact on Weed Suppression and GMO (Roundup Ready) Soybean Yield&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soil management experiment at Arlington Agricultural Research Station. Photo taken April 13, 2021. These plots will be planted to corn this growing season:
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 cover crop update/Systems Arlington 2021.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Managing &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/cerealrye?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#cerealrye&lt;/a&gt; for weed suppression in soybean? Effective termination + adequate moisture = minimal impacts on soy yield in WI. In 2021, be mindful of moisture cond. in your field and manage accordingly &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/WiscWeeds?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@WiscWeeds&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/KolbyCoverCrops?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@KolbyCoverCrops&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/agronomybadger?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@agronomybadger&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/ohYtuit01I&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/ohYtuit01I&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Nick Arneson (@arnaman6) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/arnaman6/status/1383050310243999750?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;April 16, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study was conducted at Arlington and Lancaster Agricultural Research Stations in 2019 and 2020. Treatments included six soil management strategies (tillage, no-till and 4 methods of cereal rye cover crop termination: 14 days before planting, at planting, at planting forage harvest, and 14 days after planting) and two herbicide programs (no PRE-emergence program or Authority MTZ @ 16 oz/acre applied PRE at planting). All terminations were achieved with a full rate of glyphosate plus recommended adjuvants (Roundup PowerMax @ 32 fl oz/acre + AMS @ 1% v/v). When no PRE was used, delayed cereal rye termination timing resulted in improved weed suppression, with the highest level of suppression observed in the 14 days after planting cover crop termination treatment. When a PRE was used, effective weed control was achieved across soil management strategies. The cover crop treatments, regardless of termination timing, did not reduce soybean yield compared to tillage and no-till strategies in this study. Results from this study demonstrate the value of using an effective PRE herbicide with potential added value from delayed termination of a cereal rye cover crop. The combination of these practices improved weed suppression in soybean with minimal to no yield impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For full study details, check out the UW-Mad About Weeds YouTube summary video &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Impact of
Cereal Rye Cover Crop on Weed Control and Crop Productivity in Wisconsin&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;:
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/Q6UToPwuUS4&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34; title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-2-cereal-rye-termination-timing-impact-on-non-gmo-conventional-soybean-yield&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study 2: Cereal Rye Termination Timing Impact on non-GMO (conventional) Soybean Yield&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cereal rye cover crop impact on non-GMO soybean experiment at Arlington Agricultural Research Station. Photo taken at the time of soybean planting (May 15, 2020). Note the plots of cereal rye turning yellow from the 8 days before planting termination time:
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2021 cover crop update/Food grade.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study was conducted at the Arlington Agricultural Research Stations in 2019 and 2020 in collaboration with Dr. Shawn Conley, Wisconsin Soybean Extension Specialist, and Dr. Damon Smith’s, Wisconsin Field Crops Pathologist, research programs. Treatments included two non-GMO (food grade) soybean varieties, three cover crop termination timings (8 days before planting, at planting, and 14 days after planting), and two herbicide programs (no PRE-emergence program or BroadAxe XC @ 22 fl oz/acre applied PRE at planting). The 8 days before and at planting termination timings were terminated with glyphosate plus recommended adjuvants (Roundup PowerMax @ 22 fl oz/acre + AMS @ 1.275 lb/acre). The 14 days after planting timing was terminated with a full rate of clethodim plus recommended adjuvants (Volunteer @ 8 fl oz/acre + AMS @ 2.5 lb/acre + COC @ 1% v/v). Termination timing had no impact on non-GMO soybean yield for either variety in 2019. In 2020, the 14 days after planting termination treatment (terminated with clethodim) reduced non-GMO soybean yield compared to the 8 days before planting termination timing. In general, the early part of the 2020 growing season was particularly dry compared to 2019. The 14 days after planting termination in 2020 did not completely terminate the cereal rye which remained green and standing for an extended period. In general, clethodim and other Group 1 herbicides provide a slower death compared to glyphosate which can lead to an extended period of standing, green rye. The stress from the incomplete termination, coupled with drier conditions, likely contributed to the yield drag observed in 2020 for this study. Results from this study indicate that a delayed cereal rye termination may not have an impact on soybean yield if the termination is effective and adequate precipitation occurs; however, if ineffective, a delayed termination can negatively impact soybean yield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For full study details, check out the UW-Mad About Weeds YouTube summary video &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Impact of
Cereal Rye Cover Crop on Preemergence Herbicide Fate and Non-GMO Soybean Yield in Wisconsin&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;:
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/BXqrJ1CBRBk&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34; title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more videos, check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCH-XrJxxyGoP2E-DGGpdF-w&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UW-Mad About Weeds YouTube Page&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maximizing cereal rye biomass will increase likelihood of weed suppression in soybean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Effective termination of cereal rye is necessary to minimize impacts on soybean yield&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Given adequate soil moisture, a fall-seeded cereal rye cover crop should not impact yield of mid- to late-May planted soybean, regardless of termination timing up to 14 days after planting when rye should be approaching or reached anthesis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Farmers are encouraged to visit with their insurance provider when deciding the time for cover crop termination and crop management practices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cereal rye cover crop is an additional tool for weed management and should not be used in place of an effective herbicide program when managing troublesome weeds such as waterhemp and giant ragweed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nicholas Arneson&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kolby Grint&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Graduate Student)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dan Smith&lt;/em&gt; (UW NPM Southwest Wisconsin Regional Specialist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ryan DeWerff&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Research Specialist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2020 Wisconsin Weed Science Visual Research Reports</title>
      <link>/post/2020-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-with-field-images/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-with-field-images/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this post is to share images from some of the corn and soybean herbicide evaluation research trials conducted by the Wisconsin Cropping Systems Weed Science Program during the 2020 growing season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;to-download-the-2020-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-click-here-pdf-file-img-2020-research-report-2020-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/2020 Wisconsin Weed science Research Report.pdf&#34;&gt;To download the 2020 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report, CLICK HERE (PDF FILE).&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2020 Corn Weed Control Trials (field images):&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Bayer Corn Herbicide Programs.pdf&#34;&gt;Bayer Corn Herbicide Programs (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Shieldex Weed Control and Crop Safety.pdf&#34;&gt;Shieldex Weed Control and Crop Safety (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Corn Herbicide Evaluation 1 and 2-Pass Programs with Atrazine.pdf&#34;&gt;Corn Herbicide Evaluation 1 and 2-Pass Programs with Atrazine (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Anthem Maxx Corn Herbicide Programs.pdf&#34;&gt;Anthem Maxx Corn Herbicide Programs (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Evaluation of Acuron GT in a One Pass System.pdf&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Acuron GT in a One Pass System (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Evaluation of Acuron GT in a Two Pass System.pdf&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Acuron GT in a Two Pass System (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Evaluation of Acuron XR and Acuron Flexi XR.pdf&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Acuron XR and Acuron Flexi XR (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Sinate Corn Herbicide Comparison.pdf&#34;&gt;Sinate Corn Herbicide Comparison (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2020 Soybean Weed Control Trials (field images):&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/XtendFlex Soybean Herbicide Programs.pdf&#34;&gt;XtendFlex Soybean Herbicide Programs (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Valent Herbicides in Enlist Soybeans.pdf&#34;&gt;Valent Herbicides in Enlist Soybeans (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Authority Brand Herbicide Programs in Enlist Soybeans.pdf&#34;&gt;Authority Brand Herbicide Programs in Enlist Soybeans (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Liberty and Enlist Efficacy in Enlist Soybean - BASF.pdf&#34;&gt;Liberty and Enlist Efficacy in Enlist Soybean - BASF (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Liberty and Enlist Efficacy in Enlist Soybean - Corteva.pdf&#34;&gt;Liberty and Enlist Efficacy in Enlist Soybean - Corteva (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Syngenta Herbicide Programs in Enlist Soybeans.pdf&#34;&gt;Syngenta Herbicide Programs in Enlist Soybeans (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Utility of Layering Residual Herbicides in Soybean.pdf&#34;&gt;Utility of Layering Residual Herbicides in Soybean (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Liberty Tank Mix Combinations for Waterhemp Control.pdf&#34;&gt;Liberty Tank Mix Combinations for Waterhemp Control (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Liberty and Engenia in XtendFlex Soybean.pdf&#34;&gt;Liberty and Engenia in XtendFlex Soybean (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Expanding Residual Control with Alite 27.pdf&#34;&gt;Expanding Residual Control with Alite 27 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Evaluation of Soybean Soil Residual Herbicides - Giant Ragweed.pdf&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Soybean Soil Residual Herbicides - Giant Ragweed (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2020 Bareground Weed Control Trials (field images):&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Evaluation of Roundup PowerMAX 3.pdf&#34;&gt;Evaluation of Roundup PowerMAX 3 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Burndown Control of Giant Ragweed.pdf&#34;&gt;Burndown Control of Giant Ragweed (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/Burndown Control of Glyphosate-Resistant Waterhemp.pdf&#34;&gt;Burndown Control of Glyphosate-Resistant Waterhemp (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to &lt;strong&gt;Ryan DeWerff&lt;/strong&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Research Specialist) for generating the visual research reports and to our team for capturing the images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information herein does not constitute a recommendation or endorsement of any particular product or practice. Information in these reports also does not replace any information presented on herbicide labels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please do not reproduce information presented within this report for public distribution without the expressed written consent from Dr. Rodrigo Werle.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/headers/2020WiscWeedsTeam.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2020-wiscweeds-team&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020 WiscWeeds Team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2020 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report</title>
      <link>/post/2020-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;by Ryan DeWerff (UW-Madison Weed Science Research Specialist), Nicholas Arneson (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist), and &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this report is to share the results of corn and soybean herbicide evaluation research trials conducted by the Wisconsin Cropping Systems Weed Science Program during the 2020 growing season. Information in this report does not constitute a recommendation or endorsement of any particular product or practice. Information in this report also does not replace any information presented on herbicide labels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;to-download-the-2020-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-click-here-pdf-file-img-2020-research-report-2020-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 Research Report/2020 Wisconsin Weed science Research Report.pdf&#34;&gt;To download the 2020 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report, CLICK HERE (PDF FILE).&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please do not reproduce information presented within this report for public distribution without the expressed written consent from Dr. Rodrigo Werle.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2020-research-trials&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020 Research Trials:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;corn-weed-control-trials&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Corn Weed Control Trials&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bayer Corn Herbicide Programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shieldex Weed Control and Crop Safety&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corn Herbicide Evaluation: 1 and 2-pass Programs with Atrazine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anthem Maxx Corn Herbicide Programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Acuron GT in a One Pass System&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Acuron GT in a Two Pass System&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Acuron XR/Acuron Flexi in a 1 and 2 Pass System&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sinate Corn Herbicide Programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;soybean-weed-control-trials&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Soybean Weed Control Trials&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;XtendFlex Soybean Herbicide Programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Valent Herbicides in Enlist Soybeans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Authority Brand Herbicide Programs in Enlist Soybeans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liberty and Enlist Efficacy in Enlist Soybean - BASF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liberty and Enlist Efficacy in Enlist Soybean - Corteva&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syngenta Herbicide Programs in Enlist Soybean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Utility of Layering Residual Herbicides in Soybean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liberty Tank Mix Combinations for Waterhemp Control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liberty and Engenia in XtendFlex Soybean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expanding Residual Control with Alite 27&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Soybean Soil Residual Herbicides - Giant Ragweed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bareground-weed-control-trials&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bareground Weed Control Trials&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Burndown Programs for 8-12&amp;rdquo; Marestail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Roundup PowerMAX 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Burndown Control of Waterhemp and Giant Ragweed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-this-year&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;New This Year&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summary of Giant Ragweed Control in Corn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summary of Waterhemp Control in Soybean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/headers/2020WiscWeedsTeam.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2020-wiscweeds-team&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020 WiscWeeds Team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spray solution pH and soybean injury as influenced by dicamba and 2,4-d herbicide formulation and spray additives</title>
      <link>/post/spray-solution-ph-and-soybean-injury-as-influenced-by-dicamba-and-2-4-d-herbicide-formulation-and-spray-additives/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/spray-solution-ph-and-soybean-injury-as-influenced-by-dicamba-and-2-4-d-herbicide-formulation-and-spray-additives/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Sarah Striegel, former graduate student in the Cropping Systems Weed Science program, Department of Agronomy, University of Wisconsin-Madison, had her first manuscript recently published in Weed Technology. Herein we provide the highlights of her latest publication and access to two technical articles for download and circulation to our clientele.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original research article:&lt;/strong&gt; Striegel S, Oliveira MC, Arneson N, Conley SP, Stoltenberg DE, Werle R (2020) Spray solution pH and soybean injury as influenced by synthetic auxin formulation and spray additives. Weed Technol.
DOI: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/weed-technology/article/spray-solution-ph-and-soybean-injury-as-influenced-by-synthetic-auxin-formulation-and-spray-additives/2AC0129BAD3C2EC05542E03D87635FEB&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;10.1017/wet.2020.89&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use of synthetic auxin herbicides has increased across the Midwestern United States after adoption of synthetic auxin-resistant soybean traits, in addition to extensive use of these herbicides in corn. Off-target movement of synthetic auxin herbicides such as dicamba can lead to severe injury to sensitive plants nearby. Previous research has documented effects of glyphosate on spray-solution pH and volatility of several dicamba formulations, but our understanding of the relationships between glyphosate and dicamba formulations commonly used in corn and for 2,4-D remains limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-objectives&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research Objectives&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main objectives of S. Striegel’s research were to (1) investigate the roles of synthetic auxin herbicide formulation, glyphosate, and spray additives on spray solution pH; and (2) assess the influence of glyphosate and application time of year on dicamba and 2,4-D volatility using soybean as bioindicators in low-tunnel field volatility experiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addition of glyphosate to a synthetic auxin herbicide decreased solution pH below 5.0 for four of the seven herbicides tested (range of initial pH of water source, 7.45–7.70). Among all treatment factors, inclusion of glyphosate was the most important affecting spray solution pH; however, the addition of glyphosate did not influence area under the injury over distance stairs in low-tunnel field volatility experiments. Greater soybean injury in field experiments was associated with high air temperatures (maximum, &amp;gt;85 F) and low wind speeds (mean, 0.7–3 mph) during the 48 h after treatment application. The two dicamba formulations (diglycolamine salt with VaporGrip® [Xtendimax with VaporGrip® herbicide] and sodium salt [Status herbicide]) resulted in similar levels of soybean injury for applications that occurred later in the growing season. Greater soybean injury was observed after dicamba than after 2,4-D choline treatments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technical articles for download and circulation to our clientele (PDF files):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/Update Series Articles/WWRUS Article 1_Spray Solution pH.pdf&#34;&gt;WiscWeeds Research Update Series, Article 1: Spray solution pH as influenced by synthetic auxin formulation and spray additives (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/Update Series Articles/WWRUS Article 2_Low tunnel volatility.pdf&#34;&gt;WiscWeeds Research Update Series, Article 2: Soybean injury as influenced by synthetic auxin formulation and spray additives (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;These technical articles have been developed by Nick Arneson (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist), Sarah Striegel (Former UW-Madison Weed Science Graduate Student) and Dr. Maxwel Oliveira (UW-Madison Weed Science Research Associate).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Funding for S. Striegel’s graduate research assistantship was provided by Bayer Crop Science and the R.Gordon Harvey Distinguished Graduate Fellowship. Dr. Werle served as S. Striegel&amp;rsquo;s major advisor; Drs. Conley and Stoltenberg served as advisory committee members. The authors would like to thank the University of Wisconsin-Madison Cropping Systems Weed Science research group and the Arlington Agricultural Research Station staff for their technical assistance in establishing the experiments.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weed Seed Movement Via Combines</title>
      <link>/post/weed-seed-movement/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/weed-seed-movement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Crop harvest is here and that means it’s time to be thinking about weed seedbank management. Over the last few weeks we have observed fields throughout Wisconsin with a fair amount of weed escapes. The most troublesome weeds in Wisconsin, waterhemp and giant ragweed, will retain their seeds well into October in the Upper Midwest. If you have weeds that have set seed in your field, now is the time to get out there, remove and burn them before combines start rolling. Check the &lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 combine/Weed Seed Management at Crop Harvest.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;UW-NPM Weed Seed Management at Crop Harvest (PDF file)&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; handout used in our Combine Cleaning Workshops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are unable to remove weeds that have gone to seed, it is important to develop a sound harvest strategy to minimize the spread of weeds from field to field. This would include cleaning combines between fields and harvesting fields with severe weed infestations last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last fall, to validate our concerns of weed seed movement via combines, we put out a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wiscweeds.info/post/2019-wiscweeds-research-coalition-combine-weed-seed-collection-project/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;call&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to UW-Madison Ag Extension Educators and stakeholders to take the time to clean and collect samples from combines before putting them away for the winter. We specifically asked for samples from four locations: head, feeder house, rock trap, and rotor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//player.vimeo.com/video/374533967&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total we received 31 samples from nine different combines (many thanks to all project participants). We then mixed the samples with field soil and potting mix in our greenhouse and observed what weeds emerged after two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the results by downloading this handout: &lt;a href=&#34;/img/2020 combine/Weed Seed Movement via Combines.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Weed Seed Movement Via Combines: 2019-2020 Case Study (PDF file)&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here are some of the highlights:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;97% of samples contained viable weed seed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Combine head samples contained ~49% of the total weeds emerged, followed by the feeder house ~30%, rock trap ~19%, and rotor ~2%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most frequently observed weeds were grasses, pigweeds and common lambsquarters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When time is limited, we believe that prioritizing the front of the combine (head and feeder house) would provide the most benefit in reducing weed seed spread by combines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Last winter &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/agronomybadger?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@agronomybadger&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/WiscWeeds?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@WiscWeeds&lt;/a&gt; asked for  &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/combine?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#combine&lt;/a&gt; samples 2 c what &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/weeds?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#weeds&lt;/a&gt; we&amp;#39;re moving around WI. U delivered + here is quick update. Weeds setting seed in your field? Now&amp;#39;s the time to make moves! Stay tuned 4 further updates this fall &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/3mrP60YC4D&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/3mrP60YC4D&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Nick Arneson (@arnaman6) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/arnaman6/status/1296193027648688128?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 19, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some additional tips for cleaning combines and reducing the spread of weeds:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use an air compressor or leaf blower to force air through and clear debris from critical portions of the combine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run a bag of wood shavings through the combine to clean rotor/auger area&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/nDMq1UanSkE&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34; title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nick Arneson&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dan Smith&lt;/em&gt; (UW NPM Southwest Wisconsin Regional Specialist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/em&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
