<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wisconsin Weed Science on Wisconsin Weed Science</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Wisconsin Weed Science on Wisconsin Weed Science</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 WiscWeeds</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Wisconsin Waterhemp Herbicide Resistance Project</title>
      <link>/post/wisconsin-waterhemp-herbicide-resistance-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/wisconsin-waterhemp-herbicide-resistance-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to our recent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/2018-wisconsin-cropping-systems-weed-science-survey/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SURVEY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, waterhemp has become the most concerning weed in row crop production in Wisconsin. Thus, we invite Wisconsin farmers and agronomists to collect waterhemp seeds this fall from their row crop production fields and submit them to UW-Madison for herbicide resistance screenings (we ask farmers to collect samples from only one of their fields; preferably the one with the most troublesome infestation level).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We intend to screen samples in the greenhouse for resistance to glyphosate (Group 9) and also to PPO-inhibitor (e.g., Cobra, Flextar, Cadet; Group 14), ALS-inhibitor (e.g., Pursuit, Classic, FirstRate; Group 2), HPPD-Inhibitor (e.g., Callisto; Group 27), PSII-inhibitor (e.g., Atrazine; Group 5) and Growth Regulator (e.g., dicamba, 2,4-D; Group 4) herbicides. Results will be made available to those who submit the samples after the greenhouse screenings are completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no cost associated to the herbicide resistance screening. The only cost will be your time to collect the seed samples and mailing them to: &lt;strong&gt;Rodrigo Werle, 1575 Linden Drive, Madison, WI 53706.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please download and print the &lt;a href=&#34;/img/2018 waterhemp seed collection/2018 WiscWeeds Waterhemp Seed Project.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SEED COLLECTION FORM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (PDF file) for information on how to collect the seeds and fill out the information necessary for the project. Please submit the form with the seed sample. Samples will only be included in the herbicide resistance screening if the information requested herein is provided by the farmer/agronomist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For questions, contact Dr. Rodrigo Werle via e-mail: &lt;strong&gt;rwerle@wisc.edu&lt;/strong&gt; or phone: &lt;strong&gt;608-262-7130&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thank the &lt;strong&gt;Wisconsin Soybean Marketing Board&lt;/strong&gt; for providing partial funding to support this project and also those submitting samples.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dicamba Use in Wisconsin Soybean Production - SURVEY</title>
      <link>/post/dicamba-use-in-wisconsin-soybean-production-survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/dicamba-use-in-wisconsin-soybean-production-survey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017 the Xtend soybean technology was completely launched in the United States (e.g., Environmental Protection Agency [EPA] approval of dicamba-tolerant seed trait and POST-emergence application of labeled dicamba formulations). Despite the great level of broadleaf weed control observed when dicamba was sprayed POST-emergence in Xtend soybeans, particularly of the troublesome weeds giant ragweed and waterhemp, off-target dicamba movement is still a concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have designed a short survey intended to investigate Wisconsin soybean farmers’ perceptions on dicamba use in Xtend soybeans. The survey comprises of four main sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Demographics of participants&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Outcomes from dicamba application in Xtend soybeans in 2017 and 2018&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Perceived dicamba injury in non-Xtend soybeans in Xtend 2017 and 2018&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Expected adoption of the technology in 2019 (assuming it remains available to US soybean farmers in 2019).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We truly appreciate the time of those answering the survey (even if you did not and don’t plan to adopt the technology, please take the time to answer; your feedback is of extreme importance). &lt;a href=&#34;https://aae.wisc.edu/pdmitchell/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Paul Mitchell&lt;/a&gt;, UW-Madison Extension Ag Economist, will assist with data summarization and analysis. Your answers will be kept confidential and the final results will be made available via Wisconsin Crop Manager this fall and presented during winter meetings across Wisconsin. The outcome of the survey will also be shared with the Wisconsin Department of Agriculture, Trade and Consumer Protection (DATCP) and US EPA. Moreover, results will help us decide research needs moving forward. We greatly appreciate your time and input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To participate in the survey, click &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.surveymonkey.com/r/J3XWFBX&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HERE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 dicamba survey/Wisc-QR_code_J3XWFBX.png&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Code&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reporting Dicamba-Injured Acreage in Wisconsin</title>
      <link>/post/reporting-dicamba-injured-acreage-in-wisconsin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/reporting-dicamba-injured-acreage-in-wisconsin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of July, the weather finally became conducive for POST-emergence herbicide applications in southern Wisconsin, including for dicamba application in Xtend (dicamba-tolerant) soybeans. Typically, injury from micro-rates of dicamba (via tank-contamination, particle and/or vapor drift) in susceptible crops tends to show at 10-14 days after the incident (see: &lt;a href=&#34;https://learningstore.uwex.edu/Assets/pdfs/A4161.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Soybean Injury From Dicamba A4161&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). Driving around the southern part of Wisconsin this past week, I have noticed a couple instances of dicamba injury in soybeans (I estimate less than 15 total injured acres).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 dicamba injured acres/IMG_3914.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Figure 1.&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
Figure 1. Non-Xtend soybeans injured by dicamba in south-central Wisconsin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, &lt;a href=&#34;https://plantsciences.missouri.edu/faculty/bradley.cfm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Kevin Bradley&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Professor and State Extension Weed Scientist with the University of Missouri, kept track of the estimates of dicamba-injured soybean acreage across the United States (see: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ipm.missouri.edu/IPCM/2017/10/final_report_dicamba_injured_soybean/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Final Report on Dicamba-Injured Soybean Acres&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). This year, EPA (Environmental Protection Agency) and others have requested Dr. Bradley to continue the effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Bradley is in communication with the State Departments of Agriculture regarding official complaints but is also attempting to track dicamba-injured acres that are not being officially reported.
Thus, if you have noticed dicamba injury in your soybeans and/or other susceptible crops in Wisconsin, regardless on whether an official complaint was/will be filed with the Wisconsin Department of Agriculture, Trade and Consumer Protection (DATCAP), it would appreciated if you could send me an email (&lt;strong&gt;rwerle@wisc.edu&lt;/strong&gt;) describing the county, crop and number of dicamba-injured acres or plants (if referring to vegetable or ornamental crops). Pictures of the dicamba-injured crop would also be of extreme value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The information sent to me will be kept confidential and only used to update Dr. Bradley’s estimates and hopefully provide valuable information to decision-makers this fall to support their decision on whether to extend EPA registrations for Engenia, FeXapan and Xtendimax herbicides in Xtend soybeans.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Application window for most soybean herbicides coming close to an end</title>
      <link>/post/application-window-for-most-soybean-herbicides-coming-close-to-an-end/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/application-window-for-most-soybean-herbicides-coming-close-to-an-end/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excessive and constant rainfall through the season thus far across southern Wisconsin has challenged timely herbicide applications in our experimental plots. If not raining, the wind was often blowing or the soil was too wet to even backpack spray. After spending several years in Nebraska, I learned that one can’t complain about rain, but come on! Still, we have managed to get most of our herbicide treatments out (thanks to a dedicated and hard-working research team that is literally not afraid of getting some mud on their boots!). So those out there waiting for the right opportunity to get the rig out and spray your soybean fields, I understand your pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, the soybeans keep on growing and if they haven’t already, soon they will start flowering (UW-Madison Agronomist Dr. Shawn Conley has observed the first flowers on his early-planted high-yield soybean plots at Arlington Ag Research Station this week). With the onset of flowering (R1 growth stage), comes the end of legal application window for several commonly used POST-emergence soybean herbicides such as Pursuit (Group 2), Liberty (Group 10) in Liberty Link soybeans, and Dicamba (Group 4) in Xtend Soybeans. Glyphosate (Group 9) in Roundup Ready soybeans, FirstRate (Group 2), and Cadet (Group 14) are examples of herbicides that can be sprayed up to full bloom (R2 growth stage).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your soybeans are close to flowering but still have a ways to go until reach full canopy, adding a herbicide with soil residual activity to the POST program may be a viable strategy, particularly in fields with known waterhemp infestation or where small-seeded late-season weeds are still actively emerging. Assuming soybeans are passed the 3rd trifoliate (V3 growth stage), herbicide options with soil residual activity become Outlook (Group 15; up to V5 growth stage), Warrant (Group 15; up to R2 growth stage), and Warrant Ultra (Groups 15 + 14; up to R2 growth stage; see label for geographic restrictions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the application window is getting shorter, wait for the right opportunity to spray and adjust herbicide program if necessary (don’t spray under marginal conditions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For assistance identifying soybean growth stages, see: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coolbean.info/library/documents/2017_Soybean_GrowthDev_Guide_FINAL.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“A Visual Guide to Soybean Growth Stages”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For assistance with herbicide selection, see: &lt;a href=&#34;http://learningstore.uwex.edu/Assets/pdfs/A3646.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Pest Management in Wisconsin Field Crops (UWEX Bulletin A3646)&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://ipcm.wisc.edu/download/pubsPM/Herbicide-Mode-of-Action.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wisconsin Herbicide Mode of Action Chart&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always read the herbicide label for product rate, application window, and restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Palmer amaranth is now a prohibited noxious weed seed in Wisconsin, but what does it look like?</title>
      <link>/post/palmer-amaranth-is-now-a-prohibited-noxious-weed-seed-in-wisconsin-but-what-does-it-look-like/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/palmer-amaranth-is-now-a-prohibited-noxious-weed-seed-in-wisconsin-but-what-does-it-look-like/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under a new emergency rule, &lt;strong&gt;Palmer amaranth&lt;/strong&gt; has been labeled as a prohibited noxious weed seed in Wisconsin. Given Palmer amaranth&amp;rsquo;s aggressive nature, this is a worthwhile and necessary attempt to keep this troublesome weed species out of the state. For more details, see DATCP article: &lt;a href=&#34;https://datcp.wi.gov/Pages/News_Media/PalmerAmaranth.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Keep an Eye Out for Palmer Amaranth, DATCP Cautions”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Palmer amaranth’s late and extended emergence window throughout the growing season and vigorous growth rate (up to 2 inches per day under ideal conditions) make control in row crops very difficult. Palmer amaranth is a major weed problem in the US Mid-South and parts of the Midwest. According to University of Wisconsin-Madison Weed Scientists, Palmer amaranth has been reported in 6 Wisconsin counties thus far (see map below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 Palmer amaranth/Palmer distribution WI.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Palmer distribution&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way that Palmer amaranth seeds may get introduced to a new region is via contaminated conservation or pollinator seed mixes. Thus, purchase seed mixes free of amaranth species. Moreover, be on the lookout for Palmer amaranth in areas where these seeds are planted. Equipment moving from Palmer amaranth infested areas can also transport seeds; thus, thoroughly clean equipment coming from regions where the species is present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first steps to prevent further spread of a noxious weed species, is to properly recognize it. Below I have images that may help stakeholders identify this troublesome weed and differentiate it from other common Pigweed species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key identifying characteristics of Palmer amaranth are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lack of hairs on leaves and stems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;long petiole (structure that connects the leaf blade to the stem; the petiole of a Palmer amaranth leaf is typically as long or longer than the leaf blade itself)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;female plants have long and prickly seedheads&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 Palmer amaranth/Pigweed family.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Pigweed family&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 Palmer amaranth/Palmer amaranth.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Palmer amaranth&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 Palmer amaranth/common waterhemp.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;waterhemp&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 Palmer amaranth/redroot pigweed.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;redroot pigweed&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;center&gt; Female Palmer amaranth plant growing in a corn field in West-Central Nebraska&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(note the plant height and seedheads [long and prickly]): &lt;/center&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 Palmer amaranth/Palmer corn.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Palmer amaranth corn&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The YouTube video by UW-Madison Extension Weed Specialist &lt;a href=&#34;https://fyi.uwex.edu/weedsci/mark-renz/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Mark Renz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is also a great resource to help stakeholders identify and differentiate Palmer amaranth from other Pigweed species: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?reload=9&amp;amp;v=A1vB_DQTkHI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Identifying Palmer amaranth and Waterhemp in Wisconsin using vegetative characteristics”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact your local University of Wisconsin County Ag Extension Agent if you need assistance to identify this species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s all work together to keep Wisconsin &lt;strong&gt;Palmer-FREE&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waterhemp management in soybeans</title>
      <link>/post/waterhemp-management-in-soybeans/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/waterhemp-management-in-soybeans/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to our recent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/2018-wisconsin-cropping-systems-weed-science-survey/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SURVEY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, waterhemp has become the most concerning weed in row crop production in Wisconsin. Adding to that challenge, glyphosate-resistant waterhemp populations have been confirmed in 25 Wisconsin counties (see map below). Furthermore, PPO-resistant waterhemp has been confirmed in 4 counties (Iowa, Monroe, Saint Croix, and Pierce). Resistance to ALS-inhibiting herbicides is widespread across the Midwest but has not been fully investigated in Wisconsin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 waterhemp/Herbicide Resistant Waterhemp.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;map&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1. Distribution of glyphosate-resistant waterhemp in Wisconsin (reports from University of Illinois Plant Clinic). For additional information, see the paper from UW-Agronomy Professor Dr. Dave Stoltenberg, presented during the 2018 Wisconsin Agribusiness Classic: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.agclassic.org/proceedings/2018_stoltenberg.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Current State of Herbicide Resistance in Wisconsin&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At our on-farm research site in Chippewa county, WI, waterhemp emergence has been occurring for approximately two weeks. At our site in Grant county, WI, we noticed the first waterhemp seedlings today (06/04/2018). These plants will start growing rapidly as we move into the warmer portion of the growing season. It is important to also scout for waterhemp seedlings in fields where PRE-emergence herbicides were sprayed at planting, as the soil residual activity of these herbicides fade away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 waterhemp/waterhemp seedling.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;seedling&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2. Waterhemp seedling emerging in Chippewa county, WI (picture taken on 05/23/2018).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Glyphosate (Group 9), ALS-inhibiting herbicides (Group 2; e.g.: Pursuit, Classic, FirstRate), and PPO-inhibiting herbicides (Group 14; e.g., Cobra, Flextar, Cadet, Ultra Blazer) are the three primary herbicide sites-of-action (SOA) used for broadleaf weed control POST-emergence in Roundup Ready soybeans. Growers who suspect they have a glyphosate-resistant waterhemp problem should use a tank-mixture of glyphosate and a herbicide from Group 14 and/or Group 2 for effective POST-emergence control. To have success using Group 14 or Group 2 herbicides, waterhemp height should be less than 4 inches at application. Soybean fields with emerged waterhemp where glyphosate has struggled in the past should get top priority for spraying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group 14 herbicides are likely the best choice for POST-emergence control of glyphosate-resistant waterhemp in Roundup Ready soybeans. Growers must be aware that they may need to adjust their application practices to maximize the effectiveness of these herbicides. Group 14 herbicides are contact, cell membrane disrupters that require good spray coverage for best control. It is important to read the product label to know the required carrier volume and adjuvant selection to enhance the efficacy of the selected product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberty (Group 10) in &lt;strong&gt;Liberty Link&lt;/strong&gt; soybeans or Dicamba (Group 4) in &lt;strong&gt;Xtend&lt;/strong&gt; soybeans are effective options for POST-emergence control of glyphosate-resistant waterhemp, assuming one of these traits is adopted. With Liberty (contact herbicide), weeds must be treated when they are small (&amp;lt;4 inches) and spray coverage is important for control like for Group 14 herbicides. With dicamba, off-target movement via particle and/or vapor drift and tank-contamination are current concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of waterhemp’s late and extended emergence window, the use of a soil residual herbicide from Group 15 (e.g., Dual II Magnum, Outlook, Warrant, Zidua) tank-mixed with the POST-emergence program is encouraged to control later flushes of waterhemp. See herbicide label for rates, application window, and restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several effective herbicide options are available for waterhemp control in corn. Thus, we urge growers on a corn-soybean rotation to proactively manage waterhemp in corn years, including late escapes that may not impact corn yield but will replenish the soil seed-bank for subsequent years. This will increase the odds of successful control of waterhemp in subsequent soybean years. Remember, &lt;strong&gt;“no seed no weed”&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See our YouTube Video for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=agxSPiCEKrg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Tips on Waterhemp Management in Soybeans&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-assistance-with-herbicide-selection&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For assistance with herbicide selection&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://learningstore.uwex.edu/Assets/pdfs/A3646.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pest Management in Wisconsin Field Crops&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
UWEX Bulletin A3646 (PDF)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ipcm.wisc.edu/download/pubsPM/Herbicide-Mode-of-Action.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wisconsin Herbicide Mode of Action Chart&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strategies for Late Termination of Cereal Rye Cover Crop</title>
      <link>/post/strategies-for-late-termination-of-cereal-rye-cover-crop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/strategies-for-late-termination-of-cereal-rye-cover-crop/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist) and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://ipcm.wisc.edu/contacts/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dan Smith&lt;/a&gt; (UW NPM Southwest Wisconsin Regional Specialist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fall-planted cereal rye is increasingly used as a cover crop to protect the soil during winter and spring in corn and soybean cropping systems across the Midwest. Our recent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/2018-wisconsin-cropping-systems-weed-science-survey/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;survey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; indicated that 77% of Wisconsin farmers and Ag professionals are interested in cover crops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fall-planted cereal rye is growing rapidly in southern Wisconsin and it’s important to have a termination plan in mind prior to crop establishment. The following pictures demonstrate cereal rye growth in 10 days:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 cc rye termination/IMG_2102.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;small&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1. Picture of a cereal rye cover crop field in south-central Wisconsin taken on April 30, 2018.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 cc rye termination/IMG_2163.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;large&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2. Picture of the same cereal rye cover crop field in south-central Wisconsin taken on May 10, 2018.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;cereal-rye-cover-crop-termination&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cereal Rye Cover Crop Termination&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nrcs.usda.gov/Internet/FSE_DOCUMENTS/stelprdb1263099.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NRCS Cover Crop Termination Guidelines&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, fall-planted cereal rye cover crop should be terminated at or within 5 days after planting but before crop emergence in Wisconsin non-irrigated fields. The NRCS guidelines were developed to help producers maximize conservation benefits from cover crops, while minimizing crop yield loss by conserving adequate soil water. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://aae.wisc.edu/pdmitchell/CropInsurance/CCandInsurance2016.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover Crops and Crop Insurance in Wisconsin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for additional information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 cc rye termination/CoverCropTerminationZones_NRCS.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;large&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3. NRCS cover crop termination zones.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UW-Madison and other researchers across the Midwest recommend terminating cover crops before crop planting (see: &lt;a href=&#34;http://coolbean.info/library/documents/CPN-4002.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover Crops Do’s and Don’t’s&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;cereal-rye-cover-crop-termination-options&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cereal Rye Cover Crop Termination Options&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;herbicides&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Herbicides&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research conducted in Missouri showed that 28 fl oz of Roundup (glyphosate) provided satisfactory control of cereal rye (Figure 4). The early termination treatment (early-April) resulted in slightly better control than the later termination treatment (early-May). Glyphosate efficacy decreases when plants reach reproductive stages. The contact herbicide Gramoxone was also tested and was not as effective as glyphosate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 cc rye termination/Missouri Visual Control.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Missouri&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 4. Influence of herbicide treatments and application timings on the control of cereal rye cover crop (results averaged across 3 years of research in Missouri). Data collected by Dr. Kevin Bradley’s research group at the University of Missouri.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research conducted in Wisconsin also demonstrated that glyphosate provided successful termination of cereal rye (see: &lt;a href=&#34;http://ipcm.wisc.edu/download/pubsPM/AnnualRye_WinterRye_Glyphosate.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Termination of winter rye and annual ryegrass using glyphosate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;roller-crimper&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roller-crimper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to research conducted in Pennsylvania, roller-crimpers can be used effectively for cereal rye termination after the boot stage (Figure 5). Although not widely used across the Midwest, the use of roller-crimpers is a viable strategy for producers that would like to have additional biomass in the spring before crop planting and use a mechanical strategy for cover crop termination rather than herbicides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 cc rye termination/Roller Crimper.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;RollerCrimper&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 5. Roller-crimper rolling down cereal rye cover crop in Pennsylvania. Picture obtained from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://integratedweedmanagement.org/index.php/iwm-toolbox/cultural-practices/cover-cropping/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;USDA Integrated Weed Management Resource Center Website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For additional information on roller-crimpers, watch the video: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UtxH4CJa-jk&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advances using the roller-crimper for organic no-till in Wisconsin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;final-considerations&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final considerations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If glyphosate is used for cereal rye termination, it should be sprayed when day temperatures are above 55° F and night temperatures are above 40° F. For more effective cereal rye control, glyphosate should be applied before the boot stage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Contact herbicides such as Gramoxone and Liberty may be used for cereal rye termination; however, they may not provide adequate control if the cereal rye is at boot or later stages. As with any contact herbicide, practices to improve spray coverage will improve efficacy (e.g. medium spray droplet size and higher application rates [GPA]).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If cereal rye will be harvested for forage, herbicides should be sprayed after harvest and biomass removal from the field to control the cereal rye regrowth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If a legume is part of the cover crop mix, using a growth regulator herbicide such as 2,4-D or dicamba will enhance termination (see planting restrictions prior to selecting a growth regulator for cover crop termination).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If glyphosate-resistant weeds are established at cereal rye termination (e.g., marestail, giant ragweed), adding herbicides such as 2,4-D and/or Sharpen to the tank-mix will assist with their control (see label for planting restrictions).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Late termination of cereal rye may reduce the yield potential of the main crop from excessive soil water use, temporary sequestration of plant available nutrients that are critical for the early development of the subsequent cash crop (particularly nitrogen for corn), and/or excessive amounts of residue that can difficult planting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cover crops may suppress troublesome weeds, but typically do not provide complete weed control alone. Combining cover crops and herbicide programs (including PRE-emergence herbicides) can be a powerful strategy for weed management.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For additional information on herbicide options, check the &lt;a href=&#34;http://learningstore.uwex.edu/Assets/pdfs/A3646.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pest Management in Wisconsin Field Crops&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; UWEX Bulletin A3646 (PDF). Always check the herbicide labels before application. Producers are encouraged to visit with their insurance provider when deciding the time for cover crop termination as local rules may be different.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are you PRE-emergence ready for soybean planting?</title>
      <link>/post/are-you-pre-emergence-ready-for-soybean-planting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/are-you-pre-emergence-ready-for-soybean-planting/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;br /&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;http://coolbean.info/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Shawn Conley&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Soybean and Small Grain Specialist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spring has finally arrived in Wisconsin and so has the planting season. Before getting your soybeans in the ground, make sure you have plans for your PRE-emergence herbicide program. According to our recent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/2018-wisconsin-cropping-systems-weed-science-survey/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SURVEY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, several Wisconsin soybean fields get only treated with a one-pass POST-emergence herbicide program. Because of the spread of weed species resistant to glyphosate and/or other POST-emergence herbicides (e.g., ALS- and PPO-inhibitors), a one-pass POST-emergence program in soybeans is no longer a viable strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, research conducted across the Midwest has demonstrated the importance of keeping your soybean crop weed-free from establishment through the V3 growth stage &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coolbean.info/library/documents/2017_Soybean_GrowthDev_Guide_FINAL.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;3rd trifoliate&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. Weeds emerging after the V3 growth stage will likely not impact soybean yield; however, they should still be proactively managed to prevent them from reproducing and replenishing the seedbank (remember &lt;strong&gt;“no seed, no weed”&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, PRE-emergence herbicides can help farmers maintain their fields weed-free during initial establishment of the crop (= achieve full yield potential) and also reduce the selection pressure on POST-emergence herbicides (due to fewer weeds to be controlled POST-emergence), helping on the fight against herbicide resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 Soybean PRE/PRE control Palmer.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;PRE&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several PRE-emergence herbicides are available for soybeans. Most of them can be applied before or up to 3 days after planting. To maximize their residual activity in-season, PRE-emergence herbicides should be sprayed at or shortly after planting. PRE-emergence herbicides need moisture for incorporation and activation in the soil. If there are established weeds at the time of PRE-emergence application and no additional pre-plant field cultivation will take place, it’s important to have an effective burndown herbicide in the tank-mix.
A PRE-emergence herbicide containing 2 or more effective modes of action (MOA) will likely provide control of a wider range of weed species when compared to the use of a single MOA. Using multiple MOA during each pass is also a proactive strategy for herbicide resistance management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to note that under cool and wet conditions, PRE-emergence herbicides containing metribuzin (Group 5) and/or PPO-inhibitors (Group 14; e.g.: flumioxazin, saflufenacil, sulfentrazone) may cause some crop injury, particularly in lighter soils with low OM and/or higher pH. Our preliminary research in Nebraska has demonstrated that early-season crop injury caused by metribuzin (group 5) and sulfentrazone (group 14) did not lead to yield reduction (soybeans are indeed very resilient). Moreover, the benefit of an early-season weed-free field outweighs the concerns of early-season crop injury (assuming a herbicide is applied according to the label and no significant stand reduction is observed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metribuzin injury in soybeans (note healthy new growth):&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 Soybean PRE/metribuzin.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;PRE&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-assistance-with-herbicide-selection&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For assistance with herbicide selection&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://learningstore.uwex.edu/Assets/pdfs/A3646.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pest Management in Wisconsin Field Crops&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
UWEX Bulletin A3646 (PDF)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ipcm.wisc.edu/download/pubsPM/Herbicide-Mode-of-Action.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wisconsin Herbicide Mode of Action Chart&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geographic Restrictions for Corn and Soybean PRE-emergence Herbicides in Wisconsin</title>
      <link>/post/geographic-restrictions-for-corn-and-soybean-pre-emergence-herbicides-in-wisconsin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/geographic-restrictions-for-corn-and-soybean-pre-emergence-herbicides-in-wisconsin/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist) and&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://horticulture.wisc.edu/academic_staff/richard-proost/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Richard Proost&lt;/a&gt; (UW NPM Sr. Outreach Specialist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PRE-emergence herbicides are the foundation for good weed control in corn and soybeans, particularly with the spread of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HR1KFvHgYr0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;herbicide-resistant weeds&lt;/a&gt;. The use of some PRE-emergence herbicides is limited to certain regions or counties in Wisconsin. Prior to selecting a herbicide for your weed management program, make sure the same is approved for use in your region by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://datcp.wi.gov/Pages/Homepage.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Department of Agriculture, Trade and Consumer Protection (DATCP)&lt;/a&gt;. Below are examples of herbicides that have geographic restrictions in Wisconsin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;atrazine&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Atrazine&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atrazine (Photosystem II Inhibitor, Group 5) is a commonly used corn herbicide. In Wisconsin, there are areas where the use of atrazine is prohibited (see map below). For more information on atrazine restrictions check &lt;a href=&#34;https://datcp.wi.gov/Pages/Programs_Services/Atrazine.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;DATCP information on Atrazine&lt;/a&gt; and always read the product label for rates and restrictions.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 Herbicide Restrictions/Atrazine Prohibition Area.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Atrazine&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;isoxaflutole&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Isoxaflutole&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isoxaflutole (HPPD-inhibitor, Group 27) is a PRE-emergence herbicide used for weed control in corn. Isoxaflutole-based herbicides such as Corvus and Balance Flexx are approved for use in 12 Wisconsin counties (Columbia, Dane, Fond du Lac, Jefferson, Sauk, Grant, Lafayette, Walworth, Dodge, Green, Rock, and Waukesha; see map below). See product label for rates and restrictions.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 Herbicide Restrictions/Isoxaflutole approved counties.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Isoxaflutole&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chlorimuron-ethyl&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chlorimuron-ethyl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chlorimuron-ethyl (ALS-inhibitor, Group 2) is the active ingredient in the POST-emergence soybean herbicide Classic. Chlorimuron-ethyl is also an active ingredient in several PRE-emergence soybean herbicides such as Authority XL, Canopy, Canopy EX, Enlite, Fierce XLT, Rowel FX, Synchrony XP, Trivence and Valor XLT. The use of most chlorimuron-ethyl based herbicides is typically limited to fields south of I-90 between Lacrosse and Madison and fields south of I-94 between Madison and Milwaukee (see map below). See product label(s) for rates and restrictions.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 Herbicide Restrictions/Chlorimuron-ethyl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Chlorimuron-ethyl&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fomesafen&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fomesafen&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fomesafen (PPO-inhibitor, Group 14) is the active ingredient in the POST-emergence soybean herbicide Flextar. Fomesafen is also an active ingredient in the PRE-emergence soybean herbicides Prefix and Warrant Ultra. The maximum use rates of fomesafen changes across Wisconsin (e.g., a higher rate can be used south of U.S. Highway 18 between Prairie Du Chien and Madison, and south of Interstate 94 between Madison and Milwaukee [Region 3 in the map below]). In Region 3, a maximum of 0.313 lb ai/A of fomesafen may be applied in alternate years. In Region 4, a maximum of 0.25 lb ai/A of fomesafen may be applied in alternate years. Due to carryover potential, don’t apply fomesafen on the white regions in the Wisconsin map. See product label(s) for rates and restrictions.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 Herbicide Restrictions/Fomesafen.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Fomesafen&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pendimethalin&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pendimethalin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pendimethalin (Microtubule Inhibitor, Group 3) is the active ingredient in the PRE-emergence herbicide Prowl H20. There are no geographic restrictions for Prowl H2O use in Wisconsin; however, there are differences in the application window for corn and soybeans. In corn, Prowl H2O can be used PRE-emergence and POST-emergence [“until field corn is 30-inches tall (20-inches to 24-inches tall for popcorn, popcorn seed, field seed, and fresh sweet corn) or in the V8 growth stage, which ever is more restrictive” according to the label]. In soybeans, Prowl H2O can only be sprayed PRE-plant in Wisconsin. See label for rates and restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-assistance-with-herbicide-selection&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For assistance with herbicide selection&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://learningstore.uwex.edu/Assets/pdfs/A3646.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pest Management in Wisconsin Field Crops&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
UWEX Bulletin A3646 (PDF)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://ipcm.wisc.edu/download/pubsPM/Herbicide-Mode-of-Action.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wisconsin Herbicide Mode of Action Chart&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;center-always-read-the-product-label-center&#34;&gt;&lt;center&gt; &lt;em&gt;Always read the product label.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/center&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2018 Wisconsin Cropping Systems Weed Science Survey - Where are we at?</title>
      <link>/post/2018-wisconsin-cropping-systems-weed-science-survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-wisconsin-cropping-systems-weed-science-survey/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist) and&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/maxwelco&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Maxwel Oliveira&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Postdoctoral Research Associate)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objective of our survey was to evaluate the main weed species and management strategies adopted in Wisconsin cropping systems, particularly in corn and soybeans. The survey was conducted this winter during the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ipcm.wisc.edu/blog/2017/12/2018-wisconsin-agronomy-update-meetings/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2018 Wisconsin Agronomy Update Meetings&lt;/a&gt;, held across the state. A total of 286 respondents, representing 54 counties, completed the survey. Herein we present a summary of the main survey results with the hope these may help stakeholders with management decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;primary-role-of-survey-respondents&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Primary role of survey respondents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agronomists and farmers were the main participants in our survey.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 WI survey/Figure 1. survey respondents.png&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Figure 1. Bla&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;crops-managed-by-survey-respondents&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crops managed by survey respondents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corn, soybeans, alfalfa and wheat, respectively, are the main crops managed by survey respondents.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 WI survey/Figure 2. crops managed.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 2&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;adoption-of-tillage&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adoption of tillage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tillage is a common practice in Wisconsin cropping systems according to survey respondents.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 WI survey/Figure 3. adoption of tillage.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 3&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;most-troublesome-weeds&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most troublesome weeds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Waterhemp, giant ragweed, common lambsquarters, and common ragweed, respectively, are considered the most troublesome weed species in Wisconsin cropping systems according to survey respondents.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 WI survey/Figure 4. most troublesome weeds in wisconsin.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 4&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;perceived-presence-of-glyphosate-resistant-weeds&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Perceived presence of glyphosate-resistant weeds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Waterhemp, giant ragweed, and horseweed (aka marestail) are the main weed species that have evolved resistance to glyphosate in Wisconsin according to survey respondents.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 WI survey/Figure 5. gr weeds.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 5&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;perceived-presence-of-weed-s-resistant-to-a-herbicide-site-of-action-soa-other-than-glyphosate&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Perceived presence of weed(s) resistant to a herbicide site-of-action (SOA) other than glyphosate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Several survey respondents reported the occurrence of ALS-resistant waterhemp and giant ragweed in Wisconsin.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 WI survey/Figure 6. hr weeds.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 6&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;adoption-of-1-vs-2-pass-herbicide-program-in-corn-and-soybeans&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adoption of 1- vs 2-pass herbicide program in corn and soybeans&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A 1-pass herbicide program is still pretty common in Wisconsin, particularly in corn.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 WI survey/Figure 7. 1 vs 2 pass.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 7&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;anticipated-adoption-of-auxin-tolerant-crops-such-as-xtend-dicamba-tolerant-and-enlist-2-4-d-tolerant-soybeans&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anticipated adoption of auxin-tolerant crops such as Xtend (dicamba-tolerant) and Enlist (2,4-D tolerant) soybeans&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The adoption of auxin-tolerant crops in Wisconsin will likely not be as high as in central and southern states.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 WI survey/Figure 8. auxin tolerant crops.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 8&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;adoption-of-or-interest-in-cover-crops&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adoption of or interest in cover crops&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Several survey respondents reported the adoption or expressed interest in adopting cover crops in Wisconsin.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 WI survey/Figure 9. cover crops.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 9&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned-from-the-survey&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lessons learned from the survey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wisconsin cropping systems are very diversified in terms of crop rotation and tillage is a common strategy. The combination of crop rotation and tillage has likely helped postpone the selection for herbicide-resistant weeds (when comparing to the situation in neighboring states). Thus, Wisconsin farmers, continue to do what you have been doing, it&amp;rsquo;s working!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite the &amp;ldquo;delayed&amp;rdquo; arrival, herbicide-resistant weeds are here to stay, and perhaps more widespread than some of us may think (check this presentation: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HR1KFvHgYr0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2018 Update on Herbicide Resistant Weeds in Wisconsin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). In order to manage herbicide-resistant weeds, besides continuing to deploy integrated weed management strategies (e.g., crop rotations, tillage, cover crops), farmers may have to consider adjusting their herbicide programs. A two pass program may be necessary to control the troublesome weed species with extended emergence window we are dealing with (e.g., waterhemp, giant ragweed, common lambsquarters). The addition of herbicides with soil residual activity in herbicide programs will enhance the control of these troublesome weeds and reduce the selection pressure on POST-emergence herbicides.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;For assistance with herbicide selection, check:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://learningstore.uwex.edu/Assets/pdfs/A3646.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pest Management in Wisconsin Field Crops&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
UWEX Bulletin A3646 (PDF)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://ipcm.wisc.edu/download/pubsPM/Herbicide-Mode-of-Action.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wisconsin Herbicide Mode of Action Chart&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;br /&gt;
Always read the product label.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lower interest in auxin-tolerant crops in Wisconsin is likely due to i) high diversity of sensitive crops in the landscape and concerns with off-target movement, ii) relative small fields, reducing the practically for the adoption of the technology due to buffer restrictions, and iii) lower incidence of herbicide-resistant weeds thus less need for the technology (as compared to neighboring states).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There seems to be high interest in incorporating cover crops in Wisconsin cropping systems. When deciding how best to use cover crops, it is important to consider the ultimate goal. Is it to increase soil organic matter, increase nutrient availability to subsequent crops, reduce soil compaction, supply forage for livestock, and/or suppress weeds? Answering these questions will help identify the cover crops strategies that offer the best chance of success for meeting the goal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;WiscWeeds&lt;/strong&gt; program will be investigating the several topics addressed in this survey: i) distribution and management of herbicide-resistant weeds, ii) the fit of auxin-tolerant crops in Wisconsin, and iii) cover crop management strategies. To stay tuned about our research updates and field days this summer, follow us on Twitter &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/WiscWeeds&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;@WiscWeeds&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the survey respondents for valuable feedback and to Maxwel Oliveira for compiling the results.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcoming New WiscWeeds Team Members</title>
      <link>/post/welcoming-new-wiscweeds-team-members/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/welcoming-new-wiscweeds-team-members/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am excited to introduce and welcome the new members of the Wisconsin Cropping Systems Weed Science (&lt;strong&gt;WiscWeeds&lt;/strong&gt;) Program: Maxwel Oliveira, Ryan DeWerff, Sarah Striegel, Victor Ribeiro and Nikola Arsenijevic.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/team/Maxwel Oliveira.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Maxwel Oliveira&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://maxweeds.rbind.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Maxwel Coura Oliveira&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Postdoctoral Research Associate)&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Maxwel started at the University of Wisconsin-Madison as a Weed Science Postdoctoral Research Associate in January 2018 in Dr. Werle’s program. Maxwel was born in the state of Minas Gerais, Brazil. He earned his B.S. in Agronomy and M.S. in Weed Science from the Federal University of Jequitinhonha and Mucuri Valleys, Brazil under Dr. Jose Barbosa dos Santos. He received his PhD in Weed Science from the University of Nebraska-Lincoln in December 2017 under Dr. Stevan Knezevic. Maxwel is interested in investigating the distribution and management of herbicide-resistant weeds in Wisconsin, and evaluating weed management strategies in corn, soybeans and small grains. Maxwel is responsible for training the Badger Weeds Team, mentoring undergraduate and graduate students in the WiscWeeds program, and assist with the Wisconsin Herbicide Evaluation Program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/team/Ryan DeWerff.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Ryan DeWerff&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ryan DeWerff&lt;/strong&gt; (Research Specialist)&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ryan started at the University of Wisconsin-Madison as a Weed Science Research Specialist in March 2018. Ryan grew up in central Illinois, where he was actively involved in the production of corn and soybean on his family’s farm. He received his B.S. in Crop Science at the University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign in Fall 2011. Ryan earned his M.S. in Agronomy at the University of Wisconsin-Madison in 2014, where he specialized in weed science under Dr. Vince Davis.  As part of his thesis, he researched how current soybean planting date and seeding rate recommendations affect weed management decisions in Wisconsin soybean production systems.  Ryan manages the Wisconsin Herbicide Evaluation Program and provides technical assistance for ongoing WiscWeeds program and graduate student research projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/team/Sarah Striegel.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sarah Striegel&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sarah Striegel&lt;/strong&gt; (MS Graduate Student)&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Sarah started at the University of Wisconsin-Madison as an MS student in Agronomy in April 2018, specializing in weed science under Dr. Rodrigo Werle. She was awarded the R. Gordon Harvey Wisconsin Distinguished Graduate Fellowship in Weed Science and the O.N. Allen Graduate Scholarship to support her studies. Sarah grew up in southern Iowa on a row crop corn and soybean farm. She earned her B.S. in Agronomy, Crop Management and Business at Iowa State University in December 2017. Her graduate research focuses on the evaluation of dicamba’s effectiveness as a tool for weed control in resistant crops and managing the risk of off-target movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/team/Victor Ribeiro.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Victor Ribeiro&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Victor Ribeiro&lt;/strong&gt; (Visiting MS Graduate Student)&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Victor will spend one year at the University of Wisconsin-Madison as a visiting M.S. graduate student under Dr. Rodrigo Werle. Victor comes from the state of Minas Gerais, Brazil. He is currently an M.S. student in Crop Production at the Federal University of Jequitinhonha and Mucuri Valleys, Brazil, under Dr. Jose Barbosa dos Santos, where they are studying the fate of 2,4-D and dicamba in soil. Victor earned his B.S. in Agronomy at the same institution in March 2018 and was an active student in Dr. Barbosa’s weed science program throughout his degree. As a visiting M.S. graduate student at UW-Madison, Victor will study the fate of dicamba in soil and also participate in several projects conducted by the WiscWeeds Program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/team/Nikola Arsenijevic.png&#34; alt=&#34;Nikola Arsenijevic&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nikola Arsenijevic&lt;/strong&gt; (MS Graduate Student)&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Nikola will start at the University of Wisconsin-Madison as an MS student in Agronomy this summer, specializing in weed science under Dr. Rodrigo Werle. Nikola grew up in a small town in central Republic of Serbia. He received his B.S. in Crop Protection at University of Belgrade, Serbia, in Fall 2017. As an undergraduate student, he conducted weed science research under Dr. Sava Vrbnicanin. His graduate research project will focus on the impact of soil-applied PPO and PSII herbicides on early season soybean development and Palmer amaranth control. Part of Nikola’s MS research was conducted in Western Nebraska during his senior internship at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln under Dr. Werle.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Talk</title>
      <link>/presentation/example-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/presentation/example-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Embed your slides or video here using &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/post/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;. Further details can easily be added using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
