<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wisconsin Weed Science on Wisconsin Weed Science</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Wisconsin Weed Science on Wisconsin Weed Science</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 WiscWeeds</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Can brand or generic herbicides be tank-mixed? Part-3 (we keep learning!) </title>
      <link>/post/can-brand-or-generic-herbicides-be-tank-mixed-part-3-we-keep-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/can-brand-or-generic-herbicides-be-tank-mixed-part-3-we-keep-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week I released a blog post attempting to address the question regarding tank mixing S-metolachlor/safened metolachlor, atrazine and/or mesotrione-based products for weed control in corn (see: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/can-brand-or-generic-herbicides-be-tank-mixed-part-2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Can brand or generic herbicides be tank-mixed? Part-2&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mesotrione products that I checked during my label search (i.e., Callisto, Explorer, Mesotrione 4SC and Meso Star) stated the following restriction: &lt;em&gt;“DO NOT apply this product post-emergence in a tank mix with emulsifiable concentrate grass herbicides, unless specifically directed under one of the tank mix section of this label, or crop injury can occur”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;S-metolachlor products such as Duall II Magnum, Medal EC and Brawl, and safened metolachlor products such as Me-Too-Lachlor II and Stalwart C labeled for use in corn fall under the &lt;strong&gt;emulsifiable concentrate grass herbicides&lt;/strong&gt; formulation category and thus &lt;strong&gt;SHOULD NOT&lt;/strong&gt; be tank-mixed with the &lt;strong&gt;aforementioned&lt;/strong&gt; mesotrione products for POST-emergence applications in corn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HOWEVER&lt;/strong&gt;, there are several S-metolachlor/safened metolachlor and mesotrione products out there and of course I missed checking the label of some. This week I received calls from chemical retailers in Wisconsin mentioning that my blog post was not completely accurate. Guess what? They were right. I even stated the following in the previous article &lt;em&gt;“Once this post is released there will likely be a “Part 3” coming next because I will certainly forget to address something important; going through the label exercise is not a simple task! That’s when experience comes into play. Growers should always consult an expert before spraying a custom herbicide tank mix. Always read the product label before spraying.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the feedback I received, Drexel Chemical Company has a mesotrione product called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drexchem.com/products/mesotryone-4l-2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MesoTryOne 4L&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. In their &lt;a href=&#34;https://s3-us-west-1.amazonaws.com/www.agrian.com/pdfs/Drexel1a_MesoTryOne_4L_Label.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;label&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (page 2), instead of having the particular tank mix being discussed herein under &lt;strong&gt;RESTRICTIONS&lt;/strong&gt;, they have it under &lt;strong&gt;USE PRECAUTIONS&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;“Post-emergence applications of this product in tank-mixes with emulsifiable concentrate grass herbicides may cause severe corn injury or yield loss under adverse weather conditions”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in this case, the tank mixing of an emulsifiable concentrate grass herbicide with MesoTryOne 4L POST-emergence in corn is considered a legal application; however, the label states that you must apply under “non-adverse weather conditions” to reduce the potential of crop injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you go to &lt;em&gt;“Table 5. Tank-mixtures of this Product for PRE-emergence Application in Corn”&lt;/em&gt; (page 9 of the MesoTryOne 4L label), you will see that the mixture of MesoTryOne 4L with Metolachlor (e.g., Me-Too-Lachlor II, Duall II Magnum) is listed; but the same tank mixture is not listed in &lt;em&gt;“Table 6. Tank-mixtures of this Product for Post-emergence Application in Corn”&lt;/em&gt; (page 9 of the label). Moreover, the tank mixture of commercial pre-mixes of Atrazine + Metolachlor (e.g., Trizmet, Bicep II Magnum) with MesoTryOne 4L are listed in Table 6,  but keep in mind that these pre-mixes are formulated as a suspension concentrate. The concern regarding crop injury comes from having mesotrione tank mixed and sprayed POST-emergence with emulsifiable concentrate grass herbicides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I truly appreciate the positive criticism and feedback from the clientele! Though my post was not 100% accurate, I certainly got folks to take a close look at the labels (mission accomplished!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, going through the label exercise is not a simple task! That’s when experience comes into play. Growers should always consult an expert before spraying a custom herbicide tank mix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer: I am not endorsing Drexel Chemical Company and the use of their product MesoTryone 4L (nor the opposite). I am just using their product as a pertinent example for the discussions regarding custom herbicide tank mixtures and label restrictions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always read the product label before spraying.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can brand or generic herbicides be tank-mixed? Part-2</title>
      <link>/post/can-brand-or-generic-herbicides-be-tank-mixed-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/can-brand-or-generic-herbicides-be-tank-mixed-part-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month we released a blog post entitled &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/can-brand-or-generic-herbicides-be-tank-mixed/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Can brand or generic herbicides be tank-mixed?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and in the first paragraph we wrote &lt;em&gt;“This past week we received several questions regarding herbicide tank mixtures. One common question was whether brand and/or generic S-metolachlor/metolachlor, atrazine and/or mesotrione-based products could be tank-mixed”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After speaking with industry colleagues, I learned that in the original blog post we described several important aspects to consider when developing a custom herbicide tank mix but did not actually answer if S-metolachlor/safened metolachlor, atrazine and/or mesotrione-based products could be tank-mixed; herein I will attempt to address this question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, the answer is &lt;strong&gt;“it depends”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lumax EZ is a popular pre-mix corn herbicide that contains S-metolachlor, atrazine and mesotrione. Lumax EZ herbicide can be sprayed PRE and early-POST in corn (according to the label: &lt;em&gt;“Postemergence applications to field corn must be made before crop reaches 12 inches in height”&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a grower decides to make his/her own “Lumax-equivalent” custom tank mix, that tank mix can be sprayed before corn emergence. After corn emergence, there is a caveat to be considered; the label of mesotrione-based products such as Callisto, Explorer, Mesotrione 4SC and Meso Star state the following restriction: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“DO NOT apply this product post-emergence in a tank mix with emulsifiable concentrate grass herbicides, unless specifically directed under one of the tank mix section of this label, or crop injury can occur”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;S-metolachlor-based products such as Duall II Magnum, Medal EC and Brawl, and safened metolachlor-based products such as Me-Too-Lachlor and Stalwart C labeled for use in corn fall under the &lt;strong&gt;emulsifiable concentrate grass herbicides&lt;/strong&gt; formulation category and thus &lt;strong&gt;SHOULD NOT&lt;/strong&gt; be tank-mixed with the aforementioned mesotrione-based products for POST-emergence applications in corn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q&amp;amp;A:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can S-metolachlor/safened metolachlor be tank-mixed with atrazine and sprayed POST-emergence in corn? &lt;strong&gt;YES&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can mesotrione be tank-mixed with atrazine and sprayed POST-emergence in corn? &lt;strong&gt;YES&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can S-metolachlor/safened metolachlor be tank-mixed with mesotrione and sprayed POST-emergence in corn? &lt;strong&gt;NO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can S-metolachlor/safened metolachlor, atrazine and mesotrione be tank-mixed and sprayed POST-emergence in corn? &lt;strong&gt;NO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, pay attention to the: i) geographic restrictions (for instance atrazine use is prohibited in parts of Wisconsin), ii) maximum use rate of a pesticide per application and iii) total pesticide use within a season. Always follow the most restrictive tank mix instructions for the products involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check our 2018 post &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/geographic-restrictions-for-corn-and-soybean-pre-emergence-herbicides-in-wisconsin/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Geographic Restrictions for Corn and Soybean PRE-emergence Herbicides in Wisconsin”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for additional geographic restriction information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once this post is released there will likely be a “Part 3” coming next because I will certainly forget to address something important; going through the label exercise is not a simple task! That’s when experience comes into play. Growers should always consult an expert before spraying a custom herbicide tank mix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always read the product label before spraying.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Herbicide Rotation Restrictions Before Planting Industrial Hemp</title>
      <link>/post/herbicide-rotation-restrictions-before-planting-industrial-hemp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/herbicide-rotation-restrictions-before-planting-industrial-hemp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By Nick Arneson (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist), David Wang (UW-Madison Undergraduate Research Scholar) and &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the growing interest in producing industrial hemp in Wisconsin and beyond, it is important to pay close attention to rotation interval restrictions when planting this crop in conventional production fields where herbicides are adopted. Though no synthetic herbicides are labeled for weed control in industrial hemp in the United States at this time, it’s important to keep in mind that herbicides sprayed in previous crops can have an impact on the industrial hemp crop establishment and development. Moreover, the pesticide label is the law and should be followed accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below you will find a comprehensive list of herbicides commonly used in corn-soybean rotations and their respective plant rotation restrictions (in months after application) for industrial hemp planting according to their respective labels. Note that the most restrictive interval for each product is listed below (for some products the rotation restriction may be shorter depending upon rate used, geography, soil pH, annual precipitation, etc.; please double check the label). Since industrial hemp is a new crop and thus not part of current label languages, its rotational restrictions fall under “other crops” when searching for this information in the product labels. See video &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/333384395&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Weed Talk: 2019 Industrial Hemp Herbicide Carryover Considerations”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rotation Restrictions Before Planting Industrial Hemp (in Months After Application):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0 months&lt;/strong&gt; = Cadet, Cobra, Glyphosate 4 Plus, Glyphosate 5.4, Gramoxone SL 2.0, Roundup PowerMAX&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1 month&lt;/strong&gt; = Fusilade DX, Resource, Select Max&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.5 months&lt;/strong&gt; = Harmony SG&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3 months&lt;/strong&gt; = 2,4-D (e.g., 2,4-D Amine, Barrage HF, Salvo, Shredder 2,4-D LV4)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4 months&lt;/strong&gt; = Assure II, dicamba (e.g., Clarity, Engenia, Fexapan, Status, XtendiMax)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6 months&lt;/strong&gt; = Liberty 280&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9 months&lt;/strong&gt; = Confidence, Harness, Outlook, Sharpen, Verdict, Warrant&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12 months&lt;/strong&gt; = Aim, Authority Elite, Boundary, Cinch, Command 3ME, Dual II Magnum, Parallel&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;18 months&lt;/strong&gt; = Anthem, Anthem Maxx, Armezon, Authority MTZ, Balance Flexx, Basis Blend, Beacon, Callisto, Callisto GT, Corvus, Dimetric DF 75%, FirstRate, Halex GT, Impact, Instigate, Lumax EZ, Prefix, Prequel, Raptor, Require Q, Resolve DF, Resolve Q, Resolve SG, Rowel, Solstice, Spirit, Valor SX, Valor EZ, Vise, Zemax, Zidua, Zidua SC&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;24 months&lt;/strong&gt; = Prowl H2O&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;26 months&lt;/strong&gt; = Hornet, SureStart II, TripleFLEX&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;30 months&lt;/strong&gt; = Authority Assist, Authority First, Canopy, Classic, Enlite, Envive, Rowel FX, Sonic, Synchrony, Trivence, Valor XLT&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;36 months&lt;/strong&gt; = Authority Maxx, Authority XL, Permit&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;40 months&lt;/strong&gt; = Extreme, Optill, Optill PRO, Pursuit, Torment&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will soon release an in-detail publication with additional information on how herbicide rates and soil characteristics influence rotational Industrial Hemp crop restrictions. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always read, understand and follow the pesticide label.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can brand or generic herbicides be tank-mixed? </title>
      <link>/post/can-brand-or-generic-herbicides-be-tank-mixed/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/can-brand-or-generic-herbicides-be-tank-mixed/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;br /&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;https://fyi.extension.wisc.edu/pat/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Glenn Nice&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Pesticide Applicator Training Program Manager)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the onset of the spray season and concerns regarding waterhemp and other troublesome weed species, farmers and consultants are further diversifying and including herbicides with soil residual activity in their weed control programs. This past week we received several questions regarding herbicide tank mixtures. One common question was whether brand and/or generic s-metolachlor/metolachlor-, atrazine- and/or mesotrione-based products could be tank-mixed. The Federal Insecticide, Fungicide and Rodenticide Act &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/federal-insecticide-fungicide-and-rodenticide-act-fifra-and-federal-facilities&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;FIFRA&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; allows for the tank mixing of any pesticides or pesticides with fertilizer when &lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt; prohibited on the label. This means that, as long as it is not prohibited on the label, you can mix various registered labeled herbicides for weed control in a particular crop. However, there are a few things you should be aware of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;follow the proper order for tank mixing (see Purdue Extension Publication: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ppp.purdue.edu/wp-content/uploads/files/PPP-122.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Avoid Tank Mixing Errors&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some pesticides are not compatible (they can be chemically or physically incompatible). Thus, a jar test should be conducted prior to mixing and spraying to assure the products are indeed compatible. Remember, you are responsible if the mix “goes bad” in the tank.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;follow the most restrictive tank mix instructions for the products involved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keep in mind that use rates vary by product and formulation; don&amp;rsquo;t assume that rates are the same for all products with the same active ingredient.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;many labels, for example the new dicamba products registered for use in dicamba-resistant soybeans (Xtend), have statements such as: &lt;strong&gt;use approved tank mix products as directed by the label or website&lt;/strong&gt;. This statement prohibits all tank mixes except for the ones the manufacturer has approved and specifies in their labels or webpages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While making your own pre-mix may reduce costs, it may increase the chances for error (e.g., the likelihood of accurately picking and measuring one product off of the shelf is higher than when multiple tank mix partners are involved) thus increasing the potential for crop injury, carryover concerns and/or lack of appropriate weed control. Commercially available pre-mix herbicides have been extensively studied by the chemical companies with the objective to enhance weed control while minimizing crop injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When developing a custom pre-mix or selecting a commercially available pre-mix herbicide, it’s important that farmers and crop consultants understand their target weed species and soil types, and have a solid crop rotation plan in mind. Knowing the weed species present in a particular field will allow for selecting effective active ingredient(s) to optimize weed control while minimizing the spray of unnecessary active ingredients. Understanding that soils (texture, pH and OM) vary across and within fields will allow for proper herbicide rate selection, optimizing weed control while minimizing chances for crop injury and/or carryover into subsequent crops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-assistance-with-herbicide-selection&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For assistance with herbicide selection&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://learningstore.uwex.edu/Assets/pdfs/A3646.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pest Management in Wisconsin Field Crops&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
UWEX Bulletin A3646&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ipcm.wisc.edu/download/pubsPM/Herbicide-Mode-of-Action.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wisconsin Herbicide Mode of Action Chart&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always read, understand and follow the pesticide label.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://horticulture.wisc.edu/directory/jed-colquhoun/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Jed Colquhoun&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Professor and Extension Weed Scientist) for valuable feedback towards this article.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are You PRE-pared for the Soybean (and Waterhemp) Growing Season?</title>
      <link>/post/are-you-pre-pared-for-the-soybean-growing-season/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/are-you-pre-pared-for-the-soybean-growing-season/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;br /&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;http://coolbean.info/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Shawn Conley&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Soybean and Small Grain Specialist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spring has arrived rather quickly in Wisconsin and the planting season is right around the corner (or perhaps it has already started for some growers). Before getting their soybeans in the ground, farmers should make sure they have solid weed management plans for the growing season, particularly if waterhemp is present in their operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to our &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/2018-wisconsin-cropping-systems-weed-science-survey/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2018 SURVEY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, several Wisconsin soybean fields get only treated with a one-pass POST-emergence herbicide program (keep in mind that pre-plant tillage is a common practice adopted in Wisconsin cropping systems and that helps farmers “start clean”). Because of the widespread occurrence of waterhemp populations resistant to glyphosate and/or other POST-emergence herbicides (e.g., ALS- and PPO-inhibitors; see article: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/herbicide-resistance-in-wisconsin-an-overview/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Herbicide Resistance in Wisconsin: An Overview”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) combined with its extended emergence window (mid-May through July), a one-pass POST-emergence program in soybeans is likely not a viable strategy in fields infested with waterhemp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, research conducted across the Midwest has demonstrated the importance of keeping the soybean crop weed-free from establishment through the V3 growth stage &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coolbean.info/library/documents/2017_Soybean_GrowthDev_Guide_FINAL.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;3rd trifoliate&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. Weeds emerging after the V3 growth stage will likely not impact soybean yield; however, they should still be proactively managed to prevent them from reproducing and replenishing the seedbank (remember “no seed, no weed”). Thus, effective PRE-emergence herbicides can help farmers maintain their fields weed-free during initial establishment of the crop (= achieve full yield potential) and also reduce the selection pressure on POST-emergence herbicides (due to fewer weeds to be controlled POST-emergence), helping on the fight against herbicide resistance.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 Soybean PRE/Value of PRE.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;PRE&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
Several PRE-emergence herbicides are available for soybeans. Most of them should be applied pre-plant up to 3 days after planting (see product label). To maximize their residual activity in-season, PRE-emergence herbicides should be sprayed at or shortly after planting. PRE-emergence herbicides need moisture for incorporation and activation in the soil. If there are established weeds at the time of PRE-emergence application and no additional pre-plant field cultivation will take place, it’s important to have an effective burndown herbicide in the tank-mix. A PRE-emergence herbicide containing 2 or more effective sites of action (SOA) will likely provide control of a wider range of weed species when compared to the use of a single SOA. Using multiple effective SOA during each pass is also a proactive strategy for herbicide resistance management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018 we conducted a study to evaluate and demonstrate the effectiveness of multiple PRE-emergence soybean herbicides (see results: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/img/2018%20waterhemp%20challenge/Waterhemp%20Management%20PRE%20Comparison_Lancaster%20WI%202018.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2018 UW Waterhemp Challenge: Comparison of Soil Residual Herbicides&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). While these results should be taken with a grain of salt (only one year of data), they clearly indicate the value of PRE-emergence herbicides and the programs that don’t work. This study will be replicated at multiple locations during the 2019 growing season. Stay tuned for our field days!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 Soybean PRE/2018 PRE Results.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;PRE&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When selecting a PRE-emergence herbicide program, we challenge agronomists and farmers to balance efficacy (using our results and their experience), product cost, and rotation restrictions. We also encourage farmers to use the labeled rate for their soils. The residual activity of a PRE-emergence herbicides is dependent on the rates applied; cutting rates is not a recommended strategy when attempting to manage troublesome weeds like waterhemp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to note that under cool and wet conditions during crop emergence, PRE-emergence herbicides containing metribuzin (Group 5), PPO-inhibitors (Group 14; e.g.: flumioxazin, saflufenacil, sulfentrazone) and VLCFA-inhibitors (Group 15; e.g.: acetochlor, dimetenamid-P, pyroxasulfone and S-metolachlor) may cause some early-season crop injury, particularly in lighter soils with low OM and/or higher pH. Our preliminary research in Nebraska has demonstrated that early-season crop injury caused by metribuzin (group 5) and sulfentrazone (group 14) did not lead to yield reduction (soybeans are indeed very resilient). Moreover, the benefit of an early-season weed-free field outweighs the concerns of early-season crop injury (assuming a herbicide is applied according to the label and no significant stand reduction is observed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To visualize the various types of injury potentially caused by different SOA herbicides, check our &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/img/2018%20Herbicide%20SOA%20injury%20chart/2018_HerbicideInjury_EN.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Herbicide Site of Action Key for Crop Injury Symptoms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-assistance-with-herbicide-selection&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For assistance with herbicide selection&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://learningstore.uwex.edu/Assets/pdfs/A3646.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pest Management in Wisconsin Field Crops&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
UWEX Bulletin A3646&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ipcm.wisc.edu/download/pubsPM/Herbicide-Mode-of-Action.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wisconsin Herbicide Mode of Action Chart&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always read, understand and follow the pesticide label.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strategies and Considerations for Termination of Cereal Rye Cover Crop</title>
      <link>/post/considerations-and-strategies-for-termination-of-cereal-rye-cover-crop/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/considerations-and-strategies-for-termination-of-cereal-rye-cover-crop/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist),
&lt;a href=&#34;http://ipcm.wisc.edu/contacts/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dan Smith&lt;/a&gt; (UW NPM Southwest Wisconsin Regional Specialist) and &lt;a href=&#34;http://coolbean.info/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Shawn Conley&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Soybean and Small Grain Specialist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Adapted from original article written by Rodrigo Werle and Dan Smith, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fall-planted cereal rye is increasingly used as a cover crop to protect the soil during winter and spring in corn and soybean cropping systems across the Midwest. Our &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/2018-wisconsin-cropping-systems-weed-science-survey/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2018 survey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; indicated that 77% of Wisconsin farmers and Ag professionals are interested in cover crops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fall-planted cereal rye is awakening and will start growing rapidly in southern Wisconsin; thus, it’s important to have a termination plan in mind prior to crop establishment. The following pictures demonstrate the rapid cereal rye growth during a 10-day interval in the spring of 2018:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 cc rye termination/IMG_2102.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;small&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1. Picture of a cereal rye cover crop field in south-central Wisconsin taken on April 30, 2018.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 cc rye termination/IMG_2163.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;large&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2. Picture of the same cereal rye cover crop field in south-central Wisconsin taken on May 10, 2018.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;cereal-rye-cover-crop-termination-strategies&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cereal Rye Cover Crop Termination Strategies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;herbicides&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Herbicides&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research conducted in Missouri showed that 28 fl oz of Roundup (glyphosate) provided satisfactory control of cereal rye (Figure 3). The early termination treatment (early-April) resulted in slightly better control than the later termination treatment (early-May). Glyphosate efficacy decreases when plants reach reproductive stages. The contact herbicide Gramoxone was also tested and was not as effective as glyphosate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 cc rye termination/Missouri Visual Control.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Missouri&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3. Influence of herbicide treatments and application timings on the control of cereal rye cover crop (results averaged across 3 years of research in Missouri). Data collected by Dr. Kevin Bradley’s research group at the University of Missouri.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research conducted in Wisconsin also demonstrated that glyphosate provided successful termination of cereal rye (see: &lt;a href=&#34;http://ipcm.wisc.edu/download/pubsPM/AnnualRye_WinterRye_Glyphosate.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Termination of winter rye and annual ryegrass using glyphosate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;roller-crimper&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roller-Crimper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to research conducted in Pennsylvania, roller-crimpers can be used effectively for cereal rye termination after the boot stage (Figure 4). Although not widely used across the Midwest, the use of roller-crimpers is a viable strategy for producers that would like to have additional biomass in the spring before crop planting and use a mechanical strategy for cover crop termination rather than herbicides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 cc rye termination/Roller Crimper.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;RollerCrimper&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 4. Roller-crimper rolling down cereal rye cover crop in Pennsylvania. Picture obtained from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://integratedweedmanagement.org/index.php/iwm-toolbox/cultural-practices/cover-cropping/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;USDA Integrated Weed Management Resource Center Website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For additional information on roller-crimpers, watch the video: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UtxH4CJa-jk&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advances using the roller-crimper for organic no-till in Wisconsin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;cereal-rye-cover-crop-termination-considerations&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cereal Rye Cover Crop Termination Considerations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If glyphosate is used for cereal rye termination, it should be sprayed when day temperatures are above 55° F and night temperatures are above 40° F. For more effective cereal rye control, glyphosate should be applied before the boot stage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Contact herbicides such as paraquat (e.g., Gramoxone) and glufosinate (e.g., Liberty, Cheetah, Scout, etc.) may be used for cereal rye termination; however, they may not provide adequate control if the cereal rye is at boot or later stages. As with any contact herbicide, practices to improve spray coverage will improve efficacy (e.g., medium spray droplet size and higher application rates [GPA]).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If cereal rye will be harvested for forage, herbicides should be sprayed after biomass harvest and removal from the field to control the cereal rye regrowth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If a legume is part of the cover crop mix, using a growth regulator herbicide such as 2,4-D or dicamba will enhance termination (see planting restrictions prior to selecting a growth regulator for cover crop termination).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If glyphosate-resistant weeds are established at cereal rye termination (e.g., marestail, giant ragweed), adding herbicides such as 2,4-D and/or saflufenacil (e.g., Sharpen) to the tank-mix will assist with their control (see label for planting restrictions).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;UW-Madison and other researchers across the Midwest recommend terminating cover crops before crop planting (see: &lt;a href=&#34;http://coolbean.info/library/documents/CPN-4002.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover Crops Do’s and Don’t’s&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Late termination of cereal rye may reduce the yield potential of the main crop from excessive soil water use, temporary sequestration of plant available nutrients that are critical for the early development of the subsequent cash crop (particularly nitrogen for corn), and/or excessive amounts of residue that can difficult planting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cover crops may suppress troublesome weeds, but typically do not provide complete weed control alone. Combining cover crops and herbicide programs (including PRE-emergence herbicides) can be a powerful strategy for weed management in conventional cropping systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cover crop residue may alter the fate of soil-applied PRE-emergence herbicides. Rainfall after application is necessary to move pre-emergence herbicides into the soil profile.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Producers are encouraged to visit with their insurance provider when deciding the time for cover crop termination.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For additional information on herbicide options, check the &lt;a href=&#34;https://learningstore.uwex.edu/Assets/pdfs/A3646.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pest Management in Wisconsin Field Crops&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; UWEX Bulletin A3646 (PDF). Always check the herbicide labels before application.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2019 Wisconsin Regional Waterhemp Workshops</title>
      <link>/post/2019-wisconsin-regional-waterhemp-workshops/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019-wisconsin-regional-waterhemp-workshops/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to our 2018 weed management &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/2018-wisconsin-cropping-systems-weed-science-survey/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SURVEY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, waterhemp has become the most concerning weed species in field crop production in Wisconsin. Thus, we invite farmers and crop advisors to attend one of our Wisconsin Regional Waterhemp Workshops to be held in four locations across the state in March of 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt; &lt;strong&gt;These workshops are FREE with 3 CEUs (PM) available.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2019 Waterhemp Workshops/2019_WaterhempWorkshopFlyer_final.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Download the Promotional Flyer HERE (PDF File)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These workshops are designed for farmers and crop advisors with little waterhemp experience (Waterhemp 101). Topics include 1) pigweed identification, 2) waterhemp biology, ecology, dispersal and resistance evolution, and 3) herbicide selection and integrated strategies for waterhemp management in alfalfa, corn and soybean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presenters include UW-Madison Extension Weed Scientists Drs. Rodrigo Werle and Mark Renz, UW-NPM Outreach Specialists Dan Smith and Richard Proost, and WiscWeeds Lab Members Dr. Maxwel Oliveira, Ryan DeWerff and Sarah Striegel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants should RSVP with the local contact by &lt;strong&gt;March 14&lt;/strong&gt; (limit of 50 participants per location on a first-come, first-served basis).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;march-19-chippewa-falls-wi&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;March 19: Chippewa Falls, WI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eagles’ Club Banquet Hall, 2588 Hwy 53, Chippewa Falls, WI 54729&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Registration and lunch start at noon&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workshop: 1:00 – 4:00 pm&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jerry Clark, Chippewa County Agriculture Educator&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RSVP:&lt;/strong&gt; 715-726-7950 or jerome.clark@ces.uwex.edu&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;march-20-bangor-wi&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;March 20: Bangor, WI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Log Cabin, N4697 State Rd 162, Bangor, WI 54614&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Registration, coffee and rolls start at 9:30 am&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workshop: 9:45 am – 1:30 pm (lunch: 11:30 – 12:15)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kaitlyn Lance, La Crosse County Agriculture Educator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RSVP:&lt;/strong&gt; 608-785-9593 or uwexmail@lacrossecounty.org&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;march-25-janesville-wi&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;March 25: Janesville, WI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Holiday Inn Express Janesville, 3100 Wellington Place, Janesville, WI 53546&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Registration and lunch start at noon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workshop: 1:00 – 4:00 pm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nick Baker, Rock County Agriculture Educator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RSVP:&lt;/strong&gt; 608-757-5050 or nick.baker@ces.uwex.edu&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;march-26-appleton-wi&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;March 26: Appleton, WI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;D.J. Bordini Center, Room 112-A, Fox Valley Technical College, N Systems Dr, Appleton, WI 54914&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Registration and breakfast start at 7:30 am&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workshop: 8:15 – 11:15 am&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scott Reuss, Marinette County Agriculture Educator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RSVP:&lt;/strong&gt;  715-732-7510 or scott.reuss@ces.uwex.edu&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to our sponsors (BASF, BAYER, FMC, Syngenta and Valent), meals and educational materials will be provided to participants for FREE! Thanks to the UW-NPM Program, Wisconsin Soybean Marketing Board, Wisconsin Corn Promotion Board and United Soybean Board for supporting our waterhemp educational efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For general questions related to the workshops, please contact Dr. Rodrigo Werle at 608-262-7130 or rwerle@wisc.edu.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2018 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report</title>
      <link>/post/2018-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist) and Ryan DeWerff (UW-Madison Weed Science Research Specialist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this report is to share the results of twenty-three corn and soybean herbicide evaluation research trials conducted by the WiscWeeds Program during the 2018 growing season. Information in this report does not constitute a recommendation or endorsement of any particular product or practice. Information in this report also does not replace any information presented on pesticide labels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kudos to Ryan DeWerff, Weed Science Research Specialist &amp;amp; WiscWeeds Herbicide Evaluation Program Coordinator, for leading the efforts pertaining to this research report. Thanks for the WiscWeeds lab (Maxwel Oliveira, Sarah Striegel, Nikola Arsenijevic, Victor Ribeiro and Rachel Renz) and also Dan Smith and Richard Proost (UW NPM Program) for the assistance with establishing the field trials and data collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We sincerely thank the companies and organizations who have generously supported our research program through financial and/or material donations. We would also like to give a special thanks to the many UW faculty, staff, and Arlington and Lancaster Ag Research Stations and Rock County Farm personnel who provided valuable technical assistance with many aspects of the research projects presented herein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;to-download-the-2018-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report-click-here-pdf-file-img-2018-research-report-2018-wiscweeds-research-report-web-pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/img/2018 Research Report/2018 WiscWeeds Research Report_Web.pdf&#34;&gt;To download the 2018 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report, CLICK HERE (PDF FILE)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please do not reproduce information presented within this report for public distribution without the expressed written consent from Dr. Rodrigo Werle.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-trials&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research Trials:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;corn-weed-control-trials&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Corn Weed Control Trials&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Harness Max Applied PRE Compared to Competitors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Harness Max Applied Early POST Compared to Competitors&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sequential Corn Herbicide Evaluation&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Anthem Maxx Tank Mix Partners in 1 and 2-Pass Programs&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Diflexx Duo Applied Early POST Compared to Competitors&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corn Herbicide Evaluation: 1 and 2-Pass Programs&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corvus Length of Residual with Atrazine vs Competitors&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liberty System Comparison with New Rates in Corn&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corn Herbicide System Comparison without Atrazine&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ImpactZ and Impact Efficacy and Crop Safety in 1 and 2-Pass Programs&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corteva Herbicide Programs in Enlist Corn&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Systems Approach to Weed Management in Corn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;soybean-weed-control-trials&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Soybean Weed Control Trials&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Authority Brands Programs Efficacy in Soybean&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Anthem Maxx Applied PRE Compared to Competitors&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Fierce Herbicide in Liberty Link Soybean&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Balance Bean Efficacy in Balance GT Soybean&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corteva Soybean Herbicide Programs&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Systems Approach to Weed Control in Xtend Soybean&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tavium Plus Vaporgrip Technology Efficacy in Xtend Soybean&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engenia PRO System vs Competitors in Xtend Soybean&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Utility of PRE/EPOST Application of Dicamba in Xtend Soybean&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation of Single MOA Soybean Herbicides Applied PRE&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UW Waterhemp Challenge: Comparison of Soil Residual Herbicides&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 Research Report/2018 WiscWeeds Team.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2018-wiscweeds-team&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2018 WiscWeeds Team&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the additional buffer requirements for dicamba applications in Xtend (dicamba-tolerant) crops</title>
      <link>/post/dicamba-buffer-requirements/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/dicamba-buffer-requirements/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On October 31, 2018 the United States &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.epa.gov/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Environmental Protection Agency (EPA)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; announced their decision to extend the registration of the dicamba products Engenia, Fexapan, and Xtendimax for use in dicamba-tolerant crops (Xtend technology) through December 20, 2020; however, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.epa.gov/newsreleases/epa-announces-changes-dicamba-registration&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;additional label changes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; were made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A particular change that has led to some questioning is the new &lt;strong&gt;57-foot omnidirectional buffer&lt;/strong&gt; requirement to protect federally listed threatened and endangered species and critical habitat in specific US counties. On November 19, 2018, EPA posted the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.regulations.gov/document?D=EPA-HQ-OPP-2016-0187-0974&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;list of US counties&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; where threatened and endangered species and critical habitat may exist (thus locations where the new 57-foot buffer must be incorporated).
218 US counties in 24 states are listed; see maps and figure below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 dicamba buffer/map4.png&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Figure 1&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 dicamba buffer/map5.png&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Figure 2&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 dicamba buffer/Figure1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Figure 3&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maps generated my &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/maxwelco&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Maxwel Oliveira&lt;/a&gt;, UW-Madison Weed Science Research Associate. &lt;strong&gt;Information obtained on December 11, 2018&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another significant label change pertaining to buffer requirements is that additional &lt;strong&gt;non-sensitive areas&lt;/strong&gt; may be included as part of the 110-foot downwind buffer and also the 57-foot omnidirectional buffer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to EPA, the following areas (“non-sensitive areas”) may be included in the buffer distance calculation when directly adjacent to the treated field edges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Roads, paved or gravel surfaces, mowed and/or managed areas adjacent to field such as rights of way.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Planted agricultural fields containing: corn, cotton, and soybeans.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Areas covered by the footprint of a building, silo, or other man made structure with walls and or roof.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;/img/2018 dicamba buffer/LimitationForMay 2019 (1).pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EPA Endangered Species Protection Bulletin (valid for May 2019)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;practical-implications-for-certified-applicators&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practical Implications for Certified Applicators:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is required for certified applicators using these products (Engenia, Fexapan and/or Xtendimax) to follow the measures contained in the Endangered Species Bulletins for the area which they are applying the product.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To obtain Bulletins, consult &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.epa.gov/endangered-species&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.epa.gov/endangered-species&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; or call &lt;strong&gt;1-844-447-3813&lt;/strong&gt; no more than six months before using the product. Applicators must use the Bulletin valid for the month in which they will apply the product.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the listed counties where threatened and endangered species and critical habitat may exist, besides the 110-foot downwind buffer, 57-foot buffer around the other sides of the field (omnidirectional) are now required.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In counties where threatened and endangered species and critical habitat are not listed, the 110-foot downwind buffer still applies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Non-sensitive areas described above may be included in the buffer distance calculation when directly adjacent to the treated field edges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;And remember, DO NOT spray if sensitive crops or residential areas are adjacent and downwind of application area.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those interested in the additional pertinent changes in the dicamba label, please visit the EPA website: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.epa.gov/newsreleases/epa-announces-changes-dicamba-registration&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.epa.gov/newsreleases/epa-announces-changes-dicamba-registration&lt;/a&gt; and read the registrants updated labels.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Herbicide Resistance in Wisconsin: An Overview (December 2018)</title>
      <link>/post/herbicide-resistance-in-wisconsin-an-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/herbicide-resistance-in-wisconsin-an-overview/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Joseph Zimbric (UW-Madison Agronomy Graduate Student), &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/dave-stoltenberg/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;David Stoltenberg&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Agronomy Professor), &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/mark-renz/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mark Renz&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Weed Scientist) and &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Weed Scientist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;20-unique-cases-of-herbicide-resistance-in-wisconsin&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;20 Unique Cases of Herbicide Resistance in Wisconsin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;20 unique cases (weed species by herbicide site of action) of herbicide resistance have been confirmed in Wisconsin, including 13 weed species with evolved resistance to one or more herbicide sites of action (Figure 1, Table 1).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first confirmed case of herbicide resistance in Wisconsin was PSII inhibitor resistance in common lambsquarters in 1979.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since then, ALS-inhibitor resistance has been confirmed in more weed species than other type of herbicide resistance, totaling eight weed species including common ragweed, giant ragweed, Palmer amaranth, and waterhemp.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In comparison, PSII inhibitor resistance has been confirmed in four species, whereas ACCase inhibitor resistance has been confirmed in only two species (giant foxtail and large crabgrass).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first confirmed case of glyphosate (an EPSP synthase inhibitor) resistance in Wisconsin was a non-rapid response phenotype of giant ragweed in 2011 (Figure 2). Glyphosate resistance has subsequently been confirmed in horseweed, waterhemp, Palmer amaranth, and most recently, common ragweed in 2018.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 resistance overview/Figure 1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Figure 1&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 resistance overview/Table 1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Table 1&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 resistance overview/Figure 2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Figure 2&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;waterhemp-in-wisconsin&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Waterhemp in Wisconsin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Waterhemp presence has increased rapidly in Wisconsin to include over 400 locations in 61 of 72 counties in the state (Figure 3).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In recent years, glyphosate resistance concerns have focused on waterhemp which has also increased rapidly to include confirmed cases in 28 counties (Figure 4). Among these, multiple resistance to glyphosate and PPO inhibitors has been confirmed in 10 counties.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 resistance overview/Figure 3.png&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Figure 1&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 resistance overview/Figure 4.png&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Figure 2&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;palmer-amaranth-in-wisconsin&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Palmer amaranth in Wisconsin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Palmer amaranth was first identified in Wisconsin in 2011.  Since then, 12 populations have been found among nine counties (Figure 5).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Herbicide resistance in Palmer amaranth has been limited to two cases of confirmed glyphosate resistance and one case of confirmed multiple resistance to ALS inhibitors and the HPPD inhibitor tembotrione (Figure 5).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 resistance overview/Figure 5.png&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Figure 1&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;grower-concerns&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grower Concerns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Glyphosate resistance in waterhemp, and multiple resistance to glyphosate and PPO inhibitors, have increased rapidly in Wisconsin indicating that effective waterhemp management will continue to be a top concern of Wisconsin growers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Herbicide resistance in Palmer amaranth is currently limited to three counties in southern Wisconsin, but glyphosate resistance in two populations, and multiple resistance to ALS and HPPD inhibitors in another population, also have serious management implications for Wisconsin growers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is critical that diversified management tactics be implemented to reduce the spread, persistence, and impact of these and other herbicide-resistant species.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This overview was presented as a poster at the 2018 Annual Meetings of the North Central Weed Science Society in Milwaukee, WI (December 3-6, 2018). Click &lt;a href=&#34;/img/2018 resistance overview/2018 NCWSS_HR in WI_Poster.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HERE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to download the PDF version of the poster.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2018 UW Waterhemp Challenge: Comparison of Soil Residual Soybean Herbicides</title>
      <link>/post/2018-uw-waterhemp-challenge-comparison-of-soil-residual-soybean-herbicides/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-uw-waterhemp-challenge-comparison-of-soil-residual-soybean-herbicides/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist), &lt;a href=&#34;http://ipcm.wisc.edu/contacts/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dan Smith&lt;/a&gt; (UW NPM Southwest Wisconsin Regional Specialist) and &lt;a href=&#34;https://horticulture.wisc.edu/academic_staff/richard-proost/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Richard Proost&lt;/a&gt; (UW NPM Sr. Outreach Specialist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waterhemp management in soybeans was a challenge for several farmers in 2018. As we finalize harvesting our crops, it’s important to properly map the fields infested with waterhemp and start developing an effective management plan for 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of PRE-emergence herbicides is a foundation for waterhemp control in soybeans. According to our &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/2018-wisconsin-cropping-systems-weed-science-survey/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SURVEY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; conducted earlier this year, the use of a single POST herbicide pass is still a common weed control strategy for several farmers in Wisconsin. Unfortunately, as many learned this year, this strategy will likely not work if glyphosate-resistant waterhemp is present in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018 we conducted a study to evaluate and demonstrate the effectiveness of multiple PRE-emergence soybean herbicides. This was a joint effort between the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ipcm.wisc.edu/npm/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UW-Madison Nutrient and Pest Management Program&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (NPM; Dan Smith and Richard Proost) and my team (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/wiscweeds?lang=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WiscWeeds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;; Maxwel Oliveira, Victor Ribeiro, Sarah Striegel, Nikola Arsenijevic, and Ryan DeWerff). The study was conducted at &lt;a href=&#34;https://lancaster.ars.wisc.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UW Lancaster Ag Research Station&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, in Lancaster, Grant County, southwest WI in a field with natural and significant waterhemp and common lambsquarters infestation. Treatments consisted of PRE-emergence soybean herbicides containing one, two and three different active ingredients and/or sites of action. Herbicides were sprayed the day after soybeans were planted. Since we wanted to evaluate the residual activity of the PRE-emergence herbicide treatments throughout the season, no POST-emergence herbicides were sprayed to the research plots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our intent was not to promote one product versus another, instead, demonstrate the value of using an effective PRE-emergence herbicide program. Three well-attended and well-received plot tours were held at the research site in the summer. Per request of those who attended and also from several of those who could not attend the plot tours, we decided to make our 2018 findings available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To download the &lt;a href=&#34;/img/2018 waterhemp challenge/Waterhemp Management PRE Comparison_Lancaster WI 2018.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2018 Preliminary Report of the “UW Waterhemp Challenge: Comparison of Soil Residual Herbicides” (PDF file) click HERE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these results should be taken with a grain of salt (only one year of data), they clearly indicate the value of PRE-emergence herbicides and the programs that don’t work. Moreover, the herbicide rates used in the study are the ones recommended by our industry colleagues and supported by us for a typical Wisconsin Silt Loam soil, thus, valuable information for decision-makers. In this publication we also include site and study information, pictures of plots, and the equivalent rate of single active ingredient products in the premixes evaluated (herbicides with multiple active ingredients).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When selecting a PRE-emergence herbicide program, we challenge agronomists and farmers to balance efficacy (using our results and their experience), product cost, and rotation restrictions. We also encourage farmers to compare their use rates with the ones used in our study (recommended by industry representatives and respective product labels), assuming Silt Loam soils. The residual activity of a PRE-emergence herbicide is dependent on the rates applied; cutting rates is not a recommended strategy when attempting to manage troublesome weeds like waterhemp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This same study will be replicated in at least two Wisconsin locations in 2019. Stay tuned for additional research findings related to our waterhemp control studies and also plot tour opportunities in 2019!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Take-Home from the “2018 Comparison of Soil Residual Soybean Herbicides Study”&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Several PRE-emergence soybean herbicides evaluated provided good levels of waterhemp and lambsquarters control. The onset of waterhemp emergence in the research site was noticed in the first week of June. Because of excessive rainfall in the spring, soybean planting was delayed and happened on 05/24/2018 at the research site; thus, the application of our PRE-emergence treatments (05/25/2018) matched the time waterhemp started to emerge, explaining the overall satisfactory level of weed control observed in most treatments (perfect timing!).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Group 2 herbicides (e.g., Pursuit, Classic, First Rate) applied alone were effective on lambsquarters but NOT on waterhemp. The use of imazethapyr (e.g., Pursuit, Extreme, Thundermaster), which is a common practice in Wisconsin, did not provide satisfactory control of waterhemp. When using imazethapyr (which is an effective herbicide for control of several weed species) as part of the PRE-emergence herbicide program for waterhemp control, the tank mixture with or selection of herbicides that contain other effective active ingredient(s) is recommended.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;PRE-emergence herbicide programs containing multiple effective sites of action are recommended to broaden weed control spectrum and to lower selection for additional herbicide resistance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always read, understand and follow the pesticide label.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgements:&lt;/strong&gt; we would like to thank Mimi Broeske, UW-NPM Senior Editor, for developing the publication layout. Thanks to Doug Wiedenbeck and the UW Lancaster Ag Research Station staff for their support. This study was partially funded by the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wisoybean.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Wisconsin Soybean Marketing Board&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Herbicide Site of Action Key for Crop Injury Symptoms</title>
      <link>/post/herbicide-site-of-action-key-for-crop-injury-symptoms/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/herbicide-site-of-action-key-for-crop-injury-symptoms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist) and&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/maxwelco&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Maxwel Oliveira&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Weed Science Postdoctoral Research Associate)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the widespread occurrence of herbicide-resistant weeds, corn and soybean farmers are having to diversify their herbicide programs to obtain adequate levels of weed control. The increased herbicide diversification increases the likelihood of crop injury due to carryover, misapplication, tank contamination, and/or drift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help you determine which herbicide(s) may be responsible for suspected injury on crops, this key uses the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ipcm.wisc.edu/download/pubsPM/Herbicide-Mode-of-Action.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;herbicide’s site of action (SoA) and respective Weed Science Society of America group number&lt;/a&gt;; herbicides within the same SoA can cause similar symptoms. After reaching a specific SoA, you can check if any of the herbicides from that group are the source of crop response. Herbicide control (selectivity) is specified for broadleaf and/or grass weed species and remember to also observe weeds for injury symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To download the &lt;a href=&#34;/img/2018 Herbicide SOA injury chart/2018_HerbicideInjury_EN.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Herbicide Site of Action Key for Crop Injury Symptoms&amp;rdquo; click HERE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 Herbicide SOA injury chart/Herbicide SOA Chart_EN.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This publication is available from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ipcm.wisc.edu/npm/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UW-Madison Nutrient and Pest Management Program (NPM)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We thank Mimi Broeske (NPM Senior Editor) for developing the publication layout.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wisconsin Waterhemp Herbicide Resistance Project</title>
      <link>/post/wisconsin-waterhemp-herbicide-resistance-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/wisconsin-waterhemp-herbicide-resistance-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to our recent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wiscweeds.info/post/2018-wisconsin-cropping-systems-weed-science-survey/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SURVEY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, waterhemp has become the most concerning weed in row crop production in Wisconsin. Thus, we invite Wisconsin farmers and agronomists to collect waterhemp seeds this fall from their row crop production fields and submit them to UW-Madison for herbicide resistance screenings (we ask farmers to collect samples from only one of their fields; preferably the one with the most troublesome infestation level).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We intend to screen samples in the greenhouse for resistance to glyphosate (Group 9) and also to PPO-inhibitor (e.g., Cobra, Flextar, Cadet; Group 14), ALS-inhibitor (e.g., Pursuit, Classic, FirstRate; Group 2), HPPD-Inhibitor (e.g., Callisto; Group 27), PSII-inhibitor (e.g., Atrazine; Group 5) and Growth Regulator (e.g., dicamba, 2,4-D; Group 4) herbicides. Results will be made available to those who submit the samples after the greenhouse screenings are completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no cost associated to the herbicide resistance screening. The only cost will be your time to collect the seed samples and mailing them to: &lt;strong&gt;Rodrigo Werle, 1575 Linden Drive, Madison, WI 53706.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please download and print the &lt;a href=&#34;/img/2018 waterhemp seed collection/2018 WiscWeeds Waterhemp Seed Project.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SEED COLLECTION FORM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (PDF file) for information on how to collect the seeds and fill out the information necessary for the project. Please submit the form with the seed sample. Samples will only be included in the herbicide resistance screening if the information requested herein is provided by the farmer/agronomist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For questions, contact Dr. Rodrigo Werle via e-mail: &lt;strong&gt;rwerle@wisc.edu&lt;/strong&gt; or phone: &lt;strong&gt;608-262-7130&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thank the &lt;strong&gt;Wisconsin Soybean Marketing Board&lt;/strong&gt; for providing partial funding to support this project and also those submitting samples.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dicamba Use in Wisconsin Soybean Production - SURVEY</title>
      <link>/post/dicamba-use-in-wisconsin-soybean-production-survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/dicamba-use-in-wisconsin-soybean-production-survey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017 the Xtend soybean technology was completely launched in the United States (e.g., Environmental Protection Agency [EPA] approval of dicamba-tolerant seed trait and POST-emergence application of labeled dicamba formulations). Despite the great level of broadleaf weed control observed when dicamba was sprayed POST-emergence in Xtend soybeans, particularly of the troublesome weeds giant ragweed and waterhemp, off-target dicamba movement is still a concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have designed a short survey intended to investigate Wisconsin soybean farmers’ perceptions on dicamba use in Xtend soybeans. The survey comprises of four main sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Demographics of participants&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Outcomes from dicamba application in Xtend soybeans in 2017 and 2018&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Perceived dicamba injury in non-Xtend soybeans in Xtend 2017 and 2018&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Expected adoption of the technology in 2019 (assuming it remains available to US soybean farmers in 2019).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We truly appreciate the time of those answering the survey (even if you did not and don’t plan to adopt the technology, please take the time to answer; your feedback is of extreme importance). &lt;a href=&#34;https://aae.wisc.edu/pdmitchell/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Paul Mitchell&lt;/a&gt;, UW-Madison Extension Ag Economist, will assist with data summarization and analysis. Your answers will be kept confidential and the final results will be made available via Wisconsin Crop Manager this fall and presented during winter meetings across Wisconsin. The outcome of the survey will also be shared with the Wisconsin Department of Agriculture, Trade and Consumer Protection (DATCP) and US EPA. Moreover, results will help us decide research needs moving forward. We greatly appreciate your time and input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To participate in the survey, click &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.surveymonkey.com/r/J3XWFBX&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HERE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 dicamba survey/Wisc-QR_code_J3XWFBX.png&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Code&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reporting Dicamba-Injured Acreage in Wisconsin</title>
      <link>/post/reporting-dicamba-injured-acreage-in-wisconsin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/reporting-dicamba-injured-acreage-in-wisconsin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;https://agronomy.wisc.edu/rodrigo-werle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rodrigo Werle&lt;/a&gt; (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of July, the weather finally became conducive for POST-emergence herbicide applications in southern Wisconsin, including for dicamba application in Xtend (dicamba-tolerant) soybeans. Typically, injury from micro-rates of dicamba (via tank-contamination, particle and/or vapor drift) in susceptible crops tends to show at 10-14 days after the incident (see: &lt;a href=&#34;https://learningstore.uwex.edu/Assets/pdfs/A4161.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Soybean Injury From Dicamba A4161&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). Driving around the southern part of Wisconsin this past week, I have noticed a couple instances of dicamba injury in soybeans (I estimate less than 15 total injured acres).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/2018 dicamba injured acres/IMG_3914.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Figure 1.&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
Figure 1. Non-Xtend soybeans injured by dicamba in south-central Wisconsin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, &lt;a href=&#34;https://plantsciences.missouri.edu/faculty/bradley.cfm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Kevin Bradley&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Professor and State Extension Weed Scientist with the University of Missouri, kept track of the estimates of dicamba-injured soybean acreage across the United States (see: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ipm.missouri.edu/IPCM/2017/10/final_report_dicamba_injured_soybean/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Final Report on Dicamba-Injured Soybean Acres&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). This year, EPA (Environmental Protection Agency) and others have requested Dr. Bradley to continue the effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Bradley is in communication with the State Departments of Agriculture regarding official complaints but is also attempting to track dicamba-injured acres that are not being officially reported.
Thus, if you have noticed dicamba injury in your soybeans and/or other susceptible crops in Wisconsin, regardless on whether an official complaint was/will be filed with the Wisconsin Department of Agriculture, Trade and Consumer Protection (DATCAP), it would appreciated if you could send me an email (&lt;strong&gt;rwerle@wisc.edu&lt;/strong&gt;) describing the county, crop and number of dicamba-injured acres or plants (if referring to vegetable or ornamental crops). Pictures of the dicamba-injured crop would also be of extreme value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The information sent to me will be kept confidential and only used to update Dr. Bradley’s estimates and hopefully provide valuable information to decision-makers this fall to support their decision on whether to extend EPA registrations for Engenia, FeXapan and Xtendimax herbicides in Xtend soybeans.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
