<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Homes on Wisconsin Weed Science</title>
    <link>/home/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Homes on Wisconsin Weed Science</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2022 WiscWeeds</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/home/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>**WiscWeeds**</title>
      <link>/home/hero/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/home/hero/</guid>
      <description> Wisconsin Cropping Systems Weed Science Program
Weed Science Knowledge to Academics and Practitioners University of Wisconsin-Madison </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Us</title>
      <link>/home/aboutus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/home/aboutus/</guid>
      <description>Our Research and Extension Program (WiscWeeds) at the University of Wisconsin-Madison focuses on agroecologically-based approaches to address sustainable weed management in corn, soybeans and small grains in Wisconsin and beyond. Our program also focuses on weed management strategies that can help address herbicide resistance, protect water quality, enhance agroecosystems services and increase food security.   2021 WiscWeeds Team
  2020 WiscWeeds Team
  2019 WiscWeeds Team
 Tweets by WiscWeeds</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Latest Posts</title>
      <link>/home/posts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/home/posts/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reports</title>
      <link>/home/reports/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/home/reports/</guid>
      <description>2021 2021 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report (PDF)
2021 Corn Weed Control Trials (field images):
 Evaluation of Corn PRE-Emergence Herbicides (PDF)
 Weed Control and Crop Safety with EPOST Herbicide Applications (PDF)
 Shieldex Weed Control and Crop Safety (PDF)
 Reviton Burndown Programs in Corn (PDF)
 Restraint Weed Control and Crop Safety (PDF)
 POST and Sequential Weed Control with Maverick (PDF)
 Evaluation of Acuron GT in a Two-Pass System (PDF)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Coalition</title>
      <link>/home/coalition/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/home/coalition/</guid>
      <description>WiscWeeds Research Coalition - Ongoing Projects:
 Wisconsin Waterhemp Herbicide Resistance Project
 Response of Horseweed Accessions from Wisconsin and Northern Illinois to Spring Burndown Herbicides
 Weed Seed Movement Via Combines: 2019-2020 Case Study (PDF)
  
Given the widespread occurrence of herbicide-resistant weeds across Wisconsin Cropping Systems, the shortage of novel herbicide sites of action, and the socioeconomic and environmental challenges herbicide-resistant weeds bring to farming operations and communities, it’s time for our industry to come together and work towards a similar goal: to promote and hopefully achieve effective and sustainable weed control in crop production systems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>/home/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/home/publications/</guid>
      <description>32 Manuscripts &amp;amp; 1 Book Chapter
2020 33. Bagavathiannan, M., H. Beckie, G. Chantre, J.L. Gonzalez-Andjujar, R. Leon, P. Neve, S. Poggio, B.J. Schutte, G.J. Somerville, R. Werle., and R.C. Van Acker. Simulation models in weed ecology and management: structure, quantitative insights, and applications. Agronomy. 10(10), 1611.
32. Oliveira, M.C., O.A. Ospitan, K. Begcy, and R. Werle. 2020. Cover crops, hormones and herbicides: Priming integrated weed management strategies. Plant Science.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Links</title>
      <link>/home/links/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/home/links/</guid>
      <description>University of Wisconsin Extension Publications Pest Management in Wisconsin Field Crops UWEX Bulletin A3646 (PDF)
Wisconsin Herbicide Mode of Action Chart &amp;amp; Combination Products (PDF)
Herbicide Site of Action Key for Crop Injury Symptoms (PDF)
Soybean Injury from Dicamba UWEX Bulletin A4161 (PDF)
Herbicide rotational restrictions for cover and forage cropping systems (PDF)
University of Wisconsin Field Crops Programs Wisconsin Integrated Pest &amp;amp; Crop Management
Wisconsin Pesticide Applicator Program</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Team</title>
      <link>/home/team/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/home/team/</guid>
      <description>Rodrigo Werle (Assistant Professor &amp;amp; Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist):  Dr. Werle is an Assistant Professor and Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist at UW-Madison (from Sao Paulo, Brazil; BS from Sao Paulo State University, and MS and PhD from the University of Nebraska-Lincoln) leading the Research and Extension efforts of the WiscWeeds Program (See “Werle Bio” tab for additional information).
Nick Arneson (Weed Science Outreach Program Manager):  Nick is a Weed Science Outreach Program Manager at UW-Madison (from Omaha, Nebraska; BS and MS from the University of Nebraska-Lincoln) coordinating the WiscWeeds Lab activities, Extension programming, and circulation of outreach publications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/home/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/home/about/</guid>
      <description>Rodrigo Werle is an Assistant Professor and Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist in the Agronomy Department at UW-Madison. His research and extension program (WiscWeeds) focuses on agroecologically-based approaches to address sustainable weed management in corn, soybeans and small grains in Wisconsin and beyond. The program also focuses on weed management strategies that can help address herbicide resistance, protect water quality, enhance agroecosystems services and increase food security.
Rodrigo was born in a small farming community of Dutch immigrants in the state of São Paulo, in southeastern Brazil.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>/home/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/home/contact/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>