<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Wisconsin Weed Science</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Wisconsin Weed Science</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 WiscWeeds</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Survey: Wisconsin Soybean Herbicide Tolerance Trait Selection (2019 &amp; 2020)</title>
      <link>/post/survey-wisconsin-soybean-herbicide-tolerance-trait-selection-2019-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/survey-wisconsin-soybean-herbicide-tolerance-trait-selection-2019-2020/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist) and Shawn Conley (UW-Madison Extension Soybean and Small Grain Specialist)
Dr. Shawn Conley and team (Coolbean.info) recently released the 2019 yield data from their soybean variety trials conducted across the state of Wisconsin and concluded that no yield differences were observed across herbicide tolerance traits within nor across regions (Enlist E3, RR2 Xtend and LLGT27):

Herein, we would like to ask Wisconsin soybean producers and decision influencers to help us better understand herbicide tolerance trait and POST-emergence herbicide adoption in 2019 and their plans for 2020.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2019 WiscWeeds Research Coalition Combine Weed Seed Collection Project</title>
      <link>/post/2019-wiscweeds-research-coalition-combine-weed-seed-collection-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019-wiscweeds-research-coalition-combine-weed-seed-collection-project/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist), Nick Arneson (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist) and Dan Smith (UW NPM Southwest Wisconsin Regional Specialist)
Though native to Wisconsin, waterhemp has spread like wildfire and become a major problem in agricultural fields across the state in the past few years. In the fall of 2018, stakeholders submitted seed samples from 88 populations from across the state. UW-Madison Agronomy Grad Student Felipe Faleco has screened them for resistance to glyphosate and imazethapyr (Pursuit) and found that more than 90% of the waterhemp populations screened are resistant to both herbicides applied at their respective label rates (Roundup PowerMax at 22 fl oz/acre and Pursuit at 4 fl oz/acre).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wisconsin Marestail Herbicide Resistance Screening Project</title>
      <link>/post/wisconsin-marestail-herbicide-resistance-screening-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/wisconsin-marestail-herbicide-resistance-screening-project/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)
Marestail (aka horseweed) tends to be a troublesome weed species in no-till cropping systems across the Midwest and this year we received several inquiries regarding poor marestail control in parts of Wisconsin. Thus, we would like to invite Wisconsin farmers, crop consultants, educators and industry representatives that are dealing with this weed to collect seeds this fall from their row crop production fields and submit them to UW-Madison for herbicide resistance screenings (please collect marestail seed samples from fields with consistent infestation levels).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Puckered soybeans and uncontrolled pigweeds… The thoughts of a young weed scientist</title>
      <link>/post/puckered-soybeans-and-uncontrolled-pigweeds-the-thoughts-of-a-young-weed-scientist/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/puckered-soybeans-and-uncontrolled-pigweeds-the-thoughts-of-a-young-weed-scientist/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)
Last week I took a group of UW-Madison Graduate Students to participate in the 2019 North American Weed Science Contest in Seymour, IL (July 24-26, 2019). Driving through the Interstate (I-74/I-39), Highways and country side, the off-target herbicide movement (puckered/cupped soybeans) and waterhemp pressure across central IL were evident. Thus, I would like to use this IL scenario as my “case study” for this article.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can brand or generic herbicides be tank-mixed? Part-3 (we keep learning!) </title>
      <link>/post/can-brand-or-generic-herbicides-be-tank-mixed-part-3-we-keep-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/can-brand-or-generic-herbicides-be-tank-mixed-part-3-we-keep-learning/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)
Last week I released a blog post attempting to address the question regarding tank mixing safened S-metolachlor/metolachlor, atrazine and/or mesotrione-based products for weed control in corn (see: &amp;ldquo;Can brand or generic herbicides be tank-mixed? Part-2&amp;rdquo;).
The mesotrione products that I checked during my label search (i.e., Callisto, Explorer, Mesotrione 4SC and Meso Star) stated the following restriction: “DO NOT apply this product post-emergence in a tank mix with emulsifiable concentrate grass herbicides, unless specifically directed under one of the tank mix section of this label, or crop injury can occur”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can brand or generic herbicides be tank-mixed? Part-2</title>
      <link>/post/can-brand-or-generic-herbicides-be-tank-mixed-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/can-brand-or-generic-herbicides-be-tank-mixed-part-2/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)
Last month we released a blog post entitled “Can brand or generic herbicides be tank-mixed?&amp;rdquo; and in the first paragraph we wrote “This past week we received several questions regarding herbicide tank mixtures. One common question was whether brand and/or generic S-metolachlor/metolachlor, atrazine and/or mesotrione-based products could be tank-mixed”.
After speaking with industry colleagues, I learned that in the original blog post we described several important aspects to consider when developing a custom herbicide tank mix but did not actually answer if S-metolachlor/safened metolachlor, atrazine and/or mesotrione-based products could be tank-mixed; herein I will attempt to address this question.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Herbicide Rotation Restrictions Before Planting Industrial Hemp</title>
      <link>/post/herbicide-rotation-restrictions-before-planting-industrial-hemp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/herbicide-rotation-restrictions-before-planting-industrial-hemp/</guid>
      <description>By Nick Arneson (UW-Madison Weed Science Outreach Specialist), David Wang (UW-Madison Undergraduate Research Scholar) and Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)
With the growing interest in producing industrial hemp in Wisconsin and beyond, it is important to pay close attention to rotation interval restrictions when planting this crop in conventional production fields where herbicides are adopted. Though no synthetic herbicides are labeled for weed control in industrial hemp in the United States at this time, it’s important to keep in mind that herbicides sprayed in previous crops can have an impact on the industrial hemp crop establishment and development.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can brand or generic herbicides be tank-mixed? </title>
      <link>/post/can-brand-or-generic-herbicides-be-tank-mixed/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/can-brand-or-generic-herbicides-be-tank-mixed/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)
and Glenn Nice (UW-Madison Pesticide Applicator Training Program Manager)
With the onset of the spray season and concerns regarding waterhemp and other troublesome weed species, farmers and consultants are further diversifying and including herbicides with soil residual activity in their weed control programs. This past week we received several questions regarding herbicide tank mixtures. One common question was whether brand and/or generic s-metolachlor/metolachlor-, atrazine- and/or mesotrione-based products could be tank-mixed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are You PRE-pared for the Soybean (and Waterhemp) Growing Season?</title>
      <link>/post/are-you-pre-pared-for-the-soybean-growing-season/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/are-you-pre-pared-for-the-soybean-growing-season/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)
and Shawn Conley (UW-Madison Extension Soybean and Small Grain Specialist)
Spring has arrived rather quickly in Wisconsin and the planting season is right around the corner (or perhaps it has already started for some growers). Before getting their soybeans in the ground, farmers should make sure they have solid weed management plans for the growing season, particularly if waterhemp is present in their operations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strategies and Considerations for Termination of Cereal Rye Cover Crop</title>
      <link>/post/considerations-and-strategies-for-termination-of-cereal-rye-cover-crop/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/considerations-and-strategies-for-termination-of-cereal-rye-cover-crop/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist), Dan Smith (UW NPM Southwest Wisconsin Regional Specialist) and Shawn Conley (UW-Madison Extension Soybean and Small Grain Specialist)
*Adapted from original article written by Rodrigo Werle and Dan Smith, 2018.
Fall-planted cereal rye is increasingly used as a cover crop to protect the soil during winter and spring in corn and soybean cropping systems across the Midwest. Our 2018 survey indicated that 77% of Wisconsin farmers and Ag professionals are interested in cover crops.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2019 Wisconsin Regional Waterhemp Workshops</title>
      <link>/post/2019-wisconsin-regional-waterhemp-workshops/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019-wisconsin-regional-waterhemp-workshops/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)
According to our 2018 weed management SURVEY, waterhemp has become the most concerning weed species in field crop production in Wisconsin. Thus, we invite farmers and crop advisors to attend one of our Wisconsin Regional Waterhemp Workshops to be held in four locations across the state in March of 2019.
 These workshops are FREE with 3 CEUs (PM) available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2018 Wisconsin Weed Science Research Report</title>
      <link>/post/2018-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-wisconsin-weed-science-research-report/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist) and Ryan DeWerff (UW-Madison Weed Science Research Specialist)
The purpose of this report is to share the results of twenty-three corn and soybean herbicide evaluation research trials conducted by the WiscWeeds Program during the 2018 growing season. Information in this report does not constitute a recommendation or endorsement of any particular product or practice. Information in this report also does not replace any information presented on pesticide labels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the additional buffer requirements for dicamba applications in Xtend (dicamba-tolerant) crops</title>
      <link>/post/dicamba-buffer-requirements/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/dicamba-buffer-requirements/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)
On October 31, 2018 the United States Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) announced their decision to extend the registration of the dicamba products Engenia, Fexapan, and Xtendimax for use in dicamba-tolerant crops (Xtend technology) through December 20, 2020; however, additional label changes were made.
A particular change that has led to some questioning is the new 57-foot omnidirectional buffer requirement to protect federally listed threatened and endangered species and critical habitat in specific US counties.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Herbicide Resistance in Wisconsin: An Overview (December 2018)</title>
      <link>/post/herbicide-resistance-in-wisconsin-an-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/herbicide-resistance-in-wisconsin-an-overview/</guid>
      <description>Joseph Zimbric (UW-Madison Agronomy Graduate Student), David Stoltenberg (UW-Madison Agronomy Professor), Mark Renz (UW-Madison Extension Weed Scientist) and Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Weed Scientist)
20 Unique Cases of Herbicide Resistance in Wisconsin  20 unique cases (weed species by herbicide site of action) of herbicide resistance have been confirmed in Wisconsin, including 13 weed species with evolved resistance to one or more herbicide sites of action (Figure 1, Table 1).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2018 UW Waterhemp Challenge: Comparison of Soil Residual Soybean Herbicides</title>
      <link>/post/2018-uw-waterhemp-challenge-comparison-of-soil-residual-soybean-herbicides/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-uw-waterhemp-challenge-comparison-of-soil-residual-soybean-herbicides/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist), Dan Smith (UW NPM Southwest Wisconsin Regional Specialist) and Richard Proost (UW NPM Sr. Outreach Specialist)
Waterhemp management in soybeans was a challenge for several farmers in 2018. As we finalize harvesting our crops, it’s important to properly map the fields infested with waterhemp and start developing an effective management plan for 2019.
The use of PRE-emergence herbicides is a foundation for waterhemp control in soybeans.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Herbicide Site of Action Key for Crop Injury Symptoms</title>
      <link>/post/herbicide-site-of-action-key-for-crop-injury-symptoms/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/herbicide-site-of-action-key-for-crop-injury-symptoms/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist) and
Maxwel Oliveira (UW-Madison Weed Science Postdoctoral Research Associate)
With the widespread occurrence of herbicide-resistant weeds, corn and soybean farmers are having to diversify their herbicide programs to obtain adequate levels of weed control. The increased herbicide diversification increases the likelihood of crop injury due to carryover, misapplication, tank contamination, and/or drift.
To help you determine which herbicide(s) may be responsible for suspected injury on crops, this key uses the herbicide’s site of action (SoA) and respective Weed Science Society of America group number; herbicides within the same SoA can cause similar symptoms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wisconsin Waterhemp Herbicide Resistance Project</title>
      <link>/post/wisconsin-waterhemp-herbicide-resistance-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/wisconsin-waterhemp-herbicide-resistance-project/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)
According to our recent SURVEY, waterhemp has become the most concerning weed in row crop production in Wisconsin. Thus, we invite Wisconsin farmers and agronomists to collect waterhemp seeds this fall from their row crop production fields and submit them to UW-Madison for herbicide resistance screenings (we ask farmers to collect samples from only one of their fields; preferably the one with the most troublesome infestation level).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dicamba Use in Wisconsin Soybean Production - SURVEY</title>
      <link>/post/dicamba-use-in-wisconsin-soybean-production-survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/dicamba-use-in-wisconsin-soybean-production-survey/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)
In 2017 the Xtend soybean technology was completely launched in the United States (e.g., Environmental Protection Agency [EPA] approval of dicamba-tolerant seed trait and POST-emergence application of labeled dicamba formulations). Despite the great level of broadleaf weed control observed when dicamba was sprayed POST-emergence in Xtend soybeans, particularly of the troublesome weeds giant ragweed and waterhemp, off-target dicamba movement is still a concern.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reporting Dicamba-Injured Acreage in Wisconsin</title>
      <link>/post/reporting-dicamba-injured-acreage-in-wisconsin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/reporting-dicamba-injured-acreage-in-wisconsin/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)
At the beginning of July, the weather finally became conducive for POST-emergence herbicide applications in southern Wisconsin, including for dicamba application in Xtend (dicamba-tolerant) soybeans. Typically, injury from micro-rates of dicamba (via tank-contamination, particle and/or vapor drift) in susceptible crops tends to show at 10-14 days after the incident (see: Soybean Injury From Dicamba A4161). Driving around the southern part of Wisconsin this past week, I have noticed a couple instances of dicamba injury in soybeans (I estimate less than 15 total injured acres).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Application window for most soybean herbicides coming close to an end</title>
      <link>/post/application-window-for-most-soybean-herbicides-coming-close-to-an-end/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/application-window-for-most-soybean-herbicides-coming-close-to-an-end/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)
Excessive and constant rainfall through the season thus far across southern Wisconsin has challenged timely herbicide applications in our experimental plots. If not raining, the wind was often blowing or the soil was too wet to even backpack spray. After spending several years in Nebraska, I learned that one can’t complain about rain, but come on! Still, we have managed to get most of our herbicide treatments out (thanks to a dedicated and hard-working research team that is literally not afraid of getting some mud on their boots!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Palmer amaranth is now a prohibited noxious weed seed in Wisconsin, but what does it look like?</title>
      <link>/post/palmer-amaranth-is-now-a-prohibited-noxious-weed-seed-in-wisconsin-but-what-does-it-look-like/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/palmer-amaranth-is-now-a-prohibited-noxious-weed-seed-in-wisconsin-but-what-does-it-look-like/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)
Under a new emergency rule, Palmer amaranth has been labeled as a prohibited noxious weed seed in Wisconsin. Given Palmer amaranth&amp;rsquo;s aggressive nature, this is a worthwhile and necessary attempt to keep this troublesome weed species out of the state. For more details, see DATCP article: “Keep an Eye Out for Palmer Amaranth, DATCP Cautions”.
Palmer amaranth’s late and extended emergence window throughout the growing season and vigorous growth rate (up to 2 inches per day under ideal conditions) make control in row crops very difficult.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waterhemp management in soybeans</title>
      <link>/post/waterhemp-management-in-soybeans/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/waterhemp-management-in-soybeans/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)
According to our recent SURVEY, waterhemp has become the most concerning weed in row crop production in Wisconsin. Adding to that challenge, glyphosate-resistant waterhemp populations have been confirmed in 25 Wisconsin counties (see map below). Furthermore, PPO-resistant waterhemp has been confirmed in 4 counties (Iowa, Monroe, Saint Croix, and Pierce). Resistance to ALS-inhibiting herbicides is widespread across the Midwest but has not been fully investigated in Wisconsin.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strategies for Late Termination of Cereal Rye Cover Crop</title>
      <link>/post/strategies-for-late-termination-of-cereal-rye-cover-crop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/strategies-for-late-termination-of-cereal-rye-cover-crop/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist) and Dan Smith (UW NPM Southwest Wisconsin Regional Specialist)
Fall-planted cereal rye is increasingly used as a cover crop to protect the soil during winter and spring in corn and soybean cropping systems across the Midwest. Our recent survey indicated that 77% of Wisconsin farmers and Ag professionals are interested in cover crops.
Fall-planted cereal rye is growing rapidly in southern Wisconsin and it’s important to have a termination plan in mind prior to crop establishment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are you PRE-emergence ready for soybean planting?</title>
      <link>/post/are-you-pre-emergence-ready-for-soybean-planting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/are-you-pre-emergence-ready-for-soybean-planting/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist)
and Shawn Conley (UW-Madison Extension Soybean and Small Grain Specialist)
Spring has finally arrived in Wisconsin and so has the planting season. Before getting your soybeans in the ground, make sure you have plans for your PRE-emergence herbicide program. According to our recent SURVEY, several Wisconsin soybean fields get only treated with a one-pass POST-emergence herbicide program. Because of the spread of weed species resistant to glyphosate and/or other POST-emergence herbicides (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geographic Restrictions for Corn and Soybean PRE-emergence Herbicides in Wisconsin</title>
      <link>/post/geographic-restrictions-for-corn-and-soybean-pre-emergence-herbicides-in-wisconsin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/geographic-restrictions-for-corn-and-soybean-pre-emergence-herbicides-in-wisconsin/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist) and
Richard Proost (UW NPM Sr. Outreach Specialist)
PRE-emergence herbicides are the foundation for good weed control in corn and soybeans, particularly with the spread of herbicide-resistant weeds. The use of some PRE-emergence herbicides is limited to certain regions or counties in Wisconsin. Prior to selecting a herbicide for your weed management program, make sure the same is approved for use in your region by the Department of Agriculture, Trade and Consumer Protection (DATCP).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2018 Wisconsin Cropping Systems Weed Science Survey - Where are we at?</title>
      <link>/post/2018-wisconsin-cropping-systems-weed-science-survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-wisconsin-cropping-systems-weed-science-survey/</guid>
      <description>by Rodrigo Werle (UW-Madison Extension Cropping Systems Weed Scientist) and
Maxwel Oliveira (UW-Madison Weed Science Postdoctoral Research Associate)
Introduction The objective of our survey was to evaluate the main weed species and management strategies adopted in Wisconsin cropping systems, particularly in corn and soybeans. The survey was conducted this winter during the 2018 Wisconsin Agronomy Update Meetings, held across the state. A total of 286 respondents, representing 54 counties, completed the survey.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcoming New WiscWeeds Team Members</title>
      <link>/post/welcoming-new-wiscweeds-team-members/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/welcoming-new-wiscweeds-team-members/</guid>
      <description>I am excited to introduce and welcome the new members of the Wisconsin Cropping Systems Weed Science (WiscWeeds) Program: Maxwel Oliveira, Ryan DeWerff, Sarah Striegel, Victor Ribeiro and Nikola Arsenijevic.  Dr. Maxwel Coura Oliveira (Postdoctoral Research Associate)
Maxwel started at the University of Wisconsin-Madison as a Weed Science Postdoctoral Research Associate in January 2018 in Dr. Werle’s program. Maxwel was born in the state of Minas Gerais, Brazil. He earned his B.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>